<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The legitimacy of Amicia, daughter of Hvgh Cyvelick, Earl of Chester, clearly proved with full answers to all objections that have at any time been made against the same / by Sir Thomas Mainwaring ...</title>
            <author>Mainwaring, Thomas, Sir, 1623-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 221KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51545</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12618212</idno>
  <idno type="VID">64436</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240988959</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M301</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21678</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12618212</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51545)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64436)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 673:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The legitimacy of Amicia, daughter of Hvgh Cyvelick, Earl of Chester, clearly proved with full answers to all objections that have at any time been made against the same / by Sir Thomas Mainwaring ...</title>
                  <author>Mainwaring, Thomas, Sir, 1623-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 171 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Lowndes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Mainwaring, Amicia.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Leycester, Peter, --  Sir, 1614-1678. --  Historical antiquities.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64436:1"/>
            <p>THE LEGITIMACY OF AMICIA, DAUGHTER OF <hi>HƲGH CYVELIOK</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> CLEARLY PROVED.</p>
            <p>With Full ANSWERS to all OBjECTIONS that have at any time been made against the same.</p>
            <p>By Sir <hi>THOMAS MAINWARING</hi> of <hi>Peover</hi> in <hi>Cheshire,</hi> Baronet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Lowndes</hi> over against the <hi>Exeter Exchange</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64436:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64436:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW unwilling I was to have enter'd into a publique Debate concerning <hi>Amicia,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> I think doth clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in my Epistle to Sir <hi>Peter Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester,</hi> before my Defence of the said <hi>Amicia,</hi> wherein I told him, That if he would have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, to have delivered what he did conceit concerning her, as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty onely, (as he had done that of <hi>Roger</hi> Son of the said Earl <hi>Hugh</hi>) that he knew I would have
<pb facs="tcp:64436:3"/>rested satisfied with the Judgment of those many knowing and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned Persons, that had dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented from him therein, and would never have given him and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the trouble of any lines of mine.</p>
            <p>Though Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> would not grant me this request, yet of his own accord, he proposed at the first, (as appears by several Letters of his to me, which I yet have, and were all written with his own hand) that what I had objected against his Reasons, should be print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Body of his <hi>Historical Antiquities;</hi> But afterwards alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his mind therein, he offer'd to have it put into the <hi>Addenda,</hi> at the end of his said Book; and he withal did declare, that he intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to reply, but if he did, he would reply but once, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:64436:3"/>sent me a short Reply, which he there said was the last that he would write concerning the same.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding this, he did again change his mind, and was unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that what I had written, should be printed with his <hi>Addenda,</hi> at the end of his said <hi>Historical Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> and instead of Printing the short Reply, which he sent to me, he sent for the said Reply back, and did Print an Answer to my <hi>Defence of</hi> Amicia, which was larger than what Sir <hi>Peter</hi> and I had then both of us published upon that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; for, as appears in my <hi>Defence of Amicia,</hi> Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s words, and what I did write, were comprehended in 75 pages, whereas his Answer alone did contain 79. And in that Answer of his, which was dated <hi>May</hi> 15. 1673. he did also in Print affirm, that he had taken leave
<pb facs="tcp:64436:4"/>for ever of that Controversie.</p>
            <p>But for all these Declarations both under his Hand, and in Print, he put out another little Book, which he also called <hi>Addenda,</hi> or some things to be added in his said Answer dated <hi>November</hi> 6. 1673. Then he put out two Books toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the one called, <hi>A Reply to my Book,</hi> Entituled, <hi>An Answer to Sir</hi> Peter Leicester<hi>'s Addenda,</hi> Dated <hi>April</hi> 14. 1674. and the other he was pleased to call, <hi>My Law Cases Mistaken,</hi> and was dated the first of <hi>May</hi> 1674. And afterwards he Printed another, which he called, <hi>An Advertisement to the Reader,</hi> and was dated on the third day of <hi>March</hi> following; but because I found very little of weight in this last Book, I did not then publish any Answer to the same.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64436:4"/>
            <p>But notwithstanding this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of mine, Sir <hi>Peter</hi> did again put out at once, three seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Books, the first whereof he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his <hi>Second Reply,</hi> which was dated <hi>May</hi> 28. 1675. the second he called <hi>Peroratio ad Lectorem,</hi> and it was dated <hi>December</hi> 17. 1675. and the third he called, <hi>The Case of</hi> Amicia <hi>truly Stated;</hi> which, though Printed and Paged after his <hi>Peroratio,</hi> was dated before it, <hi>viz. August</hi> the 5th. 1675. the reason whereof an intelligent Reader I suppose will easily discern; and in all these three Books, as also in his <hi>Advertisement to the Reader,</hi> there was little if any thing that was new, except two Records.</p>
            <p>In the latter end of his said <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roratio,</hi> he said, <hi>He had done if I had done;</hi> which I looked upon to be as much as if he had said he
<pb facs="tcp:64436:5"/>would never have done, so long as I did write; upon which I was put to a stand, and did not well know what to do; for as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider'd on the one hand, that I had the honour to be her Heir Male, and that not only most of the great Families in <hi>England,</hi> but also, <hi>Absit verbo Invidia,</hi> our most graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sovereign, and many other great Kings and Queens did come out of her Loins, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was bound in duty to use my Endeavours to clear her here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; so on the other hand, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that if I did continue Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I should perpetuate the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie, which I was wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to do, and did therefore resolve
<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>My Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition,</hi> p. 20.</note>, as far as in me did lie, that nothing more of mine should be published in the life-time of
<pb facs="tcp:64436:5"/>Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> whethersoever he did out-live me or not. And I do assure the Reader, that I did not make this delay, upon any fear of what could reasonably be supposed could have been by him replyed; for as I have answered all those nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Arguments, which he hath hitherto made use of, so I see no cause to suspect, that he could have discovered any new one, which would have been more strong than those formerly brought; and though he be dead, yet all learned persons can easily judge whether what is here said be substantial, or not; and I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess I do not write this, out of any conceit that it is any disgrace to descend of a Bastard, but only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I conceive that my Grandmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is very much wronged herein; for I believe there is scarcely any person whatsoever, (if any at all) but
<pb facs="tcp:64436:6"/>it would appear that he did descend of some one that was Illegitimate, if the descent of all those persons was known, with whom his Family had match'd, and of all others of whom he did collaterally descend.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>PEOVER,</hi>
                  <date>Dec. 24. 1678.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>T. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64436:6"/>
            <head>THE LEGITIMACY OF AMICIA, Daughter of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> Clearly Proved.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I come to the Reasons which have been alledged either for or against <hi>Amicia,</hi> I hold it necessary to recite these three Deeds follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that those who read them, and the Reasons on both sides, may the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the full state of the Case.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64436:7"/>
               <div type="deed">
                  <p>
                     <hi>HƲgo Comes Cestr' Constabular' Dapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer' &amp; omnibus Baronibus suis &amp; Ʋniversis Ballivis &amp; hominibus suis Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis &amp; Anglicis tam praesentibus quam futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris salutem. Sciatis me dedisse &amp; conces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisse &amp; hac praesenti Karta mea confirmasse Radulpho de Menilwarin cum Amicia Filia mea in libero maritagio servitium Gilib. filii Rogeri, scilicet, servitium trium Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum faciendo michi servitium duorum Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litum ille &amp; haeredes sui michi &amp; haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus meis, quare volo &amp; firmiter praecipio ut nullus super hoc eum vel haeredes suos vexet, vel amplius quam servitium duorum Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum de hoc praedicto tenemento requirat. Teste R. Abbate Cestr' Bertreia Comitissa Cestr' Sim. Thuschet, Rogero de Livet, Gilib. filio Pigot. Rob. fratre suo, Frumb. de Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford. Willielmo de Meinilwarin, Rob. filio Ham. Bettr. Cam. Rob. de Meinilwarin, Ran. de Lee, Rad. Clerico, Petro Clerico qui hanc Kartam fecit &amp; multis aliis apud Lee.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="deed">
                  <p>
                     <hi>RAdulfus de Meidnilwar' omnibus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentibus &amp; futuris ad quos praesens scriptum pervenerit salutem. Sciatis me dedisse &amp; concessisse &amp; praesenti carta mea
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64436:7"/>confirmasse Henrico de Alditelegh in libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum maritagium cum Bertrea filia mea Smelewde cum pertinentiis &amp; Senellest': Cum pertinent. &amp; dimid' Pichemere cum pertinentiis suis &amp; i. Marc. de redditu an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuo in Civitate Cestr' de terra quae fuit Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun. quam Robert' filius Ermwi de me tenuit illi &amp; haeredibus suis qui de dicta Bertrea filia mea pervenient habend' &amp; tenend' de me &amp; haeredibus meis in feodo &amp; haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate libere &amp; quiete plene &amp; pacifice in bosco &amp; plano in pratis &amp; pascuis in aquis viis &amp; in semitis in vivariis &amp; in molendinis &amp; in omnibus locis &amp; libertatibus praedictis ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris pertinentibus sicut liberum maritagium melius &amp; liberius teneri pot': Et ego &amp; haeredes mei illi &amp; dictis haeredibus suis contra omnes homines dictas terras Warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizabimus. Test' Ran' Com' Cestr'. Hug' Com' Ʋltoniae, Phil' de Orreby tunc Justic. Cestr. Joh. de Ptell' Hug. Malebiss. Ric. de Vern. Ran. de Meidnilwar. Clerico. Lidulf. de Tuaml' Rob. de Periis, Ric. de Kingesl. Norm. Pant. Tho. de Orreby, Alured. de Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linni. Pet. Chan. Gg. de Aldith. Ric. de Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest. Clerico &amp; multis Aliis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64436:8"/>
               </div>
               <div type="deed">
                  <p>
                     <hi>OMnibus hanc Cartam visuris vel au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dituris Rogerus de Menilwarin aeternam in Domino salutem. Noverit Ʋniversitas vestra me pro salute animae Domini Ranulphi quondam Comitis Cestriae &amp; Lincolniae Avunculi mei &amp; pro salute animae meae &amp; animarum antecessorum &amp; successorum meorum dedisse concessisse &amp; hac praesenti Carta mea confirmasse Deo &amp; Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae Mariae &amp; Abbati &amp; Monachis de Deula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cresse &amp; eorum Grangie de Biveleg. in libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram puram &amp; perpetuam Elemosynam libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram communam in bosco meo de Pevere, sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet, Ʋt accipiant de eodem bosco husbot &amp; haybot rationabiliter per visum alicujus forestariorum meorum quantum necesse ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerint, sine impedimento aeriarum nisorum meorum ubicunque nidificaverint, Praeterea dedi eis liberam pessionem &amp; quietam de pannagio quinquaginta porcis quandocunque voluerint in praedicto nemore meo de Pevere, pro hac autem donatione &amp; concessione mea, Ego Rogerus praedictus &amp; haeredes mei de praedictis Abbate &amp; Monachis de Deula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cresse nichil exigere poterimus, nisi oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; suffragia ordinis Cisterciensis. Ego vero &amp; haeredes mei sepedictam donationem &amp; concessionem meam sepedictis Abbati &amp;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64436:8"/>Monachis &amp; Grangie de Biveleg contra omnes gentes Warrantizabimus imperpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Et ut haec donatio mea rata &amp; incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussa in sempiternum perseveret eam praesen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Cartae testimonio &amp; Sigilli mei impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sione roboravi. Hiis testibus Willielmo de Menilwarin. Willielmo Capellano de Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. Ricardo de Moston. Bened. de Caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dray, Johanne de Motlawe, Willielmo de Pevere, Hugone de Weloc. Nicolao de Were<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, Gilberto Gekell, &amp; aliis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Now that the said <hi>Amicia</hi> was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly legitimate, will be proved by these following Arguments or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; </p>
               <div type="reason">
                  <p n="1"> I. First, Because the said <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> as appears by the first of the said Deeds, did give unto <hi>Ralph de Menil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warin</hi> or <hi>Mainwaring</hi> with his daughter <hi>Amicia</hi> in free Marriage the service of <hi>Gilbert</hi> son of <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ger, viz.</hi> the service of three Knights Fees, doing to the said <hi>Hugh</hi> and his Heirs the service of two Knights Fees; But our Common Law neither now, nor at any time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eretofore allowing that Lands or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices could be given <hi>In libero Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio,</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:64436:9"/>with any person that was not of the blood of the Donor, as you may see <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton,</hi> Fol. 21. b. Consequently neither Lands nor Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices could be so given with a Bastard daughter by the reputed Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause a Bastard is not <hi>de sanguine Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris,</hi> as you may find <hi>Dyer,</hi> Fol. 374. b. And therefore it necessarily follows, because the said <hi>Amicia</hi> had Services given with her in Franke Marriage by her said Father, that the said <hi>Amicia</hi> was not a Bastard.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="reason">
                  <p n="2"> II. Secondly, If the Reader please to observe, how in the first Deed, <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi>'s Countess is a Witness to the giving of those Services in Free Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with <hi>Amicia</hi> daughter to the said Earl <hi>Hugh;</hi> As also how in the second Deed, <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi>'s daughter is called <hi>Bertred</hi> after the Countess, which probably, according to Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s opinion under his own hand in <hi>April,</hi> 1664. was occasioned by the said Countess being Godmother to the said <hi>Bertred Mainwaring;</hi> As als<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> how <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> was a Witness to what was given with the said <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64436:9"/>Mainwaring</hi> in Free Marriage to <hi>Henry de Alditelegh,</hi> who was Great Grandfather to the Famous <hi>James Audley</hi> who warred in <hi>France;</hi> As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so how, as appears in Sir <hi>William Dug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi>'s Antiquities of <hi>Warwickshire,</hi> Pag. 88. <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> was with the said Earl at <hi>Coventry,</hi> and a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to his Charter to the Burgesses there; As also how <hi>Roger de Meinwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> and <hi>Henry de Alditeley,</hi> who mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried his Sister. <hi>Monast. Anglic. part</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 891. are Witnesses to the Deeds of <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> and <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln,</hi> concerning his Abby of <hi>Deula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres;</hi> As also how the said <hi>Roger Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring,</hi> as appears by the said third Deed, did give some Priviledges to the said Abby of <hi>Deulacres;</hi> As also how <hi>Ralph Menilwarin</hi> or <hi>Mainwaring,</hi> as appears by Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s Histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Antiquities, <hi>part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 130, 131, 139, 143, and 144. is a Witness to one Deed of <hi>Hugh Cyvelioks,</hi> and to three other Deeds of the said Earl <hi>Randle</hi> (who in some of them is also stiled Duke of <hi>Britain,</hi> and Earl of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond;</hi>) As also how the said <hi>Ralph de Meidinwarin</hi> or <hi>Mainwaring,</hi> is a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64436:10"/>Witness to <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi>'s Deed of Confirmation to the Priory of <hi>Calc</hi> in <hi>Darbishire,</hi> as you may see in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions to the Second Tome of <hi>Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticon. Anglic.</hi> Printed with the Third Tome, <hi>pag.</hi> 97. I shall leave it (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any more words) to the Reader to judge, whether these Circumstances be not such, as do shew a more great and constant Intimacy, betwixt the said two Families, than probably would have been, if <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> had married but an illegitimate daughter of the said Earl.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="reason">
                  <p n="3"> III. Thirdly, Because as you may see in the said third Deed, <hi>Roger Menilwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> or <hi>Mainwaring,</hi> Son of the said <hi>Ralph</hi> and <hi>Amicia,</hi> doth call <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> and <hi>Lincolne</hi> his Uncle, which if <hi>Amicia</hi> had been illegitimate he would not have presumed to have done; for though it be true, that <hi>Bastards</hi> in <hi>Histories</hi> and <hi>Records</hi> are many times called, Cosin, Brother, Uncle, Son, and Daughter, yet that is done where the persons came to be very Great, as <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> did, or else they are so called by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64436:10"/>those that write the Histories of them, or else are so termed by their Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who out of their humility, did condescend so to stile them upon or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary occasions, though it were not their due; But I believe it will be very hard to find one that can cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be proved a <hi>Bastard,</hi> or the Son of a <hi>Bastard,</hi> who doth in a Deed made by himself, call so great a person as the Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> was, his Brother or Uncle, unless he came to be a very great person himself, so that this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is also of very great force and weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="reason">
                  <p n="4">IV. Fourthly, I do conceive, that <hi>Hugh Cyveliocks</hi> passing of services in the first Deed to the said <hi>Amicia,</hi> and using these words, <hi>Cum filia mea,</hi> doth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely prove that she was a lawful Child, and by consequence by a former Wife; for if you take notice of what Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> writes in his <hi>Glos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary,</hi> on the word <hi>Bastardus,</hi> you will find him quoting <hi>Constum. du Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Artic.</hi> 77. <hi>in Annot.</hi> Thus, <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties enim agitur de honore vel commodo filiorum, appellatione filiorum non com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenduntur
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64436:11"/>Bastardi,</hi> I suppose there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this case, <hi>Amice</hi> would not have been stiled <hi>Filia,</hi> as she is in the said Deed, unless she had been a Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Child.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="reason">
                  <p n="5">Fifthly, I desire the Reader well to observe these two Deeds following, the first whereof doth belong to <hi>Henry Mainwaring</hi> of <hi>Kermincham,</hi> in <hi>Cheshire</hi> Esquire, and the other to <hi>Thomas Ravenscroft</hi> of <hi>Bretton</hi> in the County of <hi>Flint,</hi> Esquire, the words whereof do here follow, as they were copied out several years since from the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals, by Sir <hi>William Dugdale</hi> Knight.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="deed">
                              <p>
                                 <hi>SCiant &amp; omnes praesentes quam futuri quod ego Robertus Dominus Moaldie &amp; senescallus Cestrie, concessi &amp; praesenti Karta confirmavi domui sce' Werburge Virginis in Cestria &amp; Monachis ibidem Deo servientibus totam Villam de Goostree plene &amp; integre cum omnibus pertin' suis in puram &amp; perpetuam elemosynam pro salute anime mee &amp; animarum praedeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorum meorum, liberam quietam &amp; solutam ab omni seculari servicio &amp; omni seculari exactione. Ita quod in eadem Villa de
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64436:11"/>Goostree nihil ad opus meum vel haeredum meorum retinui praeter elemosynam &amp; ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones &amp; tantam libertatem in ipsa eadem Villa praedicte domui &amp; praedictis Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chis concessi quod in posterum nullus hoere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum meorum quicquid libertatis superad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere possit. Et ut hec mea concessio rata &amp; inconcussa permaneat imperpetuum eam sigilli mei appositione roboravi. Hiis testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Rad' de Menilwar' tunc Justiciar' Ham' de Masci Gwar de Vern' Rad' fil' Sim' Pho' de Orreby. Sim' de Thurschet Rog' de Menilwar' Willielmo de Venables. Toma Dispensatore Rob' fil' Picot' Petro' Cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co Com' Ricardo de Vern' Rob' de Menil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>war' Brito Paulum Patr' de Moberl' Liulf' de Twamlow. Peers de Sur' Ran' de Praers' Ricardo de Kingsl' Jo' de sancta Maria, &amp; multis aliis.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="deed">
                              <p>
                                 <hi>SCiant praesentes &amp; futuri quod ego Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de Boidele dedi &amp; quiet' clam' fratri meo Willielmo de Boidele &amp; haered' suis Doccliston in feod' &amp; Dominicis cum omnibus pertin' infra Limam. Tenend' &amp; habend de Domino meo Raul' Com' Cestr' &amp; hered' suis faciend' servicium de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict' terr' sc. De quatuor feod' &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid' praenominato Domino meo Raul' Com'
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64436:12"/>Cestr' &amp; haered' suis. Et ego vero Alanus de Boidele &amp; hered' mei praedict' terr' cum omnibus pertin' praenominato Williel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo de Boidele &amp; haered' suis contra omnes homines &amp; feminas cum pertin' waranti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zab. Et quia volo quod hec mea donatio &amp; quiet' clam' stabilis &amp; inconcussa &amp; rat' permaneat praesenti scripto sigillum meum apposui. His test' Domino Raul' Comite Cestr' domino Rad' de Mainwaringhe tunc Justiciar' Cestr' domino Roberto de Monte alto, Domino Hug' Dispensar' Domino Ham' sen' de Mascy, Domino Warino de Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nun, Domino Williemo de Venables. Toma fil' Willielmi do Goulborn, Petro de Beke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Rob' tunc persona Gropenhale scriptor' hujus scripti &amp; multis aliis.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>I shall also desire the Reader to take notice of what Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> hath observed in his <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> p. 160. how that Earl <hi>Randle de Gernoniis</hi> (as doth appear by the Charter there mentioned) did give the Office of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable of <hi>Cheshire,</hi> in Fee to <hi>Eustace,</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Halton,</hi> and his Heirs; and did constitute the said <hi>Eustace</hi> (to use the words of the said Charter) <hi>Haereditarie Constabularium &amp; Supremum conciliarium
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64436:12"/>post me &amp; super omnes optimates &amp; Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rones totius terrae meae.</hi> As also p. 161. how the Baron <hi>de Montealto</hi> or <hi>Moald,</hi> being Dapifer, Seneschal, or Steward of <hi>Cheshire</hi> in Fee, had the second Place, which is also confirmed by several Deeds, mentioned in Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s Book, <hi>p.</hi> 129. 130. 139. 144 and 162. In all which, the Constable and Steward are named be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Justice of <hi>Chester,</hi> and all the other Barons; which being so, it will be difficult to give a Reason (if <hi>Amicia</hi> was but a base Daughter) why Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> in the Deed abovesaid of <hi>Alan de Boidele,</hi> is named as a Witness next to the Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> and before Sir <hi>Robert de Monte-alto</hi> or <hi>Moald,</hi> Steward of <hi>Cheshire,</hi> and so many of the other Barons; as also in a Deed mentioned in in Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s Book, <hi>p.</hi> 139. why the said <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> is named next to the Countess of <hi>Chester,</hi> and before <hi>Roger</hi> Constable of <hi>Cheshire;</hi> as also why in a Deed in the 143 page of the said Book, the said <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> is again na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med next to the said Countess, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ralph,</hi> the Steward of <hi>Cheshire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if <hi>Amicia</hi> was a Legitimate Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64436:13"/>the reason thereof will be apparent: For though it be true, that the Husband cannot be Ennobled by the Marriage of his Wife, yet the Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> being a Count <hi>Palatine,</hi> and one that is confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by Sir <hi>Peter Leicester,</hi> p. 152 and 159. to have Royal Authority within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and not unfitly to be stiled a <hi>Petty King,</hi> having under him his Constable of <hi>Cheshire</hi> in Fee, in imitation of the Lord High Constable of <hi>England,</hi> and his Steward of <hi>Cheshire</hi> in Fee, after the example of the Lord High Steward of <hi>England;</hi> and his Noblemen about him, in imitation of the Barons of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; as also his Chamberlain, who sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth the Place of Chancellor, and his Justices of <hi>Chester</hi> (who have like pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the Judges of the Courts of <hi>Kings Bench</hi> and <hi>Common Pleas</hi>) as also a Baron of the Exchequer, a Sheriff, and other Officers proportionable to those of the Crown: It is no wonder at all, if these great Persons did voluntarily give Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedence to Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> during his life, in regard he had married a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Daughter to one of the said Earls.</p>
                  <p>Add hereunto, that when Earl <hi>Hugh
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64436:13"/>Cyvelioke,</hi> did by his Charter mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Sir <hi>Peter Leicester,</hi> p. 131. acquit the Abbot and Monks of <hi>Stanlaw,</hi> of some Toll in <hi>Chester</hi> (which could be but a little before the said Earls death, because the said Earl died in the year 1181. And the Abby of <hi>Stanlaw,</hi> as is confessed by Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> p. 267. was foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded but in the year 1178.) The said Earl in his said Charter (contrary to all former Precedents, which I have seen) doth name the Justice of <hi>Chester</hi> before both the Constable of <hi>Cheshire,</hi> and Steward of <hi>Cheshire;</hi> and the reason there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I suppose to be, because the said <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> who was Son-in-Law to the said Earl, was then Justice of <hi>Chester,</hi> as he also was some years in the life time of <hi>Randle Blundevill;</hi> though the said <hi>Ralph,</hi> as appears by his aforesaid Deed made to <hi>Henry de Alditelegh,</hi> did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards part with the said Office, <hi>Philip de Orreby</hi> being Justice of <hi>Chester,</hi> when the said <hi>Philip</hi> was a Witness to the said Deed.</p>
                  <p>Now this Preeminence could not be given to the said <hi>Ralph,</hi> because he was Justice of <hi>Chester</hi> (that Office being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64436:14"/>the Offices of Constable and Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, as appears before) but because of the Relation of the said <hi>Ralph</hi> to the said Earl, and certainly such great respect would not have been shewed him, upon that account, if his Wife had been an ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate Child.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="reason">
                  <p n="6">VI. Sixthly, Because there was such a vast disproportion of years, betwixt <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> and his Wife <hi>Bertred,</hi> that it cannot be in reason imagined, that the said Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> being so great a person, should stay unmarried, until his said Wife <hi>Bertred</hi> was Marriage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; for the said <hi>Bertred</hi> was but Twenty four years of age in the year 1181. when the said Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> dyed, as appears, <hi>Rot. de Dominabus, pueris,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>In Scacc. penes Remem. R. Sub Tit. Line. Rot.</hi> 1. by which it appears, that the said <hi>Bertred</hi> was born in the year 1157. But the said Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> as you may find in the Third Part of Sir <hi>William Dugdale</hi>'s <hi>Monasticon Anglica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> Pag. 226. did, together with his Mother <hi>Maude,</hi> give <hi>Stivinghale,</hi> (which was not <hi>Stivinghale,</hi> vulgò <hi>Stishall, in Com. Stafford,</hi> as Sir <hi>Peter Leicester,</hi> in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64436:14"/>the 86 Page of his first Reply tells us, but it was <hi>Stivinghale,</hi> which is a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Coventry,</hi> as you may see in Sir <hi>William Dugdale</hi>'s Antiquities of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wickshire,</hi> Pag. 88, 128, 129. and in Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s Historical Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Pag. 129.) And besides the said <hi>Stivinghale,</hi> the said Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> and his Mother <hi>Maude,</hi> did give a Mill next to the Park, and some other Grounds, to <hi>Walter Durdent</hi> Bishop of <hi>Chester,</hi> and his Successors, to which Deed <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stace</hi> the Constable was Witness; Now the said Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> being not in a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to seal a Deed, until he was One and twenty years of age, and the said <hi>Eustace</hi> being slain (as appears by Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s Historical Antiquities, Pag. 266.) in a Battel against the <hi>Welsh</hi> in the said year 1157. If the said Deed was made immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the said <hi>Eustace</hi> was slain, the said <hi>Hugh</hi> must needs be at the least One and twenty years older than his Wife <hi>Bertred;</hi> But, it is very likely that Deed was made some years before, <hi>viz.</hi> immediately upon the death of <hi>Randle de Gernoniis;</hi> For the said <hi>Randle</hi> died Excommunicate in the year 1153. as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64436:15"/>you may see in Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s Histor. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, Pag. 129. and <hi>Stivinghale,</hi> and those other Lands were given for his Absolution, and the health of his Soul.</p>
                  <p>But, besides what is here proved, if you look at the latter end of the <hi>Welsh Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> put out by Dr. <hi>Powel</hi> 1584, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately before the Table, you will see that the 16 line of the 197 Page of the said <hi>Welsh History</hi> is misprinted, and that in the said Page it should have been Printed thus: <hi>About the same time</hi> Hugh, <hi>Son to the Earl of</hi> Chester, <hi>fortified his Castle of</hi> Cymaron, <hi>and wan</hi> Melienyth <hi>to himself.</hi> And you may also there find, that the time when the said <hi>Hugh</hi> wan <hi>Melienyth,</hi> was in the year 1142.</p>
                  <p>Now that this <hi>Welsh History</hi> is of good credit, I suppose cannot be reasonably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied; for as Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in the 44 Page of his <hi>Historical Antiquities</hi> doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that in these <hi>Welsh</hi> matters he doth chiefly follow the same; so on the other hand you may find in <hi>Vossius</hi> his Book <hi>de Historicis Latinis,</hi> Pag. 389. &amp; 390. and in <hi>Isaackson</hi>'s <hi>Chronology,</hi> Pag.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64436:15"/>323. And in <hi>Baleus</hi> his Book <hi>de Illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Scriptoribus Majoris Britanniae,</hi> Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Basil, Apud Joannem Oporinum,</hi> Pag. 195, 196. And in <hi>Pitseus</hi> his Book <hi>de illustribus Angliae Scriptoribus,</hi> Printed at <hi>Paris</hi> 1619. Pag. 215. that the said <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radocus Lhancaruan</hi> was the Author of the said Book, and flourished in the year 1150, and by consequence was living in the year 1142, when the said <hi>Hugh</hi> wan <hi>Melienyth;</hi> And the said <hi>Pitseus</hi> tells us in the aforesaid Page, that the said <hi>Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docus</hi> was <hi>elegans Poeta, eloquens Rhetor, &amp; Historicus non contemnendus;</hi> And the said <hi>Baleus,</hi> Pag. 196. sayes that he was <hi>totus consecratus ad res gestas recentium Britanniae regulorum illust<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> das;</hi> And in <hi>Baleus</hi> and <hi>Pitseus</hi> in the aforesaid Pages, and in <hi>Powells</hi> Notes on the said History, Pag. 206. you may find this following <hi>Distichon;</hi> viz.
<q>
                        <l>Historiam Britonum doctus scripsit Caradocus</l>
                        <l>Post Caduualladrum regia sceptra notans.</l>
                     </q> So that as to the proving of the taking of <hi>Melienyth</hi> by the said <hi>Hugh,</hi> and the time when it was so taken, <hi>Caradocus Lhancaruan</hi> is a Witness free from any exception, that can be justly made.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:64436:16"/>
                  <p>The onely Question therefore is, Of what Age the said <hi>Hugh</hi> then was? And because that is uncertain, and that I am willing to reckon so, as may be most dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantageous to my self, I will suppose him to be then but Twelve years old, which is the same Age that <hi>Silvester Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raldus,</hi> in that Edition printed at <hi>London</hi> 1585. Pag. 203. sayes Prince <hi>Lhewellin ap Jorweth</hi> was of, when he began to infest his Uncles, and is indeed as young, as I have observed any to appear in such Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Affairs. Now, if we should believe that <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> did marry the said <hi>Bertred</hi> so soon as she was Fourteen years of Age, then the said Marriage would happen in the year 1171. at which time, if <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> was born in the year 1130, and was but Twelve years old when he wan <hi>Melienyth,</hi> in the year 1142. yet he would be Forty one years of Age, when he married the said <hi>Bertred.</hi> It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not therefore be imagined, that so great a person should continue unmarried till he was above Forty years old, or that he should marry to his first Wife, one so much different from him in years; But, when he had married a former Wife, who dyed, leaving him only a daughter or
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64436:16"/>daughters, it is no wonder if in his Age, he married a young Lady, to the intent he might have Issue-male to succeed him in so great an Estate.</p>
                  <p>Also if you look in Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> Pag. 131. you may find this Deed of Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> in which his Mother doth not join with him, which I think fit in this place to Transcribe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HƲgo Comes Cestriae, Constabulario suo, Dapifero, omnibus Baronibus suis, omnibus Hominibus suis, Francis &amp; Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, tam futuris quam praesentibus, salutem, Concedo Sanctimonialibus de Bolintona stagnum meum de Dunintona firmum terrae meae sicut fuit tempore Henrici Regis, in perpetuam Elemosynam pro anima mea, &amp; Patris mei, &amp; meorum Antecessorum: Et praecipio omnibus Hominibus meis, quod ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant meam firmam pacem, ita quod nullus inde praedictis Sanctimonialibus injuriam vel contumeliam faciat. Teste Roberto Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pifero de Monte alto, Filippo de Kima, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone silio Osberti, Willielmo Patric, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulfo silio Warneri, Rogero de Maletot, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanne Priore de Trentham, Orm ejus Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nico,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64436:17"/>Rogero Monacho de Hambi, Willielmo Clerico Comitis qui Chartam scripsit apud Belitesford, &amp; multis aliis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I also think fit to re-mind the Reader, how I did heretofore acquaint him, in Print, that I had a <hi>Pedigree</hi> by me of the Barons <hi>de Monte-alto,</hi> drawn not long since by Sir <hi>Peter Leicester,</hi> and written all with his own hand, in which he makes the first <hi>Robert de Monte-alto</hi> Steward of <hi>Cheshire</hi> (who he sayes lived in the time of King <hi>Steven</hi>) to have Issue, (besides other Sons who were younger) two Sons, <hi>Raph</hi> and <hi>Robert,</hi> who were afterwards successively Stewards of <hi>Cheshire</hi> all which is certainly true.</p>
                  <p>Now, that, <hi>Robert de Monte-alto,</hi> Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard of <hi>Cheshire,</hi> who was Witness to this Deed, was the first <hi>Robert de Monte-alto,</hi> will be manifest, because the second <hi>Robert</hi> came not to be Steward of <hi>Cheshire</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the life of Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> as appears by the said Pedigree, as also in Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s Book of <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> Pag. 143. and in the 33 Page of my Answer to Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s two Books, where you find <hi>Raph</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:64436:17"/>the Steward, elder Brother to the second <hi>Robert,</hi> out-living Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> and being a Witness to a Deed of Earl <hi>Randle</hi> Son to the said <hi>Hugh,</hi> it will therefore necessarily follow, if this Deed of Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> was made immediately before the death of that <hi>Robert de Monte-alto,</hi> who was a Witness thereto, that the said Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> was a great deal elder than his Wife <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred;</hi> for though the said <hi>Robert</hi> did live something longer than Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth take notice of, yet I think it cannot be proved that he was living any conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable time after the said <hi>Eustace,</hi> and I know no reason why we should conclude that <hi>Eustace</hi> was slain immediately after he was a Witness to the other Deed, or that this <hi>Robert</hi> dyed presently after he was a Witness to this Deed; nay, I think it will appear, that the aforesaid Deed to the Nuns of <hi>Bolinton,</hi> was certainly made some years before the said <hi>Robert</hi> dyed, <hi>viz.</hi> in the time of King <hi>Stephen;</hi> for if it had been made when <hi>Henry</hi> the second was King, Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> would not have said, <hi>Sicut fuit tempore Henrici Regis,</hi> (as he there doth) but he would have said, <hi>Sicut fuit tempore Henrici primi,</hi> or else he would have used some other words to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64436:18"/>distinguish King <hi>Henry the First,</hi> from the then King <hi>Henry the Second.</hi> Now King <hi>Stephen</hi> dyed in the year 1154, and <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred</hi> being not born till the year 1157, it will from this Deed be very clear, that if Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had sealed the said Deed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before King <hi>Stephen</hi> dyed, yet Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> would be at the least Twenty four years older than <hi>Bertred</hi> his Wife. And therefore no likelihood at all, that the said <hi>Bertred</hi> was his first Wife.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="arguments_to_objections">
               <p>Against these Arguments many Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions have been raised, that so they might make out in number, what they did want in weight; and particularly against the first Argument, because if that hold, there is no doubt, but the said <hi>Amicia</hi> was Legitimate;</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <p>And first, it is objected, That <hi>Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> was not at that time an equal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitor to have married a Co-heir of the Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> the Co-heirs being marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to four of the greatest Peers of the Kingdom, and therefore from hence, they would insinuate, that the said <hi>Amicia</hi> was not Legitimate. To which I answer, That I do not affirm that <hi>Mainwaring</hi> was
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64436:18"/>an equal Competitor to those great Peers, or that the said <hi>Amicia</hi> was a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heir to the said Earl <hi>Randle,</hi> she being, as appears from the aforesaid Arguments by necessary consequence a Daughter to <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> by a former Wife, and so but half Sister to the said Earl <hi>Randle,</hi> and therefore could not be a Coheir; for, as you may see in <hi>Littleton's Tenures,</hi> Sect. 2.6, 7, 8, one that is but an half Sister cannot possibly be a Coheir to her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or inherit his Lands; however that could have been no substantial Argument to prove that <hi>Amicia</hi> was not Legimate.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Because sometimes some particular persons have the fortune to marry Wives far beyond their degrees or Estates.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Neither was Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> so inconsiderable a person, as perhaps some may conceit him to be: For, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides that, Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Roger Mainwaring,</hi> Son of the said Sir <hi>Ralph,</hi> did after the death of the said Sir <hi>Ralph,</hi> give to Sir <hi>William Mainwaring</hi> his younger Son, <hi>Peover,</hi> as also some other Lands; the said Sir <hi>Ralph</hi> had also the Lordship of <hi>Waburne</hi> in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk,</hi> and the Lordships, (or great part)
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64436:19"/>of <hi>Rode, Blakenhal, Warmincham, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therden, Ashton juxta Kelsall, Henbury,</hi> and <hi>Pexhull, Willaston, Greate Warford, Little Warford, Whelock, Winnington, Cokishall, Tatton, Senellestune, Smalwood,</hi> and half of <hi>Pichmere;</hi> as also other Lands in <hi>Cheshire;</hi> the most of which came to Sir <hi>William Trussel,</hi> who about <hi>Edward the First</hi>'s time, married <hi>Matilda,</hi> the sole Daughter and Heir of Sir <hi>Warine Mainwaring,</hi> Son of Sir <hi>Thomas Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> Son of Sir <hi>Roger,</hi> Son of the said Sir <hi>Ralph</hi> and <hi>Amicia:</hi> And the said Sir <hi>Ralph</hi> was Chief Justice of <hi>Chester,</hi> which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently hath been a Place of that great Repute, that Dukes of <hi>York, Glocester, Exeter</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Earls of <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Wiltshire, Suffolk, Shrewsbury,</hi> and <hi>Derby;</hi> besides other great Persons have heretofore enjoyed the same.</p>
                     <p>And though it hath been objected by Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in the 17 page of his Answer to my Defence of <hi>Amicia,</hi> that as to the Note of Dukes and Earls to have been antiently Judges of <hi>Chester,</hi> I should have distinguished of the times; for that was not till the Reign of <hi>Richard the Second</hi> (who made Deputies to act in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64436:19"/>their stead) before which time he finds no such great persons Judges there; yet in this Sir <hi>Peter</hi> was mistaken, for that person which is said in his Catalogue of Judges of <hi>Chester</hi> to be Judge of <hi>Chester</hi> in the 15<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>Edward the Third,</hi> and by him is onely called <hi>Ralph Stafford,</hi> was Baron of <hi>Stafford</hi> at that very time, as appears by this following Deed, the Original whereof I my self have, and did give to Sir <hi>Peter Leceister</hi> a Copy thereof.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="deed">
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>SCiant praesentes &amp; futuri quod ego Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanna que fui ux. Johannis Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trevers in pura viduitate mea dedi concessi &amp; hac presenti carta mea confirmavi Alex. de Venables totam illam placeam terrae cum domibus &amp; omnibus aliis pertin. quam habeo in villa de Wylaston que vocat. le Rudyngges Habend. &amp; tenend. praedict. Alex. hered. &amp; Assignatis suis totam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictam placeam terrae cum pertin. de capitali dom. feodi illius per servicia inde debita &amp; de Jur. consueta libere quiete bene &amp; in pace J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>r. &amp; hereditarie impertuum cum omnib. libertatib. comoditatib. communibus &amp; easiamentis dicte placie terrae quoquo modo pertinentib. Et ego vero predicta Johanna &amp; heredes mei totam predictam placeam
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64436:20"/>terrae cum pertin. predicto Alex. heredibus &amp; assignatis suis cont. omnes gentes Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantizabimus Acquietabimus &amp; defende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus imperpetuum. In cujus rei testimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um huic presenti cartae Sigillum meum ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posui hiis testibus R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>dulpho Barone de Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford tunc Justic. Cestriae Willielmo de praers Johanne de Wetenhale Thom. de Erdeswyks Ricardo de Fouleshurst Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmo Hamelyn &amp; Aliis Dat. apud Cestriam die dominica proxima post festum sancti Barnabe apostoli An. Regni Regis Edwardi tertii post conquestum quinto decimo.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>And as you may see in Mr. <hi>Ashmole</hi>'s <hi>Institution of the Order of the Garter,</hi> p. 643. 670 &amp; 688. and in <hi>Vincent</hi>'s <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections upon Brooke,</hi> p. 488 &amp; 489. and in the first Part of Sir <hi>William Dugdale</hi>'s <hi>Baronage of</hi> England, <hi>pag.</hi> 160. the said <hi>Ralph Stafford</hi> was one of the first Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty five Knights Companions of the Order of the Garter, and was afterwards, <hi>viz.</hi> on the 5th of <hi>March,</hi> 25 <hi>Edward</hi> III. advanced to the Title of Earl of <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford;</hi> and it is impossible that there could be any Dukes or Earls made Judges of <hi>Chester</hi> before that Earldom was united to the Crown, because there were no
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64436:20"/>such persons belonging to the said Earls (except <hi>John Lacy</hi> Constable of <hi>Chester,</hi> who was made Earl of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> but was not made so as appears in Sir <hi>Peter Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi>'s <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 270. till the 23 of <hi>November,</hi> 1232. which was but something above four years before the death of <hi>John Scot,</hi> the last of the said Earls.) But there were ever antiently persons of good quality that were Judges of <hi>Chester,</hi> and if it had not always been a place of good repute, the Kings of <hi>England</hi> would never have made such very great persons to have succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them therein.</p>
                     <p>Neither was the Case the same with the other Daughters of the Earl of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> when <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> married with <hi>Amicia,</hi> as it was afterward, for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micia</hi> was married in the life time of her Father Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> whereas those four came to be such great fortunes upon the death of their Brother <hi>Randle,</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> and <hi>Lincolne,</hi> without Issue, to whom they then became Heirs, they being his Sisters of the whole Blood; and though all, or most of them were married be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they came to be his Heirs, yet the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64436:21"/>said Earl <hi>Randle</hi> having never had Issues the expectations of that Estate added to their other Portions, must needs make them very considerable Fortunes; whereas <hi>Amicia</hi> was but of the half Blood, being a Daughter of Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> by a former Wife, and therefore not in a capacity to have a share in that great Estate. And whereas it hath been objected, that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> matching his only Daughter, which he had by a former Wife, would have married her to as considerable a person as was either provided by himself, or his Son for his younger Children by a second Venter; I do answer and say, That I am not certain whether <hi>Amicia</hi> was the only Daughter that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had by his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Wife, because, I know some that pretend they can tell of some other Daughter or Daughters which the said Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had by his said Wife; but I do confess, I have never seen just proof of any but her; but supposing her to be the only Child by his first Wife, I have in my first Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 23, 24 &amp; 25: shewed that there is no strength in this Argument; And I may here further add, that if any will search for Examples, they may find very many, where the elder
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64436:21"/>Sisters, sometimes, because swayed by their Affections, and sometimes for other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, have not been married to so great persons as the younger Sisters have been; Neither can any one tell what Portions Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> gave to <hi>Amicia,</hi> or to any of his other Daughters; Neither is there any necessity that the elder Sister, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause by a former Wife, must have as great a Portion as a younger Sister by a latter Wife; because many times persons are not able to give so great Portions in their younger days, as afterwards: and because, the Children of the living Wife are oftentimes better provided for, than those of the dead Wife; and of this, I could, if I pleased, instance in some that I know; and in case the Father dies, and leave only Issue Female by the first, and a Son and Issue Female by a latter Wife (as in this case) there is great like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood (besides the advantage that the Sisters by the latter Wife would have by being Heirs at Law to their Brother he dying without Issue) that the Bro, her will naturally be more kind to those Sisters that are of the whole Blood, and about the same age, and bred up with him, than he will be to her that is but
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64436:22"/>his half Sister, and much older than himself.</p>
                     <p>And though Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> doth object in the 69 page of his Answer to the Defence of <hi>Amicia,</hi> That if <hi>Amicia</hi> had been Legitimate, she being of the first Venter, would have been more worthy than those of the Second, though that be true when the Sisters Claim as Heirs to their Father; yet when they come to Claim as Heirs to their Brother (as in this Case) if there be Sisters of two Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and the Brother be of the second Venter, then the Sisters that are of the second Venter, shall be preferred before those of the first Venter, because those of the second Venter are of the whole Blood. And those of the half Blood, are so far from being preferred before those of the whole Blood, that as I have herein before shewed the most remote of the Kindred shall be preferred before those who are but of the half Blood.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <p n="2">2. Secondly, Against <hi>Amicia's</hi> being Legitimate, it hath been objected thus;</p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:64436:22"/>
                     <p>If <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> had no other Wife but <hi>Bertred,</hi> then <hi>Amice</hi> must certainly be a Bastard; for she was not a Daughter by <hi>Bertred,</hi> as is granted on all sides.</p>
                     <p>But <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> never had any other Wife but <hi>Bertred. Ergo, Antice</hi> was a Bastard.</p>
                     <p>Now the <hi>Minor</hi> is to be proved by the Affirmer, <hi>Oportet Affirmantem probare;</hi> To which I answer,</p>
                     <p>First, That by this Rule, Sir <hi>Peter Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> was as much bound to prove <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia</hi> to be a Bastard, as I am bound to prove that <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> had a former Wife; For he as clearly affirmed that as I affirm the other, and there is no reason why Suppositions should pass for Proofs any more in his case, than they should do in mine.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, That less Proof by many degrees will serve, to prove a thing that was done long since, than will be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to prove that which was done lately. To instance in one Case, which may serve instead of many. If you be to prove a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64436:23"/>Deed that was lately sealed, it will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected you produce the Witnesses who were present at the sealing and delivery thereof. If your Deed was sealed a good while ago, the proving of the Hands will be required: But if the Deed be so old, that none alive could know the Hand-writing of the Witnesses, then the Deed carries its own Proof with it: And the like reason there is in all Cases of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, and especially in those that are so very ancient as this is. For, if I did only prove her called a Daughter, being it is so long since, she ought to be presumed Legitimate, unless the contrary do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. For the proving she was not by <hi>Bertred,</hi> does not prove that she was a Bastard; But onely proves that she was either a Bastard, or else by a former Wife: And our Law at this day is, That a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stard cannot be proved a Bastard but in his Life-time; and so it anciently was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, as appears by the old Treatise called <hi>Fleta. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 39. <hi>sect.</hi> 14. where it is thus said, <hi>Si autem post mortens alicujus op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponatur Bastardia, non allocabitur; cum defunctus ad talem exceptionem respondere non poterit.</hi> Now, if a Person cannot be proved a Bastard immediately after his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64436:23"/>death, because he cannot answer for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, What reason is there to charge <hi>Amice</hi> with Bastardy so many hundred years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her decease. And especially upon imagination onely, without direct proof for the same. And proof cannot so easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or truly be had several Hundreds of years after the Parties decease, as it might have been had within a few years after the Party was dead.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, If this Argument would hold as it is here framed, we should have almost nothing but Bastards in the ancient times: For if all must be Bastards, if we could not tell who their Mothers were, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly prove who their Fathers married, we might then conclude, most Persons to be Bastards that lived in the first and second Centuries after the Conquest. I shall not offer to put the Case upon any other Family but my own (though it doth reach a multitude of others.) But as to my own, if I mistake not, I find Eight persons whose Wives we are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ignorant of, and Six of those per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons left Issue, all which Issue, by this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, would be Bastards, which I am consident no reasonable man can or will
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64436:24"/>suppose; I shall instance only in one, <hi>viz, Roger Menilguarin,</hi> who in the Reign of King <hi>Henry the First,</hi> as you may see in the First Part of <hi>Monasticon Anglicanum,</hi> Pag. 985. gave <hi>Plumley</hi> (a place in <hi>Cheshire,</hi> near to <hi>Peover</hi>) to the Abby of S. <hi>Werburge</hi> at <hi>Chester;</hi> and as it appears by the said Record, the said <hi>Roger Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi> had Three Sons, <hi>William, Randle,</hi> and <hi>Wido.</hi> Now if Sir <hi>Peter</hi> should af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That the said <hi>William, Randle,</hi> and <hi>Wido,</hi> were Legitimate, which I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he would not scruple to do, I could thus frame his own Argument against him.</p>
                     <p>If <hi>Roger Melinguarin</hi> had no Wife, then, <hi>William, Randle,</hi> and <hi>Wido,</hi> Sons of the said <hi>Roger,</hi> were certainly Bastards: But <hi>Roger Melinguarin</hi> aforesaid had no Wife. <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Now if this Argument would hold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Amicia,</hi> it would also hold against these Three Children of <hi>Roger Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> and indeed against all other Persons whose Fathers we could not directly, and <hi>in terminis,</hi> prove to have been married, (the Proof lying on the Affirmers side)
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64436:24"/>the Absurdity of which is so great, that Sir <hi>Peter</hi> himself cryes, <hi>God forbid all Children should be concluded Bastards, whose Mothers cannot be proved.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Also it is very hard, if possible, to tell whose Daughter the Wife of <hi>Robert de Ferrars,</hi> the first Earl of <hi>Ferrars</hi> and <hi>Derby</hi> was, and yet he was certainly mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and had Issue <hi>William Ferrars,</hi> who lived not to be Earl, and <hi>Robert de Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> who succeeded his said Father <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> in the Earldom, and <hi>Wakelin de Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rars,</hi> and a Daughter named <hi>Isolda,</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Stephen de Beauchamp,</hi> and another Daughter married to <hi>Walchelin Maminot.</hi> So also it is unknown who was the Wife of the second <hi>Robert de Ferrars</hi> Earl of <hi>Ferrars</hi> and <hi>Derby,</hi> and yet he also was certainly married, and had Issue <hi>William</hi> his Son, who succeeded him in the said Earldom; so also we cannot find who was the Wife of <hi>Ralph de Maunt</hi> Earl of <hi>Hereford,</hi> and yet he was certainly mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and left Issue-male. So also <hi>William de Mohun,</hi> the Third of that name, and the first Earl of <hi>Somerset</hi> or <hi>Dorset,</hi> (for those two Counties alwayes going toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in those elder times, and both served
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64436:25"/>by one Sheriff (as you may see in <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> upon <hi>Brooke,</hi> Pag. 472.) gave occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of indifferency to give the attribute of either, to him that had <hi>tertium dena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> the third peny of them) was also certainly married, for his Grandchild <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginold de Mohun</hi> was Earl of <hi>Somerset</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him; and yet our Authors, who write of these things, do not know whose Daughter the Wife of the said <hi>William de Mohun</hi> was; And to name no more of very many other Noblemen, whose Wives are not known, what great wonder is it that we do not know who was the first Wife of <hi>Hugh Cyvelick,</hi> by whom he had only Issue-female, when it is not known who were the Wises, of the above-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med great Persons, although they had Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue Male, by the said Wives; And which is worthy of observation, if <hi>Bertred,</hi> the second Wife of the said Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> had dyed before her said Husband, as his first Wife did, we had not known whose Daughter the said <hi>Bertred</hi> had been; for I think there is no ancient Historian, who doth speak thereof; neither do I know of any Record, except those which relate to the said <hi>Bertreds</hi> Joynture or Dower, which do tell whose Daughter the said <hi>Bertred</hi> was.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:64436:25"/>
                     <p n="3">3. Thirdly, It hath been objected, That whatsoever is given in Frank Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, is given as a Portion; But the giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Services of three Knights Fees in Frank Marriage, for which the Services of two Knights Fees are to be done, doth not seem to be a competent Portion, for a Legitimate Daughter of the Earl of <hi>Chester.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To which I answer, That the reason why Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> calls it a Portion, is, because he would have it thought that this was all her Portion; and thence would infer, that she was Illegitimate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause so very little was given with her; But this doth not well agree with what Sir <hi>Peter</hi> sayes in the 135 Page of his <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storical Antiquities,</hi> and 63 Page of his Answer to my Defence of <hi>Amicia,</hi> where he tells us, That Bastards in those elder Ages, were not of such disrepute as now in our dayes; And that the ancient Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern People admitted Bastards to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in their Inheritance, and that <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror was not ashamed of that Title, who began his Letter to <hi>Alan</hi> Earl of <hi>Little Britain,</hi> (as he did many others) <hi>Ego</hi> Willielmus <hi>cognomento</hi> Bastardus; so
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64436:26"/>that I think any Man that will weigh things indifferently, will easily and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily conclude, That if she had been but a Bastard, yet being a Bastard of so great an Earl, and being married to Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> who was no inconsiderable Person, she would have had a far greater Portion than those Services upon those terms they were given; for those Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces so given, would not be a Portion an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to the Estate of an ordinary Countreyman; And this is so clear, that when Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> was told, that it was like Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> had a great deal more with <hi>Amicia,</hi> he confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth Pag. 71. of his Answer to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Amicia,</hi> It may be so, What then? So that you may see he was at last con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, that those Services could not be her whole Portion; And though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not now tell what Portion the said Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> had, yet it is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that the Lordship of <hi>Henbury</hi> in <hi>Cheshire,</hi> might be part of the Portion of the said <hi>Amicia;</hi> for as appears in Sir <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Leicester</hi>'s <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> Pag. 107. <hi>Henbury</hi> was one of those Towns which <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> held in Demesne; And I do not find that any <hi>Mainwaring</hi> was
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64436:26"/>possessed thereof, before Sir <hi>Ralph Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring,</hi> who was Husband to the said <hi>Amicia,</hi> neither have I ever yet seen or heard of any Record or Deed which shews how <hi>Henbury</hi> first came to the <hi>Mainwarings.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But besides what is here said, Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s Rule, That whatsoever is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Frank Marriage, is given as a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; cannot hold good; for any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that pleaseth may give a Woman a Portion, but no man can give any thing in Frank Marriage, with any Woman but such who is of his whole Bloud: as Sister or Cousin collateral within the fourth Degree, so as they may not Enter-marry by the Law. As Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> says in his <hi>Grand Abridgment of the Law,</hi> p. 970.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <p n="4">4. Fourthly, It hath been objected, That the Antient Historians of our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as <hi>Policronicon,</hi> writ by the Monk of <hi>Chester, Henry Knighton,</hi> the Monk of <hi>Leicester,</hi> and others; also <hi>Stow</hi> and <hi>Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> have Recorded the lawful Daughters and Coheirs of Earl <hi>Hugh.</hi> And also the Record of 18 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. And had <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mice</hi> been a Legitimate Daughter, it is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64436:27"/>likely that these Historians would not all have omitted her, but of her there is <hi>Altum silentium</hi> among all the Historians and Records.</p>
                     <p>To which I answer, That in this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, there is no weight at all; for those Historians which Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> doth speak of there, do not take upon them to give an account of all the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> but only to tell who were the Heirs of <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> which none of his Sisters could be, unless such as were of the whole Bloud to him; and of this Sir <hi>Peter</hi> was so sensible, that in his <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> p. 138. he doth confess, that this is not a sure evincing Argument; but Sir <hi>Peter</hi> did forget him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, when he said there was <hi>Altum silen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium</hi> concerning <hi>Amicia,</hi> among all the Historians which he there named; for Mr. <hi>Cambden,</hi> which is one of those which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> himself doth there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as he tells us, who were the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs of <hi>Randle Blundevil,</hi> so he takes notice of the Wife of the said <hi>Ralph Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilwarin</hi> or <hi>Mainwaring,</hi> and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Brand of Bastardy at all, as you may see in his <hi>Britannia,</hi> in his Descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64436:27"/>of the Country of <hi>Chester,</hi> whose words are these: <hi>Cum jam Danus sub North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich, de qua dixi, cum wevero aquas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sociaverit, in occasum recta prolabitur We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Peverum{que} recipit ab ortu, Qui prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfluit, &amp; nomen facit Pevero, ubi habet sedem vetusta illa nobilis familia de Meinil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warin vulgo Manewaring, e qua Radulphus duxit filiam Hugonis Kevelioc Comitis Cestriae, ut constat ex charta antiqua penes Ranulphum ejusdem familiae nunc heredem.</hi> And to let you see how little strength there is in objecting, That a Daughter is not Legitimate, because our Historians do not mention her, I shall here inform you of one <hi>Matilda,</hi> a Daughter to <hi>Randle de Micines</hi> or <hi>Meschines</hi> one of our Earls of <hi>Chester,</hi> who was married to <hi>David</hi> Earl of <hi>Dundee</hi> in <hi>Scotland;</hi> which <hi>David</hi> was Brother to <hi>Malcolme,</hi> and <hi>William</hi> Kings of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and was Nephew to <hi>Matilda</hi> or <hi>Mande,</hi> who was Queen of <hi>England,</hi> and Wife to King <hi>Henry the First;</hi> and yet all our antient Historians, except <hi>John Bromton,</hi> do wholly omit the said <hi>Maude,</hi> and so also doth Sir <hi>Peter Leicester,</hi> though he spent so many years in Writing and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewing what he had written of the Earls
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64436:28"/>of <hi>Chester</hi> since the <hi>Norman</hi> Conquest; and so do all our Modern Writers that I have Read: The words of the said <hi>John Bromton</hi> (who writes from the year 588, to the year 1198.) as they are in his <hi>Chronicon,</hi> col. 966 and 967. are these:</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                           <body>
                              <div type="history">
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>ANno Domini M. lxix. &amp; Regis Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmi quarto, Malcolmus rex Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum cum infinita multitudine per Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlandiam versus orientem se diveriens, vniversam Tesedale &amp; loca ejus finitima ultra citra{que} feroci depopulatione vastavit. Depopulata{que} quadam parte Clivelandiae quasi ex subito Hersernesse occupavit. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de{que} per terras sancti Cuthberti discurrens, multos rebus &amp; vita privavit, villas &amp; ecclesias cum hiis qui in eas confugerant, concremando, senes &amp; vetulae gladiis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truncantur, alii indifferenter confodiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, rapti{que} ab uberibus matrum parvuli in altum projiciuntur, &amp; lanceis excipiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: hac enim crudelitate maxima Scoti bestiis crudeliores pro ludi spectaculo dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctabantur, qui demum in terram malam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertentes, juvenes &amp; virgines, robustos, miseros &amp; captivos secum duxerunt, &amp; eos perpetua servitute dampnaverunt, in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64436:28"/>tantum ut vix esst domus in Scotia, quae servo aut ancilla Anglici generis careret. Tunc vero secundum quosdam, iste Malcol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus rex Scotiae in revertendo de Anglia, dictam Margaretam dicti Edgari sororem primo invenit, &amp; eam in uxorem duxit, per quam post-modum ferocitatem in parte dimisit, &amp; honestior factus est. Et ex qua per processum temporis genuit sex fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os, &amp; duas filias, scilicet Edwardum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenitum, qui cum patre interfectus fuit; Edmundum ante patrem decedentem; Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garum, qui post patrem novem annis regna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit; Edredum ante patrem decedentem; Alexandrum, qui post Edgarum fratrem suum</hi> xvii. <hi>annis regnavit, &amp; David, qui post Alexandrum fratrem suum</hi> xxix. <hi>annis regnavit. Et ex Matilda de sancto Licio genuit Henricum comitem sed non regnantem. Genuit etiam Malcolmus rex ex dicta Margareta Matildam postea regis Angliae Henrici primi uxorem, ex qua pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessit Matildis imperatrix. Altera quo{que} filia Malcolmi, Maria nomine, Eustachio Comiti Bononiae, postea nupta fuit, de qua processit Matilda quae postea Stephano regi Angliae extitit maritata. Henric. vero Comes filius David regis genuit tres filios, scili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet Malcolmum, qui post David</hi> xii. <hi>annis
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64436:29"/>regnavit; Willielmum, qui post fratrem suum</hi> xlix. <hi>annis regnavit, &amp; David Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitem de Dundee. Willielmus vero rex genuit Alexandrum secundum, qui regnauit</hi> xxxv. <hi>annis, &amp; genuit Alexandrum tertium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui</hi> xxxvii <hi>annis regnavit, &amp; genuit Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garetam neptem regis Edwardi Angliae pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi post conquestum. David autem comes de Dundee filius Henrici Comitis genuit ex Matilda filia Ranulphi Comitis Cestriae</hi> iiii. <hi>filias, scilicet Margaretam, Matildam, Isabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, &amp; Aldam. Margareta vero nupsit Alano de Galeway, ex qua processit Dever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goil uxor Johannis de Balliolo, quae genuit Johannem de Balliolo, quem dictus rex An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae Edwardus primus post conquestum in Regem Scotiae post mortem Alexandri tertii praefecit. Altera vero filia dictae Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retae Elena nomine, Comitissa Wintoniae, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duxit Comitissam de Ferers Margaretam, Elenam de la Souch, &amp; Elizabetham Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitissam de Boghan. Matilda vero alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra filia David Comitis sine liberis decessit. Tercia vero filia ejusdem Comitis David Isabella, nupsit Roberto de Brus, qui genuit Robertum, &amp; ille Robertus genuit Rober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum regem Scotiae, qui genuit David re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem Scotiae, cui rex Angliae Edwardus a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questu tercius sororem snam Johannum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritavit.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64436:29"/>Quarta vero filia Alda nupsit Henrico de Hastyng, qui genuit Henricum, qui genuit Johannem.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>Now if a Daughter to an Earl of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> who was Wife to so great a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, was omitted by our Historians, what wonder can it be, if <hi>Amicia</hi> the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> and the Wife of <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> was also omitted by them? And as <hi>John Bromton</hi> did men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the said <hi>Matilda,</hi> because he did know there was such a one, though other Historians were ignorant thereof; and as Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> did take notice of the Wife of the said <hi>Ralph,</hi> because he had seen the Deed which proved it, in the hands of my Great Grandfather <hi>Randle</hi> (who was afterwards Sir <hi>Randle Mainwaring</hi> Knight) so I suppose that our other Authors, both Antient and Modern, would have mentioned the said <hi>Matilda</hi> and <hi>Amicia,</hi> if they had seen what <hi>John Bromton,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cambdon</hi> did see.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <p n="5">5. Fifthly, It hath been objected. That without any alteration <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> by any Act of Parliament, the Common-Law
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64436:30"/>in sundry things is alter'd at this day, from what it was in former ages, long after <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, <hi>Coke upon Little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> fol. 34. sect. 39. <hi>Coke</hi> ibid. fol. 3. a. fol. 8. a. at the bottom of the Page, and on the other side of the bottom, and fol. 26. b. sect. 29. wherein there is sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to be Proofs that the Common-Law is altered in many things without any Act of Parliament, from what it was in those elder times.</p>
                     <p>To which I answer,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. First, That if the Common-Law had been or could be altered other ways than by Act of Parliament, yet it would make nothing, as to the Point in hand, unless the Common-Law had been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in the Case of Frank Marriage itself.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Secondly. That Sir <hi>Peter Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> did mistake himself when he thought my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> said, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law had been altered in those par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth mention in these places which are cited before; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> tells us, that the Common-Law was taken and holden sometimes differently from what it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:64436:30"/>now, and withal, fol. 8. b. at the bottom tells us, that if it be an antient Grant, it must be expounded as the Law was taken at the time of the Grant; And these Cases which Sir <hi>Peter Leceister</hi> doth cite, are some of those which my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> doth bring to prove that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law was differently taken in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages in some things, from what it is taken to be in this Age, but not to prove that there was a change of the Common Law, without an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; To instance therefore in every one of those particulars which Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> hath as aforesaid taken notice of; In that in fol. 34. sect. 39. my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> tells us, that in antient times, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by <hi>Glanvil,</hi> lib. 6. cap. 1. It was taken that a Man could not have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed his Wife <hi>Ad ostium Ecclesiae,</hi> of more than a third part, but of less he might; But at this day the Law is taken, as <hi>Littleton</hi> here holdeth. But my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> says not that the Law is altered therein from what it was; so also fol. 3. a. he says, The Parishioners or Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, or <hi>Probi homines</hi> of <hi>Dale,</hi> or the Churchwardens, are not capable to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase Lands, but Goods they are, unless
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64436:31"/>it were in antient time, when such Grants were allowed; here my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> says not one word that the Common Law is herein altered, but only that some kind of Grants were allowed then, which would not be allowed now, and this agrees with that f. 8. b. on the other side at the bottom, where he says, if it be an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Grant, it must be expounded as the Law was taken at the time of the Grant; so also fol. 8. a. at the bottom of the page. He says of antient time the Heir was permitted to have an Action of Debt upon a Bond made to his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors and his Heirs, but the Law is not so holden at this day; so in that fol. 26. b. sect. 29. But it hath been said, that if a Man give Land to another, and to his Heirs of the Body of such a Woman lawfully begotten; that this is no Estate Tail for the uncertainty by whom the Heirs shall be begotten, for that the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Donee or other Cousin, may have Issue by the Woman which may be Heir to the Donee, and Estates in Tail must be certain; therefore our Author, to make it plain in all his Cases, added to these words (his heirs) which he shall Inegn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. But that opinion is since our Author
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:64436:31"/>wrote overrul'd, and that Estate judged to be an Estate Tail, and begotten shall be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily intended begotten by the Donee.</p>
                     <p>So that my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> doth not in any of those places say; that the Law is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in altered, but he all along avoids that expression, and only tells us, that such and such Grants were allowed, the Law was so and so taken, and so and so hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and such and such an opinion hath been over-rul'd, and accordingly all such other like expressions of my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> are thus to be understood; But withal it must be acknowledged (as was before expressed) that in those particular Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, where the law hath been holden otherwise, then it is holden now, that if it be an antient Grant, it must be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, as the Law was taken at the time of the said Grant. And thus, as you may see <hi>Coke upon Littleton,</hi> fol. 21. b. in the Case of <hi>Piers de Saltmarsh,</hi> and others, it was judged in King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Third</hi>'s time, and in King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Fourth</hi>'s time, That a Man might give Land to his Son in Frank Marriage, but in King <hi>Henry the Eigth</hi>'s time it was holden otherwise, the former Books be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not remembred; but notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64436:32"/>that this Point was judged thus dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently, the Law was still the same, and all that can be said is, that some of the Judges did not judge right, according to the Common Law; and indeed, if this Rule of Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s was true, that because the Judges in one Age did take the Common Law to be otherways, than it was taken in former Ages, that therefore the Common Law was changed; The Judges then could never do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Common Law; for when they had declared (though erroneously) that the Common Law ought to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise taken, than it was formerly, the Common Law by Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s Rule, would be thereupon changed, and what they did, would ever be Legal, the absurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whereof every one may easily discern.</p>
                     <p>And indeed my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> is so far from being of opinion that the Common Law hath or can be changed, unless by Act of Parliament, that in the first Part of his <hi>Institutes,</hi> fol. 115. b. he tells us, That whatsoever was at the Common Law, and is not ousted or taken away by any Statute, remaineth still. And a few lines lower he also says, The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law hath no Controler in any Part
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64436:32"/>of it, but the High Court of Parliament, and if it be not abrogated or altered by Parliament, it remains still.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <p n="6">6. Sixthly, It hath been objected, that in this very particular Case of Frank-Marriage the Law is different now from what it was in those former Ages, and this hath been pretended to be proved by the words of <hi>Glanvil,</hi> who lived in the same Age with <hi>Amicia</hi> (and as Sir <hi>Henry Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> tells us) was the first that reduced our Law into Writing; as also by the words of <hi>Bracton,</hi> who was the second that did Write of our English Laws, and lived in the time of King <hi>Henry the Third,</hi> as also by Precedents of some Lands given to <hi>Geva</hi> the Wife of <hi>Geffrey Riddel,</hi> and Daughter of <hi>Hugh Lupus,</hi> and to <hi>Joane</hi> the Wife of <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> Prince of <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wales,</hi> and Daughter of King <hi>John;</hi> which Gifts of the said Lands Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> will have to be Gifts in Frank-Marriage, and also says that the said <hi>Geva,</hi> and <hi>Joane,</hi> were both of them Bastards:</p>
                     <p>And to make this out, Sir <hi>Peter</hi> in that Book of his, which he was pleased to call my <hi>Law Cases Mistaken,</hi> pag. 5 &amp; 6.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64436:33"/>names us seven several particulars, which he calls <hi>Parcels of the Law in</hi> Glanvil<hi>'s time, and those more antient Ages;</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter</hi> says they are contrary to those pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by me. But all these seven Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s Law, are easily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered; for neither <hi>Glanvil,</hi> nor any other Author that I can find, ever said any word of the first six of them; and as to the seventh, though he there tells us that Earls and great Lords in those former Ages, did often Join with their Mothers, who then had the Tuition of them in Deeds and Charters, whiles they were very young, yet, as will appear anon, I believe there will be but one single Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent found, in which any young Lord, who was under Age, Joined with his Mother, and did use her Seal to any Charter or Deed; neither will that Case relate to this of <hi>Amicia</hi> in the least de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. But let us take a view of those words of <hi>Glanvil,</hi> lib. 7. c. 1. which sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> doth so much relie upon as they are by him truly quoted in the seventh page of the second of his two Books, which words are these:</p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:64436:33"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IN alist acceptione accipitur Dos secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum leges Romanas: secundum quas proprié appellatur Dos, id quod cum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liere datur viro: quod vulgariter dicitur Maritagium.: Potest ità{que} quilibet liber homo, terram habens, quandem partem ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae suae cum filiâ suâ, vel cum aliquâ aliâ quâlibet muliere, dare in maritagium, sive habuerit haeredem sive non, velit haeres vel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> &amp; eo contradicente.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Also lib. 7. cap. 18. <hi>Maritagium, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem aliud nominatur liberum, aliud Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitio obnoxium: liberum dicitur marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium, quando aliquis liber homo aliquam partem terra suae dat cum aliquâ muliere alicui in maritagium, ità quod ab omni servitio terra illa sit quieta, &amp; a se &amp; haeredibus suis, versus capitalem Dominum acquietanda: &amp; in hâc quidem libertate ita stabit terra illa usque ad tertium haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem: neo interim tenebuntur haeredes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de facere aliquod homagium: Post tertium verò haeredem, ad debitum servitium terra ipsa revertetur; &amp; homagium inde capie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Quia, si fuerit pars feodi militaris, pro quantitate terrae servitium feodi inde prestabit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:64436:34"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Solet autem qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ndo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> terra aliqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in maritagi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, Salvo &amp; retent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> debil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitio ipsi Capitoli Domino: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> tenebuntur maritus midier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ips<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>: &amp; ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redes sui servitium id facere, sed sine h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> usque ad tertium h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>redem.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And these are all the worde of <hi>Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth any where Cite, which do relate to any Gifts mad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Free-Marriage, or in Marriage li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Services.</p>
                     <p>And here let me observe, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I have many times blamed Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> for so often affirming that <hi>Glate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> said that Lands might be given with any Woman in <hi>liberum maritagium,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Glanvil</hi> had said no such thing, that Sir <hi>Peter</hi> at the last, in the second Page of that Reply, which he calls the <hi>Second Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> says, <hi>Though</hi> Glanvil <hi>hath not these very words— Lands may be given with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y Woman in</hi> liberum Maritagium; yet he saith it by consequence drawn clearly out of his words, lib. 7. cap. 18. which (Sir <hi>Peter</hi> says) is the same in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. So that Sir <hi>Peter</hi> with much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:64436:34"/>doth acknowledge that <hi>Glanvil</hi> hath not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>presly said any such thing, onely it seem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> he fancied, that the same may be by consequence drawn out of <hi>Glanvil</hi>'s words; which how Sir <hi>Peter</hi> did prove I am now to enquire into. As for those words which <hi>Glanvil</hi> hath, lib. 7. cap. 1. they cannot prove any such thing; for those words, <hi>Potest itaque quilibet liber homo, terram habens, quandem partem ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae suae cum filiâ sua, vel cum aliquâ aliâ quali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>et nonliere, dare in maritagium, sive ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>erit haeredem sive non, velit haeres vol non, imo &amp; eo contradicente.</hi> Do only prove that a man may give Lands with any Woman in <hi>Maritagium,</hi> and therefore <hi>Maritagium</hi> being two-fold, viz. <hi>Maritagium liberum</hi> and <hi>Maritagium ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitio abnoxium, Maritagium</hi> being the <hi>Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> doth comprehend both Free-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and Marriage liable to Services; so that if a Man can give Lands with any Woman in Marriage liable to Services, he may give Lands with any Woman in <hi>Maritagium;</hi> and there never was any doubt made, but that a Man may give Band<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> with any Woman whatsoever in Marriage liable to Services; But that upon which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth most princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64436:35"/>rely, are these words of <hi>Glanvil,</hi> lib. 7. cap. 18. <hi>Maritagium, autem aliud nominatur liberum, aliud servitio obnoxium liberum dicitur maritagium, quando aliquis liber homo aliquam partem terrae suae dat cum aliqua muliere alicui in Maritagium, itâ quod ab omni servitio terra illa sit quieta, &amp; a se &amp; haeredibus suis, versus capita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem Dominum acquietanda.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For from thence, as you may see in the 54 page of the first of his two Books, which he calls his <hi>Reply,</hi> and again, at the bottom of the 29 page, and in the 30 page of the second of his two Books, Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> frames this Argument:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Glanvil</hi> there saith, that a Man may give Land with any Woman in Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, so that it be acquit from all Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice <hi>à se &amp; haeredibus suis, versus capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talem Dominum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But Land so given (saith <hi>Glanvil</hi>) <hi>est liberum Maritagium.</hi> Ergo <hi>Glanvil</hi> saith, Lands may be given with any Woman in <hi>liberum Maritagium.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:64436:35"/>
                     <p>To which I answer, That Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> is the first Man, that ever, so far as I can find, went about to prove a Point of Law by a Syllogism; and in this new way of his he hath no good success; for his major and minor Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions are both of them untrue; for <hi>Glanvil</hi> neither says, That a Man may give part of his Land with any Woman in Marriage, so that it be acquit from all Service, <hi>a se &amp; haeredibus suis, versus capitalem Dominum.</hi> Neither doth <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> say, That Lands so given (<hi>viz.</hi> with any Woman) <hi>est liberum Maritagium,</hi> for <hi>Glanvil</hi> onely says, That <hi>liberum Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagium,</hi> is when a Man gives Lands <hi>cum</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note>
                        <hi>aliqua muliere ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cui in Maritagium, ita quod ab omni servitio terra illa sit quieta, &amp; a se &amp; haeredibus suis, versus capitalem Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num acquietanda;</hi> that is, Free-Marriage is where a Man gives Lands with
<note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> some Woman (<hi>viz.</hi> one of his Kindred) in Marriage, so that it may be acquit from all Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that Lands so given with some Woman <hi>est liberum Maritagium,</hi> but <hi>Glanvil</hi> doth not here, nor any where else
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:64436:36"/>say, that Lands may be given with any Woman in <hi>Maritagium,</hi> so that it may beacquit from all Service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for though Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> doth here and many times elsewhere construe these words <hi>(cum aliqua muliere)</hi> with any Woman, yet they are not Latine for <hi>with any Woman,</hi> but for, with some Woman, for <hi>Aliquis</hi> when alone without <hi>Quili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet,</hi> or some such other like word, is La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine for some one, but not for any one, as you may see in Sir <hi>Thomas Eliot</hi>'s Bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liotheca or Library, Printed 1545. where he renders the word <hi>Aliquis</hi> thus; <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis, Aliquae, Aliquod,</hi> Some. <hi>Aliquis est,</hi> he is a man of no small reputation; So also in Mr. <hi>Gouldman</hi>'s Dictionary print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> 1674. <hi>Aliquis vel Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui, Aliquae vel Aliqua, Aliquod vel Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid; ex alius &amp; quis:</hi>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Somewhat, Something, Some Body, Some One, <hi>Aliquis, ut Graecis,</hi>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Capitur pro homine non obscuro. Ʋt fac ut me velis esse aliquem,</hi> Cic. i. e. <hi>non prorsus obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Aliquor viginti dies.</hi> Plau. <hi>i.e. circiter viginis dies.</hi> Sic. Var. de re rust. <hi>Aliqua foliaquinque.</hi> So also Dr. <hi>Thomas Holyoke</hi> in that large Dictionary of his Printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1677. <hi>Aliquis, vel qui, quae, vel,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64436:36"/>qua, quod, vel quid;</hi>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>achad, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Some Body, Some One, Somewhat, Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <hi>Aliquis ut Graecis</hi>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>capitur pro bomine non obscuro: ut; fac, ut me velis esse aliquam,</hi> Cic. <hi>i. e. non prorsus, obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> ¶ <hi>Aliquos viginti dies,</hi> Plaut. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naec. <hi>i. e. circiter viginti dies,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>And so in <hi>Thomas Thomasius,</hi> and in other Dictionaries; so that Sir <hi>Peter</hi> did run himself into very many errors, by his mistaking of the aforesaid words, <hi>cum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua muliere;</hi> for <hi>Glanvill</hi> is so far, from proving the Law in his time to be diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in the point of <hi>Frank Marriage</hi> from what it is now, that he proves the Law to be the very same then in that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, that it is now; For he sayes, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears before, <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. that Lands may be given with any Woman whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>in Maritagium,</hi> which is yet true, for Lands may yet be given with any Woman whatsoever in Marriage liable to services, and <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. when he tells us what <hi>Liberum Maritagium</hi> is, he sayes Lands may be so given <hi>cum aliqua Muliere,</hi> with some Woman (<hi>viz.</hi> with one of the Kindred) which also is true at this very day.</p>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:64436:37"/>
                     <p>And hereupon my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> who knew the Law much better than Sir <hi>Peter Leicester,</hi> did in the first Part of his <hi>Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,</hi> or <hi>Commentary upon Littleton,</hi> fol. 21. b. (which is the very same side of the Leaf where he tells us, that the Woman or Man that is the cause of the Gift in <hi>Frank Marriage,</hi> must be of the blood of the Donor) cite in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, <hi>Glanvill lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. and <hi>cap.</hi> 18. which certainly he would never have done, if <hi>Glanvill</hi> instead of confirming, had directly contradicted what my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> had said.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <p n="7">7. Seventhly, It hath been objected by Sir <hi>Peter Leicester,</hi> that <hi>Bracton</hi> (who lived in the Reign of King <hi>Henry the Third,</hi> and was the second person who since the Conquest did write of out <hi>English</hi> Laws) doth say, that Lands might in his time be given in <hi>Frank Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage</hi> with any Woman; and for that he citeth these words of <hi>Bracton,</hi> lib. 2. cap. 7. par. 3. <hi>Et est maritagium aliquando li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berum, scilicet ab omni servitio quietum; &amp; aliquando servitio obligatum: liberum autem maritagium dicitur, ubi donator oult
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:64436:37"/>quod terra, sic data, quieta sit &amp; libera ab omni seculari servitio, quod ad Dominum feodi possit pertinere, &amp; ita quod ille, cui sic data fuerit, nullum omninò faciat inde ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitium usque ad tertium haeredem.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As also these words of <hi>Bracton,</hi> lib. 2. cap. 7. par. 1. <hi>Quoniam terra data Bastar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do in maritagium, sicut &amp; aliis, vel Bastar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do per se, in se tacitam habet conditionem vel expressam de reversione</hi>—&amp;c.</p>
                     <p>To which I answer, that those words of <hi>Bracton, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>par.</hi> 3. do only tell us what a Gift in <hi>Frank Marriage</hi> is, but there is not one word amongst those which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth there set down, which tells us with what kind of persons, such gifts are to be made. And those other words, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>par.</hi> 1. do only prove, that Lands may be given <hi>Bastardo in marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium</hi> (which they also may at this day) but there is not one word at all to prove, That Lands may be given to a Man <hi>cum Bastarda,</hi> whereas in this Case of <hi>Frank Marriage,</hi> the Party with whom the Land is given, not the Party to whom the Land is given, is the principal thing that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable herein. And though Sir <hi>Peter</hi>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:64436:38"/>in the 11<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Page of that Book of his which he unjustly calls, <hi>My Law-Cases Mistaken,</hi> sayes that this Answer of mine is very <hi>superficial and insufficient; For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teer the Party to whom, nor the Party with whom, is herein principally considerable, but the Party who is the principal cause if the Donation;</hi> yet the contrary will appear by <hi>Bracton</hi> is own words, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> which because Sir <hi>Peter</hi> cuts off too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> with an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I will here give you their more at large out of <hi>Bracton</hi> himself.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                           <body>
                              <div type="book_excerpt">
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>QƲoniam terra data Bastardo in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                                          <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                       </gap> tagium, sicut &amp; aliis, vel Bast<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                                          <desc>•••</desc>
                                       </gap> per se, in se tacitam habet conditionem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                                          <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                       </gap> expressam de reversione: ideo videndum si terra data fuerit Bastardo in maritag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                                          <desc>•••</desc>
                                       </gap> cum aliqua muliere, aut d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                                          <desc>••</desc>
                                       </gap>tur ipsis &amp; cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                                          <desc>•••</desc>
                                       </gap> haeredibus commnnibus, aut haeredibus ipsius uxoris tantum, in primo casu revert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>
                                       <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                                          <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                       </gap> donatorem, si defecerint haeredes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                                          <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                       </gap>, per modum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                                          <desc>••</desc>
                                       </gap>citum donationis. Si <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                                          <desc>••</desc>
                                       </gap>em fit haeredibus nxoris, tunc si haeredes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                                          <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                                       </gap>
                                       <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit de Bastardo, remanebit eorum haeredibus communibus terra, quia tales erunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                                          <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                       </gap> uxoris, quainvis communes, si autem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                                          <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                       </gap> munes destecrint, tunc defe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                                          <desc>••••</desc>
                                       </gap>
                                       <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                                          <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                       </gap>
                                       <pb n="65" facs="tcp:64436:38"/>data aliis haeredibus ipsius uxoris de altero viro vel à latere venientibus.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>From which words, it doth plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that in this case the Woman with whom the Land is given, is the principal thing that is considerable herein, and not the Bastard to whom the Land is given; For he here only tells us, that when Land is given <hi>Bastardo in maritagium cum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua muliere,</hi> that <hi>aut datur ipsis &amp; eorum haeredibus communibus, aut haeredibus ipsius uxoris tantum;</hi> whereas if the Woman with whom the Land is given, had not been the principal thing, that is conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the said Gift, he would have said, <hi>Aut datur ipsis &amp; eorum haeredibus commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, aut haeredibus ipsius uxoris tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, aut haeredibus ipsius Mariti tantum.</hi> But he sayes not one word of the Land coming to the Heirs of the Husband alone, though he tells you it may come to the Heirs of the Wife alone, which doth fully prove, that which I do here affirm, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Party with whom the Land is given, is the principal thing that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable, and that therefore though Lands may be given <hi>in liberum maritagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nm Bastardo-vel Bastardae,</hi> yet they may
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:64436:39"/>not be so given <hi>cum Bastardo vel cum Bastarda.</hi> Also <hi>Bracton</hi> is so far from proving that Land might have been given in his time in <hi>Free Marriage</hi> with any Woman whatsoever, that he proves, that such Gifts could only be made with a Woman who was of the blood of the Donor, his words, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>par.</hi> 3. are these; <hi>Et sciendum quod terra datur ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando ante sponsalia &amp; propter nuptias à patre mulieris vel alio parente ipsi marito cum muliere aliqua vel utrique simul, scilicet tali viro &amp; uxori suae (quod idem est) &amp; corum haeredibus vel alicui mulieri ad se maritandam, &amp;c.</hi> And presently after, <hi>Fit etiam talis donatio ante Matrimonium contractum, aliquando in ipso contractu, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando post contractum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Which is as much as to say, That this kind of Gift can only be made by the Father, Mother, or some other Kinsman, (For the word <hi>Parens</hi> or <hi>Parent</hi> in Latine and French, hath oftentimes that signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and we usually say, when a Man is of the same kindred with such a one, that he is of the same Parentage with him) And though Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> say in the 47 page of the second of his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:64436:39"/>two Books, that <hi>here is not one word to prove what I alledge it for; but rather the contrary: For a Father, or other Parent, may give Lands with any Woman in express terms, not to any of his Kindred only, no such word at all.</hi> In this Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth again mistake himself; For here he doth also falsly construe the words, <hi>cum muliere aliqua,</hi> with any Woman; whereas I have before proved, they are not Latine for with any Woman, but for with some Woman. And besides, <hi>Bracton</hi> here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly speaks of a Gift made by the Father of the Woman, or some other Parent, (that is, some other Kinsman) and if the Donor was Father or Cousin to the Woman, the Woman must of necessity be either Daughter or Cousin to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. Also my Lord <hi>Coke in his Institutes upon Littleton,</hi> Fol. 21. b. tells us, <hi>That one of those things incident to a Frank Marriage is, that the Woman or Man that is the cause of the Gift, be of the blood of the Donor.</hi> And for this, as appears let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>(i)</hi> he in the margent, cites <hi>Bracton, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. (which is this very place.) And can any Man think, that my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> would have cited that place, and the aforesaid places in <hi>Glanvill,</hi> to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:64436:40"/>that the Woman or Man who was the cause of the Gift, must be of the blood of the Donor, if <hi>Glanvill</hi> and <hi>Bracton</hi> in those places, had said that such Gifts might be made with those who were not of the blood: Also to what purpose should the Law have been changed by the Statute of <hi>Westminster</hi> the second, in this case of <hi>Frank Marriage,</hi> from what it was in ancient times, seeing since there were Estates in tail, there could be no great occasion to make Gifts in <hi>Free Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages;</hi> and therefore my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> says <hi>in his first Part of Institutes,</hi> Fol. 178. b. <hi>That such Gifts are almost grown out of use, and serve now principally for Moot Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and Questions in the Law, that thereupon were wont to arise.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <p n="8">8. Eightly, It hath been objected, That <hi>Geva</hi> was a base daughter of <hi>Hugh Lupus,</hi> and that she had Lands given her in <hi>Frank Marriage,</hi> as doth appear by this following Deed.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                           <body>
                              <div type="deed">
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>RAnulfus Comes Cestriae Willielmo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stabulario &amp; Roberto Dapifero &amp; omnibus Baronibus suis &amp; hominibus Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64436:40"/>&amp; Anglicis totius Angliae salutem. Scia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis me dedisse &amp; concessisse Gevae Ridell fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae Comitis Hughes Draytunam cum perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentiis in libero conjugio, sicuti Comes Hughes ei in libero conjugio dedit &amp; eon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessit. Et teneat bene &amp; in pace, honorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, &amp; liberè, ut melius &amp; liberius tenuit tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Hugonis Comitis &amp; aliorum meorum antecessorum eisdem consuetudinibus &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertatibus. Testibus Gilberto filio Ricar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, &amp; Adelizâ sorore mea, &amp; Willielmo Blundo, &amp; Alexandro de Tresgor, &amp; Roge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro de Bellocampo, &amp; Willielmo de Sais, &amp; Roberto de Sais, &amp; Ricardo filio Aluredi, &amp; Hugone filio Osberti, &amp; Henrico de Chalder: Apud Saintonam.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>To which I answer first, That there is no proof at all, that the said <hi>Geva</hi> was a Bastard; And secondly, That the said Gift was not a Gift in <hi>Frank Marriage.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>First, I say, there is no proof that the said <hi>Geva</hi> was a Bastard, neither doth any Author either ancient or modern call her so, except Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> alone. And she is by one very knowing person ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly said to be a legitimate Child. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:64436:41"/>Sir <hi>Peter</hi> hath very often positively said, that <hi>Ordericus</hi> did say she was a a Bastard, but in his <hi>Second Reply,</hi> (which is the sixth Treatise he did write concerning <hi>Amicia</hi>) after he had been many times told, that <hi>Ordericus</hi> had said no such thing, he is forced <hi>page</hi> 3. to confess, that <hi>Ordericus</hi> hath not these very words <hi>(Geva is a Bastard)</hi> but yet he pretends, that by sure consequence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows out of the words of <hi>Ordericus,</hi> that she was a <hi>Bastard,</hi> which (he says) is all one to effect; And to make this out, he cites <hi>Ordericus. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Ecclesiasticae Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae,</hi> Pag. 522. whose words are these <hi>E Pellicibus plurimam Sobolem utriusque sexûs genuit, quae diversis infortuniis ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorpta penè tota periit: Ermentrudem filiam Hugonis de Claromonte Beluacensi uxorem duxit, ex quâ Ricardum Cestrensis Comita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tûs haeredem genuit, qui juvenis liberisque Carens naufragio periit.</hi> But because those words do not prove that <hi>Geva</hi> was one of those <hi>Bastards</hi> which <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> had, he doth not so very much insist upon them, as he doth upon what <hi>Ordericus</hi> doth write, <hi>Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>Ecclesiast. Hist. pag.</hi> 787. where <hi>Ordericus</hi> says thus, <hi>Ricardus Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherrimus puer, quem so lune ex Ermentrude
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:64436:41"/>filiâ Hugonis de Claromonte genuit, Consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum (Cestriae scilicet) tenuit;</hi> For he says that these words of <hi>Ordericus</hi> do put it out of doubt, that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got <hi>Richard</hi> on <hi>Ermentrude</hi> his Wife, and says that then by sure consequence out of those words it must needs follow, that <hi>Geva</hi> was one of the Earl's <hi>Bastards,</hi> she being no Child by <hi>Ermentrude</hi> his Wife; But by those words, <hi>Richardus autem pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherrimus puer quem solum ex Ermentrude filia Hugonis de Claromonte genuit; Orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus</hi> might as well mean, that he was the onely Son which Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had by <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentrude,</hi> as that he was the onely Child that he had by her; For there is no neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity to take the word <hi>solum</hi> adverbially, neither is it marked as an Adverb in <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericus</hi>'s Book, though it be so in Sir <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s, and yet in <hi>Ordericus</hi>'s Book, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs are usually marked. And though Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> alledge, that <hi>Ordericus</hi> doth not say <hi>quem solum filium,</hi> as I inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret him, but indefinitely, <hi>quem solum ex Ermentrude genuit;</hi> and so, whether <hi>solum</hi> be understood adverbially, or whether it be taken for a noun, no more can be made of it in <hi>English</hi> than thus, <hi>Richard</hi> a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Youth, whom only Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> begot
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:64436:42"/>on <hi>Ermentruae,</hi> &amp;c. and so, whether we English it, whom only he begot, or whom he only begot, it retains the same sense, and shews that no other person, either Son or Daughter, was begotten on <hi>Ermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude</hi> by Earl <hi>Hugh.</hi> I must take leave to dissent from him herein; For, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this expression of <hi>quem solum genuit,</hi> doth amount to as much as if he had said, <hi>quem solum filium genuit;</hi> which if it do, then (notwithstanding the said expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> might possibly have a Daughter or Daughters by the said <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentrude;</hi> For, to what Antecedent can the word <hi>quem</hi> so properly relate, as to the word <hi>puer?</hi> and if so, then <hi>quem so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum puerum,</hi> is as much as <hi>quem solum fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> and so doth not exclude him from having a Daughter or Daughters by the said <hi>Ermentrude;</hi> For, though the word <hi>puer</hi> be by some understood to signifie a Child of either Sex, as Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> also seems to take it in his <hi>Historical An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities,</hi> pag. 113. &amp; 114. (But mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed 121. &amp; 122.) Yet Mr. <hi>Gouldman</hi> in his Dictionary will tell us that it is a mistake, where on the word <hi>puer</hi> he thus writes, <hi>Nonnullis habetur communis gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, sed male, ex Ovidiano illo carmine, de Iphide puella in puernm mutata,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64436:42"/>Dona puer solvit quae foemina voverat Iphis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And though Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> says, that <hi>Geva</hi> could not be by any former Wife, because Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had never any other Wife; yet that is more than ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> or I know; for there were many things done in those Ages which never came to our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges.</p>
                     <p>Neither is there any force in what Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth alledge, that probably if <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> had any more Legitimate Children by his Wife besides Earl <hi>Richard,</hi> either Son or Daughter, that <hi>Ordericus</hi> would have recorded them as well as others, being indeed his usual method through the whole course of his History. For he could have no Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Son but Earl <hi>Richard,</hi> unless he had another Wife besides <hi>Ermentrude (Orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus</hi> being express therein) and possibly for some Reasons he might have another Wife besides <hi>Ermentrude:</hi> But whether <hi>Geva</hi> was by a first or second Wife, I know no necessity to conclude that <hi>Ordericus</hi> should Record her, I finding no such
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:64436:43"/>usual method of his, as this which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> speaks of: For he doth not (that I see) make it his business to Record what Wives or Children the Earls of <hi>Chester,</hi> and other great Men had, but onely speaks of them occasionally, and so he doth also of some of their Illegitimate Children; but if he made it his design to give an exact account of these things, he ought to reckon <hi>Geva,</hi> either amongst the Lawful, Doubtful, or Illegitimate Children of <hi>Hugh Lupus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And as to Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s Objection, That if <hi>Geva</hi> had been Legitimate, her Issue ought to have succeeded into the Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Chester,</hi> rather than <hi>Randle de Meschines</hi> after the death of <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester;</hi> That doth not necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follow, whethersoever <hi>Geva</hi> was a lawful Daughter of <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> by a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Wife, or that she was his Daughter by his Wife <hi>Ermentrude:</hi> For if she was his Daughter by a former Wife, she would be but of the half Bloud to <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> and then <hi>Randle de Meschines</hi> would be Heir before her; But it seems to me, that <hi>Randle de Meschines</hi> was not the next Heir to Earl <hi>Richard;</hi> for as
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:64436:43"/>Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> in his <hi>Britannia,</hi> in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of <hi>Cheshire,</hi> tells us, [which is also spoken of by Sir <hi>Peter</hi> in his <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 105.] King <hi>William,</hi> commonly called <hi>The Conqueror,</hi> created <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> Count Palatine of <hi>Chester, Totum{que} hunc comitatum tenendum sibi, &amp; haeredibus ita libere ad Gladium: sicut ipse Rex tenebat Angliam ad coronam, dedit; (haec enim sunt verba Donationis) qui statim sibi Barones substituit,</hi> &amp;c. so that this Earldom by the words of the said Grant, being not tied up to the Heirs Males of the Body of the said <hi>Hugh Lupus,</hi> nor to the Heirs of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the said <hi>Hugh,</hi> but to his Heirs in general, if <hi>Randle de Meschines</hi> had been the next Heir to <hi>Hugh Lupus,</hi> the Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom would have descended to the said <hi>Randle,</hi> but that it did not do; for <hi>James York</hi> in his <hi>Ʋnion of Honor,</hi> pag. 105. says, That this <hi>Randle</hi> was made Earl by Grant of King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>First;</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in his <hi>Historical Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> pag. 118. (for which he cited <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericus,</hi> a contemporary Author, <hi>pag.</hi> 876.) tells us, that the said <hi>Randle</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored to King <hi>Henry</hi> all the Lands which he had by his Wife the Widow of <hi>Roger
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:64436:44"/>de Romara,</hi> for the Earldom of <hi>Chester;</hi> which he did not need to have done, if he had been the next Heir; so that I cannot imagine any reason of this new Grant to <hi>Randle de Meschines,</hi> unless <hi>Geva</hi> was a Legitimate Daughter; but if <hi>Geva</hi> was a Legitimate Daughter of <hi>Hugh Lupus,</hi> then there might a Case happen, which would make it necessary that whoever was Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> must have a new Grant; for if Earl <hi>Richard,</hi> when he died left two Sisters, viz. <hi>Geva</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Sister, the Earldom would be then at an end; for as you may see in <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi>'s <hi>Correction of Brooke,</hi> pag. 545. if an Earldom be conferred upon any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and his Heirs, if that person, or who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever else succeeds him doth die, leaving two or more Daughters, or two or more Sisters to be his Heirs, in this case the Earldom doth Escheate, and fall into the Kings hands, because it could not be divided; for though Lands may, yet <hi>Honor non potest dividi;</hi> and how easily might <hi>Geva</hi> have a Sister, who might die young presently after the death of <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> without being taken notice of by our Authors, doth clearly appear by the former Precedents
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:64436:44"/>in the like Cases; and if <hi>Geva</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Sister of hers were both living when Earl <hi>Richard</hi> died, the Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom would extinguish, and being once extinguished, could not revive again, upon the death of the said <hi>Geva's</hi> Sister; And whereas it hath been objected by Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in the 39 page of his answer, That if <hi>Geva</hi> had been Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, it is more than probable, she would have looked after the obtaining of so great an Inheritance, yea, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it too before <hi>Randle;</hi> Nay had she been but of the half Blood, she would by all probability have buzled hard for so great an Estate in those Ages, before she had lost it. In this Sir <hi>Peter</hi> was mistaken; for if she had been but of the half Blood, I have before proved that any Kinsman or Kinswoman, though never so remote, would have inherited Earl <hi>Richard</hi>'s Lands before the said <hi>Geva;</hi> and if <hi>Geva</hi> was Legitimate and sole Daughter to <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> by his Wife <hi>Ermentrude,</hi> and consequently on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sister of the whole Blood to Earl <hi>Richard,</hi> yet it doth not necessarily follow, that she would have had the Lands; for when <hi>Randle Blundevill</hi> died,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:64436:45"/>his Sisters of the whole Bloud, had not the Estate of the said <hi>Randle,</hi> but <hi>John Scot,</hi> eldest Son to <hi>Maude</hi> the eldest Sister of the said <hi>Randle,</hi> was Earl of <hi>Chester;</hi> and when the said <hi>John Scot</hi> died, leaving only Sisters to be his Heirs, none of the Husbands or Sons of any of the said Sisters of the said <hi>John Scot,</hi> was made Earl; and the said King <hi>Henry</hi> III. also laid that fair Inheritance unto the Domaine of the Crown, and assigned other Revenues elsewhere to the said Heirs. The words of Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> in his <hi>Britannia</hi> in his Description of <hi>Cheshire,</hi> speaking of <hi>John Scot</hi> are these, <hi>Qui cum itidem nulla suscepta prole diem obiisset, Rex Henricus tertius tam lauto patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio, oculum adjiciens, Domanio Regio ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scripsit, Johannis{que} sororibus alios alibi reditus assignavit; Ne (ut ipse Rex dixit) tanta haereditas inter colos diduceretur;</hi> And as the Sisters of the said <hi>Randle Blundevill</hi> and the Sisters of the said <hi>John Scot,</hi> though they did not inherit the Earldom, had some other Lands gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, and were well provided for, so <hi>Geva</hi> Sister of Earl <hi>Richard,</hi> as you may see in Sir <hi>William Dugdale</hi>'s first Part of the <hi>Baronage of</hi> England, <hi>pag.</hi> 34. <hi>b.</hi>
                        <pb n="79" facs="tcp:64436:45"/>had also Lands given unto her, and was married to <hi>Geffrey Ridell,</hi> who is there said to be an eminent Man in those days, <hi>viz.</hi> Justice of <hi>England</hi> under King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the First;</hi> and it is certain that when Earl <hi>Richard</hi> died, his Lands did not descend to the next Heir; for if <hi>Geva</hi> was his next Heir, she had them not; and if <hi>Geva</hi> was not his next Heir, then <hi>Randle de Bricasard,</hi> by some cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Randle de Micenis</hi> or <hi>Randle Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines</hi> was his next Heir, and though the said <hi>Randle de Meschines</hi> had the Lands of Earl <hi>Richard,</hi> Son of <hi>Hugh Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> yet they came not to him by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scent; for as I have before shewed out of <hi>Ordericus Vitalis,</hi> and out of Sir <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Leicester</hi>'s <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> the said <hi>Randle</hi> restored to King <hi>Henry the First,</hi> all the Land which he had by his Wife, the Widow of <hi>Roger de Romara</hi> for the Earldom of <hi>Chester;</hi> and it is also plain that the said <hi>Randle</hi> did give Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for the said Earl <hi>Richard</hi>'s Lands; for it appears <hi>Rot. Pip. de An.</hi> 5 <hi>Regis Steph. Rot.</hi> 12. <hi>M.</hi> 1. <hi>Linc.</hi> that in the said fifth year of King <hi>Stephen, Ranulph</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> (Son to the said <hi>Randle de Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines</hi>) is certified to be indebted to the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:64436:46"/>King in a thousand Pounds, <hi>De debito patris sui, pro terra Hugonis Comitis.</hi> So that here is no Proof at all, that the said <hi>Geva</hi> was an unlawful Child.</p>
                     <p>But secondly, If there had been any Proof, that the said <hi>Geva</hi> had been a Bastard, yet it would have been nothing to the Case in hand, because the said Gift unto the said <hi>Geva</hi> was not a Gift in Frank-Marriage; if we peruse what my Lord <hi>Coke upon Littleton</hi> says, <hi>fol.</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> he will there tell us, that these words <hi>In liberum Maritagium,</hi> are such words of Art, and so necessarily requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as they cannot be expressed by words equipollent or amounting to as much. As if a man give Lands to another with his Daughter <hi>in Connubio soluto ab omni servitio,</hi> &amp;c. yet there passeth in this Case but an Estate for Life; for seeing that these words <hi>In liberum Maritagium</hi> create an Estate of Inheritance against the general Rule of Law, the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth that they should be legally pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued. And in this Deed to <hi>Geva,</hi> the words are not <hi>in liberum Mritagium,</hi> but <hi>in libero Conjugio;</hi> and so are but like the words <hi>in connubio soluto ab om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:64436:46"/>servitio,</hi> which make but an Estate for life, and so might be passed either to to a Bastard, or any other person what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever. And if we look well on the Deed to <hi>Geva,</hi> it is worded as if it intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only an Estate for life, there being no mention of her Heirs, and running also in the Singular number, <hi>Et teneat bere &amp; in pace, &amp;c. ut melius &amp; liberius te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit, &amp;c.</hi> Also if we observe my Lord <hi>Coke upon Littleton,</hi> a little before <hi>fol.</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> he will tell us, that four things are incident to a Frank-Marriage? The first whereof is, that it be given for conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Marriage, either to a Man with a Woman, or as some have held, to a Woman with a Man, (and with this <hi>Bracton,</hi> lib. 2. cap. 7. doth accord.) And the fourth thing is, that the Donees shall hold freely of the Donor, till the fourth Degree be past (with which the old Treatise, called <hi>Fleta,</hi> lib. 3. cap. 11. doth agree) for both which Reasons, this Gift cannot be a Gift in Frank-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, because what is here given, is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Geva</hi> alone, and not to an Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band with her; there being here no Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nees, but one Donee onely, and the Estate was not to continue till the fourth
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:64436:47"/>Degree was past, but was only an Estate intended for the life of <hi>Geva,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears before; whereas what was given by Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> to <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> with his Daughter <hi>Amicia,</hi> and by <hi>Ralph Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi> to <hi>Henry de Alditelegh</hi> with his Daughter <hi>Bertred,</hi> was given in Free-Marriage, and their Heirs are mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in both the Deeds: It remains there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore clear, that the Deeds to <hi>Geva</hi> was not a Gift in Frank-Marriage, and is also very uncertain, whether <hi>Geva</hi> was a Bastard, as Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth suppose.</p>
                     <p>And though I believe the <hi>Bassets</hi> did afterwards enjoy the same Lands, which in the aforesaid Deed were given to <hi>Geva,</hi> because in <hi>Monasticon Anglicanum,</hi> Par. 1. p. 439. and in Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s <hi>Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Antiquities,</hi> p. 113. (but mis-print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 121.) I find <hi>Geffrey Rydel</hi> and <hi>Ralph Basset</hi> called the Heirs of the said <hi>Geva;</hi> as also that the said <hi>Drayton</hi> was called <hi>Drayton Basset,</hi> yet I do not know how or by vertue of what Deed, they did enjoy the same; for if these persons were the Heirs of her Body, and the aforesaid Deed a Gift in Frank-Marriage, why did not Earl <hi>Randle</hi> confirm or grant
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:64436:47"/>those Lands to her Heirs, as well as to her; and if they were not the Heirs of her Body, she could not be a Bastard; for as my Lord <hi>Coke on Littleton,</hi> fol. 3. b. tells us, a Bastard can have no Heir but of his own Body.</p>
                     <p>And whereas Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in the 45 page of his Answer to the <hi>Defence of Amicia</hi> says, that though my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> say that by those words <hi>in connubio soluto ab omni servitio,</hi> there passeth but an Estate for life, yet he saith not, that by those words <hi>in libero conjugio,</hi> or by the words <hi>in libero connubio,</hi> that there passeth onely an Estate for life; in this Sir <hi>Peter</hi> was also mistaken; for my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> positively says, that an Estate of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance cannot be passed by a Gift in Free-Marriage by any other words but those very words <hi>in liberum Maritagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> and that no equipollent words or words amounting to as much will serve the turn, as you may see <hi>Coke upon Little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, fol.</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> And in that very place, he tells us the reason thereof, is, because the words <hi>in liberum Maritagium</hi> create an Estate of Inheritance, against the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rule of the Law, and therefore
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:64436:48"/>the Law requireth that they should be legally pursued; and whereas S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                        <hi>Peter</hi> also objects, that by this Rule, a Gift of Lands by the words in Frank-Marriage in an English Deed, and a Gift <hi>de terres en Franke-Marriage,</hi> in a French Deed, would be void Grants; in this Sir <hi>Peter</hi> did also mistake; for the Latin words <hi>in liberum Maritagium,</hi> and the English words <hi>in Frank-Marriage,</hi> and the French words <hi>en Frank-Marriage,</hi> are the very same, although in different Languages; but the words <hi>in libero connubio,</hi> or <hi>in libero conjugio,</hi> or <hi>in Maritagio soluto ab omni servitio,</hi> or the French words, <hi>en Nopsage acquite de services,</hi> or the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish words <hi>in Wedlock Free from all Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices,</hi> and all such other like, are but equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollent words, and an Estate of Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance will not pass thereby.</p>
                     <p>And whereas the said Sir <hi>Peter</hi> being very desirous if he could to prove, that anciently Lands might be given in <hi>Free Marriage</hi> by other words than the words <hi>in Liberum Marritagium</hi> tells us in the second of his two Books, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 29. that <hi>Dos</hi> is called <hi>Marritagium</hi> in Dooms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Book; and for that end he cites
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:64436:48"/>
                        <hi>Coke upon Littleton,</hi> fol. 31. And also sayes that <hi>Dos</hi> is called <hi>Maritagium</hi> by <hi>Glanvill,</hi> lib. 7. cap. 1. And also tells us of a Deed made in the time of King <hi>John,</hi> transcribed in one of the <hi>Couchir</hi> Books of the <hi>Dutchy Office</hi> in <hi>Grays-Inne</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> Tom. 2. <hi>Honor sive soca de Bolingbroke,</hi> num. 26. pag 508. in which <hi>Saher de Quency,</hi> Earl of <hi>Winchester,</hi> gives to <hi>Hawise,</hi> Sister to the Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> and Wife of <hi>Robert,</hi> Son of the said <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her de Quency,</hi> certain Lands <hi>in liberum Donarium;</hi> which word <hi>Donarium,</hi> Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> sayes is misprinted for the word <hi>Dotarium,</hi> and thereupon sayes that the words <hi>in liberum Dotarium</hi> in that Deed, are the same with the words <hi>in liberum Maritagium;</hi> I shall therefore, before I answer the same, give you the words of the said Deed, as I find it in Sir <hi>Peter's Historical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 133.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                           <body>
                              <div type="book_excerpt">
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>SAherus de Quency Comes Wintoniae, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Hominibus &amp; Amicis suis, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentibus &amp; futuris, salutem. Sciatis, me concessisse &amp; dedisse &amp; praesenti Chartâ meâ confirmâsse Roberto de Quency Filio meo
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:64436:49"/>&amp; Haeredi ad dandum in liberum Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium Hawisiae Sorori Comitis Cestriae, Ʋxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ejusdem Roberti, Bucehebeiam &amp; Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesset, &amp; Bradeham, &amp; Herdewich, cum omnibus earundem terrarum pertinentiis, pro centum Libratis terrae: Et si hae predictae terrae non valeant per annum centum Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras, Ego in aliis terris meis de propriâ Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditate meâ in Anglia, ei tantum perficiam, quòd plenariè habeat centum Libratas terrae per visum &amp; considerationem legalium Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum hominum videlicet, Comitis Cestriae, &amp; meorum. Et praeterea dedi eidem Roberto Feoda duorum Militum, scilicet, Feodum Matthei Turpin in Winterslawa in Wilte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire, pro servitio Feodi unius Militis, ad dandum simul cum terris nominatis praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae Hawisiae Ʋxori suae in liberum Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium. Testibus his, Comite Davide, Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmo Comite de Ferrars, Philippo de Orreby, Roberto de Basingham, Ricardo de Lindes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, Willielmo de Grumpington, Henrico de Braibroc, Willielmo de Syelford, David Giffard, Willielmo Picot, Hugone &amp; Iho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma &amp; Henrico Dispensariis, Waltero de Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventrey, Waltero Daivilla, &amp; multis aliis.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:64436:49"/>
                     <p>And now as you may see in the 29th <hi>page,</hi> of the 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg> of his two Books, he says, That in his <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> the word <hi>Donarium</hi> was there misprinted for the word <hi>Dotarium;</hi> whereas the word <hi>Dotarium</hi> is not in the said Copy which he cites, as a knowing Friend of mine doth inform me, who, at my request, did carefully examine the same in one of the <hi>Couchir</hi> Books in the <hi>Dutchy Office</hi> in <hi>Grays-Inn;</hi> but the word is <hi>Donarium,</hi> which probably the Transcriber did mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake for <hi>Donarium,</hi> the <hi>u</hi> and <hi>n</hi> being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently written alike, and the <hi>v</hi> conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant not then used. But if the word had been <hi>Dotarium,</hi> it would not signifie <hi>Marriage,</hi> as he doth fancy, although <hi>Dos</hi> in Doomsday Book be called <hi>Maritagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um:</hi> For <hi>Dos</hi> is twofold, and that <hi>Dos</hi> which is <hi>Dotarium,</hi> is the same with <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> which we in <hi>English</hi> call <hi>Dower,</hi> and is not that <hi>Dos</hi> which sometimes is called <hi>Maritagium:</hi> For this see <hi>Glanvil, lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. whose words are these, <hi>Dos duobus modis dicitur, dos enim dicitur vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garitèr, id quod aliquis liber homo dat spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sae suae ad ostium Ecclesiae tempore desponsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis suae,</hi> &amp;c. And lib. 7. cap. 1. <hi>In
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:64436:50"/>alia enim acceptione, accipitur Dos secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Leges Romanas,</hi> (which 3 last words, with some others, Sir <hi>Peter</hi> leaves out in the 8th <hi>page</hi> of the first of his two Books) <hi>secundum quas proprie appellatur dos, id quod cum muliere datur viro, quod vulgariter dicitur Maritagium;</hi> Now that <hi>Dotarium,</hi> is that <hi>Dos</hi> which is <hi>Dower,</hi> and not that <hi>Dos</hi> which is called <hi>Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium,</hi> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> may see in Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi>'s <hi>Glossary,</hi> Printed at <hi>London</hi> 1664. page 174. whose words are these:
<q>¶ <hi>De eo Dotis genere, quod uxoribus constituunt Angli.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>¶ <hi>Doarium, Dodarium, Dotarium, Dauarium, Dotalitium.] Omnia recte interpretatur vernaculum nostrum Douer, non Latinum dos. Est enim proprie dos, illud quod maritus accipit cum uxore haec vero id quod in remunerationem dotis, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portat uxor.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And Sir <hi>Peter</hi> did very well know, that what is given in the aforesaid Deed, was only given as a Dower or Jointure, and not as a Gift in <hi>Free Marriage,</hi> as you may see in the 132 <hi>page</hi> of his <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> where he thus writes:</p>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:64436:50"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hawise,</hi> fourth Daughter of Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> by <hi>Bertred,</hi> married <hi>Robert Quency,</hi> Son and Heir of <hi>Saher de Quency,</hi> Earl of <hi>Winchester.</hi> She had the Earldom of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> to wit, the Castle and Honor of <hi>Bolingbroke,</hi> and all the Lands of Earl <hi>Randle</hi> in <hi>Lindsey</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> in <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colnshire,</hi> for which she gave 50 <abbr>l.</abbr> for Relief. On <hi>Hawise</hi> was estated for
<note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> Jointure, <hi>Bukby, Grantesset, Bradeham,</hi> and <hi>Herdwick,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by this Deed in the Couchir Book of the <hi>Dutchy</hi> Office, <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Honor sive Soca de Bolingbroke;</hi> num. 26. pag. 508.</p>
                     <p>So that you see Sir <hi>Peter</hi> hath former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confessed, that this Gift <hi>in liberum Donarium,</hi> was only a Jointure setled on the said <hi>Hawise;</hi> and it could not be a Gift <hi>in liberum Maritagium,</hi> because <hi>Saher de Quincy</hi> doth not give the Lands there mentioned, unto <hi>Hawise</hi> the Wife of his Son <hi>Robert</hi> (as Sir <hi>Peter</hi> says he did) but he gives them to his Son <hi>Robert ad dandum Hawisiae uxori ejusdem Roberti.</hi> And though a Man may settle Lands in Joynture upon his Wife, yet he cannot
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:64436:51"/>give Lands unto her in Free-Marriage, for that would be to give Lands unto himself; and whereas Sir <hi>Peter</hi> in the 26 and 27 <hi>pages</hi> of the second of his two Books, tells us, that the words <hi>in liberum Maritagium,</hi> in the more ancient Ages, were not by Law so strictly required, and sayes this is clear out of <hi>Glanvil,</hi> lib. 7. cap. 18. where he tells us, That a Grant of Land with any Woman <hi>in Maritagio, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendum praedictam terram sibi &amp; haeredibus liberam &amp; quietam ab omni servitio, à se &amp; haeredibus suis, versùs capitalem Dominum;</hi> This was a good Grant <hi>in libero Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio,</hi> and was as good as if the words had been <hi>in libero Maritagio:</hi> and therefore the words of my Lord <hi>Cook</hi> touching <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berum Maritagium</hi> reach not the age of <hi>Glanvill,</hi> so as alwayes then to be tyed up to those very words, and no other. Sir <hi>Peter</hi> therein fathers upon Mr. <hi>Glanvill</hi> what he never said or meant; for Mr. <hi>Glanvill</hi> doth not say that Lands might be given with a Woman in <hi>Frank Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> by other words than the words <hi>in liberum Maritagium;</hi> neither doth Sir <hi>Peter</hi> say right, when he affirms that Mr. <hi>Glanvill</hi> sayes, That a Grant of Land may be given with any Woman <hi>in Maritagio,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:64436:51"/>Habendum praedictam terram sibi &amp; haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus liberam &amp; quietam ab omni servitio, à se &amp; haeredibus suis, versus capitalem Dominum;</hi> For Mr. <hi>Glanvill</hi> only tells us, That <hi>liberum dicitur Maritagium, quando aliquis liber homo aliquam partem terrae suae dat cum aliquâ Muliere</hi> (that is, not with any Woman, but with some Woman, <hi>viz.</hi> one of the Kindred) <hi>alicui in Maritagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ita quod ab omni servitio terra illa sit quieta, &amp; à se &amp; haeredibus suis, versus ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalem Dominum acquietanda: &amp; in hac quidem libertate ita stabit terra illa usque ad tertium haeredem: nec interim tenebuntur haeredes inde facere aliquod homagium: Post tertium verò haeredem, ad debitum servitium terra ipsa revertetur; &amp; homagium inde capietur.</hi> All which hath been proved to be Law at this day, as well as it was in <hi>Glanvil</hi>'s time.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <p n="9">IX. Ninthly, It hath been objected by Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> that <hi>Joan</hi> the Wife of <hi>Llhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellyn ap Jorwerth,</hi> Prince of <hi>Northwales,</hi> was base Daughter of <hi>John</hi> King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and that there are several Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, that Lands were given to the said <hi>Joan</hi> in <hi>Frank Marriage.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:64436:52"/>
                     <p>To which I Answer:</p>
                     <p>First, That it is not absolutely certain that the said <hi>Joane</hi> was a Bastard.</p>
                     <p>And secondly, That those Precedents which are alledged by Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> of Lands given in <hi>Frank Marriage</hi> to the said <hi>Joane</hi> are not any of them Gifts in <hi>Frank Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> and therefore will not at all work any thing in the case in hand.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. First let us examine whether it be certain, that the said <hi>Joane</hi> was a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stard or not; and in order thereunto, let us observe how many Wives the said King <hi>John</hi> had. First, he married <hi>Alais</hi> Daughter of the Earl of <hi>Moriana,</hi> in the year 1173. as we may read in <hi>Brompton</hi>'s <hi>Chronicon,</hi> col. 1082. n. 35. <hi>Hoveden (Faankfurt</hi> Edition printed 1601.) pag. 532. n. 5. <hi>Matt. Paris</hi> (put out by Dr. <hi>Watts</hi>) pag. 127. n. 5. (which Editions of <hi>Hoveden</hi> and <hi>Paris,</hi> I do all along follow) and the like we may find in <hi>Vincent upon Brooke,</hi> pag. 133. who also there tells us, that by <hi>Moriana</hi> is not meant <hi>Moreton,</hi> but <hi>Savoy,</hi> with which
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:64436:52"/>
                        <hi>Matt. Par.</hi> p. 751. n. 46. doth also ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; but the said <hi>Alais</hi> being then scarcely seven years of age, as we may see in <hi>Matt. Par.</hi> p. 127. n. 6. and dying presently after, the said King <hi>John</hi> could not possibly have any Issue by that Wife.</p>
                     <p>Soon after this, <hi>viz.</hi> in the year 1176. (as you may read in <hi>Hoveden,</hi> p. 553. n. 46. and <hi>Matt. Paris,</hi> p. 132. n. 29.) there was an Agreement for a Marriage to be had between the said <hi>John</hi> (then youngest Son of the said King <hi>Henry</hi> II.) and a Daughter of <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester,</hi> Son of <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Glocester;</hi> which said Daughter is not there named, but her name was <hi>Hawisia</hi> or <hi>Avis,</hi> and the Marriage afterwards took effect, but he was divorced from her in the year 1200. as will anon appear.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, Immediately upon his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce he married <hi>Isabel</hi> Daughter of the Earl of <hi>Engolisme,</hi> who was his last Wife; for she survived him, and by her he had Issue (as will be agreed by all) <hi>Henry</hi> (afterwards King <hi>Henry the Third) Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> Earl of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> (afterwards King
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:64436:53"/>of the <hi>Romans) Joane</hi> Wife of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Second</hi> King of <hi>Scots, Eleanor,</hi> first married to <hi>William Marshall</hi> the younger, Earl of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to <hi>Simon Mountford,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester,</hi> as also <hi>Isabel,</hi> who was sixth Wife to <hi>Frederick the Second,</hi> Emperor of <hi>Germany.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But King <hi>John</hi> marrying the said <hi>Isabel</hi> in the year 1200. could have no Child by her old enough to be married to the said <hi>Lhewellin</hi> in the year 1204.</p>
                     <p>The only question then will be, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lhewellins</hi> Wife was King <hi>John</hi>'s Legitimate Daughter by his Wife <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wisia,</hi> for that she must be if she was Legitimate; and the Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the said <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Hawisia</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing agreed on, in the year 1176, the said <hi>Hawisia</hi> might very well have a Daughter old enough to be married to the said <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> in the year 1204.</p>
                     <p>To prove that the said <hi>Joane</hi> Wife of <hi>Lhewellin</hi> was a Bastard, Sir <hi>Peter Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> in the 101 page of that Book, which he calls the <hi>Case of</hi> Amicia <hi>truly Stated,</hi>
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:64436:53"/>cites these several Authorities. <hi>Vincent upon Brook,</hi> p. 204. <hi>Speed</hi>'s History, <hi>p.</hi> 518. <hi>Stow</hi>'s <hi>Annals Augmented by</hi> How's p. 167, 168. <hi>Policronicon</hi> Translated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to English by <hi>Trevisa,</hi> lib. 7. cap. 33. <hi>Cambden</hi>'s <hi>Britannia in Shropshire,</hi> p. 453. also <hi>Daniel and Fabian,</hi> and <hi>Mill</hi>'s <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of Honour,</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi>'s History, who do all call her Base Daughter of King <hi>John;</hi> and no Author at all calls her lawful Daughter, or reckoneth her among the Daughters of any of his Wives: some of them say she was begot by King <hi>John</hi> on <hi>Agatha de Ferrars.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To which I answer first, that I believe it doth not yet certainly appear, by any Deed, Record, or Contemporary Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, that the said <hi>Joane</hi> was a Bastard, and by consequence, there is no absolute proof that she was Illegitimate; for the Author of the <hi>Polycronicon</hi> is the first of those Authors which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or I have taken notice of, who doth call the said <hi>Joane</hi> a Bastard, and the said Author of the <hi>Polycronicon</hi> (as <hi>Vossius</hi> tells us in his Book, <hi>de Historicis Latinis, pag.</hi> 487.) dyed in the year 1363. which
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:64436:54"/>was 159 years after the said <hi>Llhewellin</hi> married the said <hi>Joane.</hi> But all those Records, Deeds, and ancient Authors, which I have seen do call her Daughter onely, without any Brand of Bastardy at all; For this, see the Copy of King <hi>John</hi>'s Precept to the Sheriff of <hi>Shropshire,</hi> to make Livery of the said Lordship of <hi>Ellesmere.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <head>Ex Rot. Clauso de anno sexto Regis Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannis (in arce Lond) membrana <hi>7.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>REX Vicecom. Salop. Salutem. Scias quod dedimus dilecto filio nostro Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellino manerium de Ellesmere, eum omnibus pertinentiis suis, in Maritagio filiaenostrae, Et ideo, &amp;c. Teste, &amp;c. apud Wigorn.</hi> 23 <hi>Martii.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                     <p> So also.</p>
                     <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <head>Claus. <hi>2.</hi> H. <hi>3.</hi> M. <hi>1.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>MAndatum est Vic. War. quod plenam seisinam habere faciat Leolino Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipi Norwall. de Villa de Budiford cumper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentiis suis quam Dominus Johannes Rex pater Domini Henrici Regis dedit ei in Maritagium cum Johannae sorore Henrici Regis uxore ipsius Leulini. Test.</hi>
                              <note n="*" place="bottom">Scilicet Willielmo Marescallo Comite Pembrochiae tunc Rectore Regis &amp; Regni.</note>
                              <hi>Comite apud Westm.</hi> 10. <hi>Oct.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                     <p>So also.</p>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:64436:54"/>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                           <body>
                              <div type="charter">
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Ex Rotulo Chartarum de anno sexto Regis Johannis, numero</hi> 32.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Charta Lewellini Principis Walliae.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>JOhannes Dei gratia, &amp;c. Sciatis, nos dedisse, concessisse, &amp; hac Charta nostra confirmasse, Lewellino Principi Northwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae, in Maritagium cum Johanna filia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra Castrum de Ellesmara cum omnibus pertinentiis suis:</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>So also <hi>Matt. Paris,</hi> who was contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary with the said <hi>Joane,</hi> p. 231. n. 52. calls her the <hi>Kings daughter,</hi> without the addition of <hi>Bastard,</hi> or any thing tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereto; his words are these, <hi>Quo facto, venit alius nuncius ex parte filiae ejus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Regis uxoris videlicet Leolini Regis Walliae, &amp;c.</hi> Also in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> III. her Son <hi>David</hi> is by him (p. 537. 569. and in many other places) stiled <hi>Nepos Regis,</hi> and p. 695. called <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos Regis ex Sorore;</hi> and p. 570. he is said to be <hi>propinquus Regi consanguini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:64436:55"/>
                     <p>Also <hi>Knighton,</hi> col. 2417. n. 42. thus sayes of her, <hi>Rex Johannes dedit filiam suam Leolino Principi Walliae in uxorem, &amp; cum ea dedit castellum &amp; totum territorium de Ellesmere in confinio Walliae.</hi> And the King himself in the aforesaid Record gives her the title of <hi>filiae nostrae.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Also in <hi>lib. Barlings</hi> (in which Book, besides what concerns the Abby of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> in <hi>Lincolnshire,</hi> there are certain An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals (beginning <hi>An.</hi> 1050. and ending <hi>An.</hi> 1231.) she is called the said Kings daughter, without the Addition of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stard;</hi> there being these words onely in the said Book in Sir <hi>John Cotton</hi>'s Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which do concern the said <hi>Joane,</hi> viz. <hi>Lewelinus disponsavit filiam Regis I.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So also <hi>Vanghan</hi> in his <hi>British Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> (as he is cited by Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in the first of his two Books, <hi>pag.</hi> 28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 29.) gives us out of an old Manuscript these very words:</p>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:64436:55"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LEwellinus Gervasii filius princeps Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae, primo desponsavit Tanglwyst, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Lhowarch Vychan de qua genuit Grif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fith &amp; Gwlades ddu, quondam uxorem Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulphi de Mortuo mari: Post mortem dicta Tanglwyst, idem Lewelynus desponsavit Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannam, filiam Johannis Regis Angliae, de qua genuit David, principem; &amp; Guelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant uxorem Johannis Lacy Comitis Lincol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae, &amp; Angharad primo desponsatam Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanni de Brewis Domino de Brechon; post cujus decessum, desponsata fuit Malgoni Vachan ap Maelgon ap Rees, &amp; ex eadem uxore genuit filiam quae maritata est Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Scotico, Comiti Cestriae, qui fuit nepos Ranulphi Comitis Cestriae ex parte soro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris suae.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So that we see in all these Recorde, Deeds and old Authors, there is not one word tending to prove that the said <hi>Joane</hi> was an illegitimate Child.</p>
                     <p>Also our later Authors, as <hi>Vincent</hi> and others, who say that she was illegitimate, do many of them say, That King <hi>John</hi> was divorced from his second Wife, as well for that she was barren, as within
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:64436:56"/>the degrees of Consanguinity; which barrenness, if it could be made to appear, would certainly prove the said <hi>Joane</hi> to be a <hi>Bastard;</hi> And this opinion hath so far prevailed in this last Age, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as learned Mr. <hi>Cambden,</hi> as we may see in his <hi>Britannia</hi> in Latine printed at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> 1607. p. 259. speaking of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce of the said <hi>Hawisia,</hi> (whose name he mistakes, and calls <hi>Isabel</hi>) doth only use these words, <hi>illam repudiatam,</hi> Doctor <hi>Philemon Holland</hi> in the English Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (unjustly) renders it thus, That King <hi>John</hi> did repudiate her upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, as well that she was barren, as that they were within the prohibited degrees of Consanguinity. But our ancient Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storians say nothing of her being barren. For this see <hi>Hoveden</hi> (who was living all the time that <hi>Hawisia</hi> was Wife to King <hi>John</hi>) p. 803. n. 34. in the year 1200.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>EOdem Anno factum est divortium in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Johannem Regem Angliae &amp; Hawisam uxorem suam filiam Willielmi Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitis Gloucestriae per Heliam Burdegalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sem Archiepiscopum, &amp; per Willielmum Pictavensem, &amp; per Henricum Sanctonen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sem Episcopos: erant enim affines in tertio
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:64436:56"/>gradu consanguinitatis. Facto itaque Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vortio inter Johannem Regem Angliae, &amp; uxorem suam, ipse Rex Angliae consilio Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini sui Philippi Regis Franciae duxit sibi in uxorem Isabel filiam Ailmari Comitis de Engolismo, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So also <hi>Matt. Paris</hi> (living in the time of the said <hi>Joane</hi>) p. 200. n. 23. in the said year 1200.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>EOdem tempore celebrato Divortio inter Regem Anglorum &amp; uxorem suam Hawisam Comitis Gloverniae filiam; eo quod affines erant in tertio gradu consanguinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis; Duxit idem Rex, consilio Regis Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum Isabel filiam Comitis Engolismi.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So also <hi>Mat. Westminster</hi> in that Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1570. lib. 2. p. 76. n. 25.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ANno gratiae. M. CC. Rex Johannes Isabellam filiam Comitis Engolismi duxit in uxorem, &amp; dominica proxima ante festum sancti Dyonisii consecrata est in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginam ab Huberto Cantuariensi Archiepis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copo, quia celebratum fuit divortium inter ipsum &amp; Hawisiam, Comitis Gloverniae fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:64436:57"/>eò quod contingebant se in tertio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanguinitatis gradu.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>See also the words of <hi>Rad. de Diceto,</hi> (who lived in the time of the said King <hi>John</hi>) col. 706. n. 5. which words are these:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>CElebratum est divortium inter Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Regem Angliae &amp; filiam comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Glocestriae in Normannia, ab Episcopis Lisoriensi, Baiocensi, Abrincensi, &amp; aliis Episcopis qui interfuerant, quam ipse tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore patris permissione Romanae Ecclesiae duxerat in uxorem cum Comitatibus de Glocestria, de Sumersatum, de Devenesire, de Cornwaille, &amp; aliis quamplurimis per Angliam honoribus. Set ille sublimioris thori spe raptatus, consilio pravorum eam abegit, unde magnam summi Pontificis, sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet, Innocentii tertii, &amp; totius curiae Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae indignationem incurrit, praesumens temere contra leges &amp; canones dissolvere quod eorum suerat auctoritate colliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>See also <hi>Lipsius</hi> in his <hi>Monita &amp; exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla politica,</hi> printed at <hi>Amsterdam</hi> 1630. p. 220. who there tells us, that <hi>sterilitas
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:64436:57"/>sola est causa divortii, quoties apud principes valuit,</hi> and then judge if she had been barren, whether that would not have been alledged as a cause of King <hi>Johns</hi> putting her away, as well as his desire of match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into a more sublime Family; And (which is very observable, all those Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors which Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> cites in the said 101 Page, or who I have met with, who do either say that King <hi>Johns</hi> said Wife was barren, or do call the said <hi>Joane</hi> the Wife of the said <hi>Lhewellin</hi> a <hi>Bastard,</hi> do not any one of them (except Sir <hi>Richard Baker</hi>) know the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Name of the said divorced Wife of the said King <hi>John,</hi> but are either silent therein, or else (which almost all of them do) do call her <hi>Isabell</hi> instead of <hi>Hawisia;</hi> and how are those persons like to know whether she had Issue or not, seeing they did not so much as know her true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Name? Also Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi> in his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections upon <hi>Brooke,</hi> pag. 204. cites a Deed of which Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in his Advertisement to the Reader, <hi>pag.</hi> 60. gives us these words, and no more.</p>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:64436:58"/>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                           <body>
                              <div type="book_excerpt">
                                 <head>Chartae <hi>14.</hi> Hen. <hi>3.</hi> membrana. <hi>5.</hi>
                                 </head>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Pro Roberto de Audley.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Henricus Rex salutem. Inspeximus Chartam Richardi de Landa in haec ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>SCiant praesentes &amp; futuri, quod ego Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardus de Landa dedi &amp; concessi &amp; bac praesenti Charta mea confirmavi Roberto de Audley &amp; haeredibus suis in liberum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagium cum Johanna filia mea centum &amp; tres solidatos &amp; quatuor denaratas terrae cum Pertinentiis in Insula Scapeya. Hiis Testibus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>But Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> omits a great part of the said Deed, and amongst the rest these words, <hi>Sicut carta Regis Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis quam inde habeo rationabiliter Testatur,</hi> which words do shew that King <hi>John</hi> gave those said Lands to the said <hi>Richard de Landa.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:64436:58"/>
                     <p>Now though this Deed doth prove that <hi>Joane</hi> the Wife of <hi>Robert de Aud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> was by the Law of <hi>England,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Richard de Landa,</hi> yet Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi> in the said 204 page of his <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections upon Brooke</hi> (being that very page in which he cites the said Deed) tells us that this <hi>Joane,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert de Audley,</hi> was really the Base Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of King <hi>John,</hi> begotten on his Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour <hi>Agatha</hi> the Daughter to <hi>William de Ferrars,</hi> the second Earl <hi>Ferrars</hi> of that Christian Name, as he says shall be more largely discovered in the Life of King <hi>John;</hi> which if so, the said <hi>Agatha</hi> was then the Wife of the said <hi>Richard de Landa.</hi> And that Kings did sometime beget Children on the Bodies of other Mens Wives, which yet were owned as the base Children of the said Kings is not without Precedent; for (to instance in no more) you may find in Sir <hi>Richard Baker</hi>'s Chronicle, printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1665. pag. 66. That King <hi>Henry the Second,</hi> by his famous Concubine the Wife of <hi>Ralpe Blewet,</hi> a Knight, had a Son named <hi>Morgan,</hi> who was Provost of <hi>Beverley,</hi> and being to be elected Bishop of <hi>Durham,</hi> went to <hi>Rome</hi> for a
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:64436:59"/>Dispensation, because being a Bastard, he was else uncapable: But the Pope refusing to grant it, unless he would pass as the Son of <hi>Blewet,</hi> he absolutely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, he would for no cause in the World deny his Father, and chose ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to lose the Dignity of the Place, than of his Bloud, as being the Son, though but the base Son of a King. But the said Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi> mistakes this <hi>Joane,</hi> Wife of <hi>Robert de Audley,</hi> to be the same <hi>Joane</hi> who was Wife of <hi>Lhewellin</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales;</hi> for he says that after the death of <hi>Lewellin,</hi> she was re-married to <hi>Robert de Audley,</hi> which cannot be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause as appears before, <hi>Lhewellin</hi> was Husband to his Wife <hi>Joane</hi> in the year 1204. and as you may find in the <hi>Welsh</hi> History, put out by Dr. <hi>Powell,</hi> pag. 293. The said <hi>Joane</hi> Daughter to King <hi>John,</hi> and Princess of <hi>Wales,</hi> died in the Spring, 1237. and was buried upon the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoar, within the Isle of <hi>Anglesey,</hi> at <hi>Lhanvaes,</hi> as her pleasure was, where the Prince did build a House of <hi>Bare-foot Fryers,</hi> over her Grave; But the said <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> as you may see in the said <hi>Welsh</hi> History, pag. 298. and in Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 47.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:64436:59"/>and in <hi>Matt. Paris,</hi> put out by Dr. <hi>Watts,</hi> pag. 525. died <hi>tertio Idus Aprilis, scilicet die sancti Guthlaci, Anno Christi,</hi> 1240. so that he outlived his said Wife <hi>Joane</hi> three years; and therefore the said <hi>Joane de Audley</hi> could not be that <hi>Joane</hi> who was Wife of the said <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> but must of necessity be another <hi>Joane.</hi> And why might not other Writers mistake this <hi>Joane</hi> Wife of <hi>Robert de Audley,</hi> to be the same <hi>Joane</hi> who was Wife of <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> as well as Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi> did; and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on call <hi>Joane</hi> the Wife of <hi>Lhewellin</hi> a Bastard. But though Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi> do here promise to discover more fully in the Life of King <hi>John,</hi> that <hi>Joane</hi> the Wife of <hi>Robert de Audley</hi> was the Daughter of King <hi>John,</hi> by the said <hi>Agatha de Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rars,</hi> yet because the said Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi> did not (that I can find) live to write the Life of the said King <hi>John,</hi> so that I cannot learn what Arguments he would have brought for the further discovery of what he did undertake; I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the present wave the same, and not conclude that she was Legitimate, although she might be so, for any thing that doth yet to the contrary ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:64436:60"/>
                     <p>Secondly, Sir <hi>Peter Leceister</hi> objects that <hi>Lhewellin</hi> gave with <hi>Hellen</hi> his Daughter unto <hi>John Scot,</hi> Earl of <hi>Cbester,</hi> the Mannor of <hi>Budeford</hi> in <hi>Warwick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> and the Mannor of <hi>Suttehel</hi> in <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestershire, In libero Maritagio cum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus pertinentiis sicut Dominus Johannes Rex ea illi dedit in libero Maritagio,</hi> and therefore says, that nothing can be more clear than that the Gift of <hi>Budeford</hi> and <hi>Suttehel</hi> with the said <hi>Joane</hi> Wife of <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> was an express Gift in Frank-Marriage. And for the proving of this, he gives us this Agreement or Deed, which he supposeth to be made about <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1222. 6 <hi>H.</hi> 3.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>HAEcest conventio facta inter Dominum Ranulfum Comitem Cestriae &amp; Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colniae, &amp; Dominum Lhewellinum Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pem Northwalliae; Quod Johannes de Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ, nepos praedicti Comitis de sorore, suâ primogenita, ducet in uxorem Helenam filiam ipsius Lhewellini: ita quod dictus Lhewellinus dabit dicto Johanni in libero Maritagio totum manerium de Budeford in Warewied, &amp; manerium de Suttehele in
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:64436:60"/>Comitatu Wigorniae cum omnibus pertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis, sicut Dominus Johannes rex ea illi dedit in libero maritagio: Et totum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerium de Welneton in Comitatu Salopes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buriae, cum omnibus pertinentiis infrà vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam &amp; extrà. Habendum dicto Johanni, &amp; haeredibus suis ex dictâ Helenâ prove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nientibus, sicut idem Lhewellinus ea aliquo tempore melius &amp; integrius tenuit. Et preterea dabit eidem Johanni mille mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas Argenti, &amp;c. Testibus Domino Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo Episcopo de sancto Asaph, Domino H. Abbate Cestriae, Domino Hugone de Lasci Comite Ʋltoniae, Phillippo de Orreby tunc Justiciario Cestriae, H. de Aldideley, Gualtero de Daivill, Ricardo Fitton, Edrevet Liagham, Edmundo filio Righerit. Coronon filio Edrevet, Helin Idhit, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistro Estruit, Magistro Adâ, Davide Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico Lhewellini, Magistro H. — Clericis Domini Comitis Cestriae, &amp; multis aliis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To which I answer, that as it is not certain that the said <hi>Joane</hi> was a Bastard, so this Deed is only an Agreement, in the nature of Articles betwixt <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> and <hi>Lincolne</hi> on the one part, and <hi>Lhewellin</hi> Prince of <hi>North-Wales</hi> on
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:64436:61"/>the other part; concerning an intended Marriage betwixt the said <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Hellen,</hi> for they were not then married, as appears by the said Articles or Deed; and the said <hi>Lhewellin</hi> doth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by give to the said <hi>John Scot, Budeford</hi> and <hi>Suttehel,</hi> but only Covenants that he will give them unto him, as appears by the word <hi>Dabit,</hi> which is the future Tense; and it is very likely that the said <hi>Budeford</hi> and <hi>Suttehel</hi> were given to the said <hi>Lhewellin, in Maritagio,</hi> without the word <hi>libero,</hi> as will be proved by these Records.</p>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                           <body>
                              <div type="record">
                                 <head>Claus. <hi>2.</hi> H. <hi>3.</hi> M. <hi>1.</hi>
                                 </head>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>MAndatum est Vic. Warr. quod plenam seisinam habere faciat Leolina Principi Norwall. de villa de Budeford cum pertinentiis suis quam Dominus Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes rex pater Domini Henrici Regis deditei in Maritagium cum Johanna sorore Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici Regis uxore ipsius Leulini. Test.</hi>
                                    <note n="(*)" place="bottom">Scilicet Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>ielmo Marescallo Comite Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                                          <desc>••••</desc>
                                       </gap>
                                       <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiae tunc Rectore Regis &amp; Regni.</note>
                                    <hi>Comite apud Westm.</hi> 10. <hi>octo.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <pb n="111" facs="tcp:64436:61"/>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Rot. Pip. de ann.</hi> 2 H. 3. <hi>Warrr. &amp; Leic.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Willielmus de Cantilupo Philippus de Kinton pro eo reddit comp. de</hi> cxxviii <hi>l.</hi> ii <hi>s. bl. de firma de Warewick: &amp; de quater viginti &amp; quinque libris</hi> xvi <hi>s.</hi> iiii <hi>d. bl. firma de Leicestershire.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>—<hi>Et Leuelino Principi Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall:</hi> lxxvi <hi>s. in Budiford in Maritagio cum Johanna uxore sua, de dimidio anno per Breve Regis.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>And as there are in these Records the words <hi>in Maritagio,</hi> without the word <hi>libero,</hi> so also there was <hi>livery</hi> made of the same Lands, which in a Gift in Frank-Marriage is needless to be done; but be it how it will, there can be no Argument drawn from this Deed or Agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Earl <hi>Randle</hi> and <hi>Lhewellin;</hi> for it is very apparent, that he who did write the said Deed or Agreement was a very ignorant Person, and did not at all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand what a Gift in Frank-Marriage was; for if King <hi>John</hi> gave <hi>Budeford</hi> and <hi>Suttehel</hi> to the said <hi>Lhewellin</hi> with his Daughter <hi>Joane, in Maritagio,</hi> without the word <hi>libero,</hi> then the said <hi>Lhewellin,</hi>
                        <pb n="112" facs="tcp:64436:62"/>might give them to <hi>John Scot,</hi> with his Daughter <hi>Hellen,</hi> in whatsoever manner he did please; but if King <hi>John</hi> gave the said Mannors of <hi>Budeford</hi> and <hi>Sutte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> to <hi>Lhewellin</hi> with his Daughter <hi>Joane, in libero Maritagio,</hi> then the said <hi>Lhewel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> could not give away from his Son <hi>David</hi> (who out-liv'd the said <hi>Lhewellin</hi>) the said Mannors of <hi>Budeford</hi> and <hi>Sutte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hel,</hi> to <hi>John Scot,</hi> with his Daughter <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len;</hi> for though he who hath Lands gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him in Marriage liable to Services, hath the Inheritance of the said Lands, and may dispose of them as he doth please; yet he who hath lands given to him in Frank Marriage hath not the inheritance of the said lands, but hath only <hi>Custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam cum uxore,</hi> and therefore cannot dispose of the same; and yet this igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant person, who did write the said A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement or Deed, doth suppose that King <hi>John</hi> gave <hi>Budeford</hi> and <hi>Suttehel</hi> in Frank-Marriage to <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> and that the said <hi>Lhewellin</hi> might give them in Frank-Marriage to the said <hi>John Scot.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Neither can it be objected, that the Law hath been changed in this Point, or otherways holden from what it is now;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:64436:62"/>for I will shew that the Law was the same in this particular, and also so holden after the time of the said <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> in the time of the said <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> and before the time of the said <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> and that I do thus prove;</p>
                     <p>If you look in my Lord <hi>Coke upon Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleton,</hi> fol. 22. a. you will find that the Husband in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> III. was so far from having the inheritance of Lands given to him in Frank Marriage, that if he and his Wife were divorced, the Woman should enjoy the whole, Land; and for this he cites in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, 13 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>tit. Ass.</hi> 19 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>Ass.</hi> 83. with several other proofs of the like nature;</p>
                     <p>Also in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> I. as you may see in the ancient Treatise cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Fleta,</hi> (which was written in that Kings time) the inheritance in these ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Frank Marriage was in the Wife with whom the Land was given, and not in the Husband, but it was
<note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note>
                        <hi>Secus</hi> otherways, when Lands were given in Marriage <hi>pro Homagio &amp; servitio viri,</hi> as you may see
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:64436:63"/>in the third Book and 11<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Chapter, <hi>de Donationibus in Maritagiis,</hi> where it is thus said, <hi>Et quamvis fiat mentio in dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, quod terra data sit in Maritagium ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li viro, cum tali uxore, res data tamen est liberum tenementum uxoris, &amp; non viri, cum non habeat nisi custodiam cum uxore, donec liberum tenementum sibi accres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, per legem Angliae: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note>
                        <hi>si pro homagio &amp; servitio viri, &amp; in Maritagium facta fuerit donatio.</hi> And so also the Law doth continue until this day.</p>
                     <p>Also in the 9 <hi>H.</hi> 3. (which is but three years from that year in which Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> doth suppose the said Deed, or Agreement, betwixt the said <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> and the said <hi>Lhewellin</hi> to be made) the inheritance of those Lands which were given to a Man with a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in Frank Marriage, was in the Wife, and not in the Husband; for my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> on <hi>Littleton,</hi> fol. 21. b. tells us, That if the King give Land to a Man with a Woman of his Kindred in Frank Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and the Woman dyeth without Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue, the Man in the Kings case shall not hold it for his life, because the Woman
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:64436:63"/>was the cause of the gift, but otherways it is in the case of a common person, and for this in the margent he cites 9 <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>Dower.</hi> 202. so that it seems, though a Man might be Tenant by the courtesie of <hi>England</hi> of Lands given to him by a Subject in Frank Marriage with his Wife, yet where the King did so give the Lands, if the Woman after she had Issue did dye, and her Issue all dye before her; the Husband in that case would not be Tenant by the courtesie of <hi>England,</hi> or enjoy the Lands for his life, so far was he from then having the Inheritance of the said Lands.</p>
                     <p>So also <hi>Bracton</hi> (who was the second that did write of our <hi>English</hi> Laws, and was living in the the time of King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> III. and in the time of the said <hi>Lhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellin</hi>) lib. 2. cap. 11. thus sayes:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Si autem fiat mentio quod terra data sit in Maritagium cum uxore &amp; eorum haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus, communes haeredes de corpore utrius<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que admittantur, qui si defecerint, reverti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur terra data, &amp; alii remotiores excludun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: quia res data est liberum tenementum uxoris, &amp; non viri, cum non habeat nisi
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:64436:64"/>custodiam cum uxore. Si autem sic terra detur in Maritagium viro cum uxore &amp; eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum haeredibus, pro homagio &amp; servitio vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri (qued fit aliquando) licet detur in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertum Maritagium, quae sunt sibi ad invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem adversantia sive repugnantia, tunc pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur homagium, &amp; erit acsi fieret donatio tam viro quam uxori.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And that the <hi>Maritagium</hi> which <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton</hi> here first speaks of, was <hi>Maritagium Liberum,</hi> is very apparent, because we see here, he immediately after speaks of Lands given in Marriage not free, <hi>viz.</hi> of Lands given <hi>in Maritagium, pro homagio &amp; ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitio viri;</hi> so also Mr. <hi>Glanvil,</hi> who lived before the time of the said <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> viz. in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> II. and was the first that did write of our <hi>English</hi> Laws, <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. after he hath told us what Free Marriage is, hath these words:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cum quis itaque terram aliquam cum ux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre sxa in Maritagium ceperit, si ex eadem uxore sua haeredem habuerit silium, vel fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am clamantem &amp; auditum infra quatuor parietes, si idem vir uxorem suam supervix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crit, sive vixerit haeres sive non, illi in nita
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:64436:64"/>sua remanet Maritagium illud, post mortem vero ipsius ad donatorem vel ejus haeredes est reversurum. Sin autem ex uxore sua nunquam habuerit haeredem, tunc statim post mortem uxoris ad donatorem vel haeredes ejus revertetur Maritagium. Et haec est quaedam causa quare de Maritagio tali non solet recipi homagium. Si enim sic donata esset terra aliqua in Maritagium, vel alio modo, quod inde reciperetur homagium, tunc nunquam de cetero ad donatorem, vel ejus haeredes licite possit reverti ut supradictum est.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So that Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> also here tells us, that the Husband hath not the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of such Lands as are given to him in Frank Marriage with his Wife, for where Lands are given in Marriage, for which <hi>homage</hi> is not to be done, if the Husband have Issue by his Wife, whether that Issue live or dye, the Husband shall (by the courtesie of <hi>England</hi>) hold those Lands for his life; but if he never have Issue, then those Lands upon the death of the Wife shall revert to the Donor, or his Heirs, so far was the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band from having the Inheritance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; but on the other hand we see, that
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:64436:65"/>Mr. <hi>Glanvil</hi> tells us, that if Land be given in such Marringe, for which <hi>homage</hi> is done, that the Husband hath the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the said Lands, and may dispose of them as he doth please, because such Lands can never revert to the Donor or his Heirs, as Lands given in Frank Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage may do; so that hereby the gross ignorance of him, that did write that Deed or Agreement betwixt the said Earl <hi>Randle,</hi> and the said <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> doth suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently appear, and there can be no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument brought from their covenanting to do a thing, which could not possibly be done.</p>
                     <p>And here because Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> sayes, that the words in <hi>Maritagio</hi> were oftentimes in old Deeds taken for the words <hi>in Libero Maritagio,</hi> I think it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to prove, that whensoever Lands are given by Deed, with these words <hi>in Maritagio,</hi> without any other word join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therewith, that such Lands were given in Marriage liable to services; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Maritagium</hi> be twofold <hi>viz. Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigium Liberum &amp; Maritagium servitio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>onexium,</hi> as I have long since in the 39 and 40 pages of my reply to Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:64436:65"/>answer to my Defence of <hi>Amicia,</hi> proved both out of Mr. <hi>Glanvil,</hi> and other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, yet when the word <hi>Maritagium</hi> is used alone in a Deed, and Lands are passed by Deed to a Man with a Woman <hi>in Maritagio,</hi> without either the word <hi>Libero,</hi> or the words <hi>Servitio obnoxio,</hi> in this case the word <hi>Maritagium</hi> cannot be the <hi>Genus,</hi> and comprehend both <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagium Liberum,</hi> and <hi>Maritagium Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio obnoxium;</hi> for it is impossible that a Man should at one and the same time, hold the very same Lands of the same per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, in Frank Marriage, and in Marriage liable to services; the onely question therefore is, when a Man gives Lands with any one <hi>in Maritagio</hi> onely, without either the word <hi>libero,</hi> or the words <hi>servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio obnoxio,</hi> what construction the Law will make of such a Deed; and whether it shall be a Gift in Frank Marriage, or a Gift in Marriage liable to services?</p>
                     <p>Now that such a Deed shall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strued in Law to be a gift liable to ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices will thus appear;</p>
                     <p>First, Because if such a Deed be made with the words in <hi>Maritagio</hi> only, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:64436:66"/>no other word be expressed in the said Deed to declare that it should be a Gift in Frank Marriage, it is impossible that those Lands should be held free from all services; For if, as my Lord <hi>Coke upon Littleton</hi> tells us <hi>fol.</hi> 21 <hi>b.</hi> these words <hi>in Liberum Maritagium</hi> are such words of art, and so necessarily required (in a Gift in Frank Marriage) as they cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd by words equipollent, or amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to as much; How can it be that <hi>Lands</hi> given <hi>in Maritagio,</hi> can be held free from services, when there are no equipollent words, nor any expression at all, to shew that the Donor intended that the said Lands should be held free from servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces?</p>
                     <p>Secondly, Because <hi>Maritagium servitio obnoxium,</hi> is the elder Brother to <hi>Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium Liberum;</hi> For when lands are given <hi>in Maritagio servitio obnoxio,</hi> such Gifts are agreeable to the Common Law of <hi>England,</hi> but when they are given <hi>in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berum Maritagium,</hi> as we may see in <hi>Coke upon Littleton,</hi> fol. 21 b. they create an estate of inheritance against the general Rule of the Law; and therefore though this younger Son be connived at, and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:64436:66"/>tolerated, yet, as we may there see, the Law requireth that such Gifts be legally pursued, and that is the reason why such Gifts cannot be made to any but those of the bloud, as also why the words <hi>in Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Maritagium,</hi> are such words of Art, and so necessarily required, as that they cannot be expressed by words equipol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, or amounting to as much.</p>
                     <p>Also our Common Lawyers have a Rule (as we may see <hi>Coke upon Littleton,</hi> fol. 189. a.) that <hi>Additio probat minori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem;</hi> and thereupon it is that my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> there tells us, that the younger Son giveth the difference; and pursuant to this Rule, when a Gift is made in <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagio,</hi> which is intended to be liable to services, (that being the elder Brother) they use the word <hi>Maritagio</hi> in the Deed, and no more; but when it is given in Free Marriage, (which is the younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) according as my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> tells us, the word <hi>Liberum</hi> (which is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence) is absolutely necessary: and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with agrees the common practice; For I never saw in all my life, where Lands were given <hi>in Maritagio,</hi> liable to servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that the words <hi>in Maritagio servitio
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:64436:67"/>obnoxio,</hi> were used in any of the said Deeds, but only the words <hi>in Maritagio;</hi> and if they did intend that any other services should be done, over and above those services which the Law did create by the words <hi>in Maritagio,</hi> then, they did afterwards in the said Deeds mention those other services, but else not.</p>
                     <p>So also the word <hi>Foedum,</hi> or <hi>Fee</hi> is twofould, <hi>viz. Foedum simplex,</hi> and <hi>Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum tale,</hi> and yet in this case, like unto the other, <hi>Fee-simple</hi> being the elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Fee-tail,</hi> (all inheritances being in <hi>Fee-simple</hi> before the statute of <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster</hi> 2. cap. 1. as <hi>Littleton</hi> tells us, <hi>lib.</hi> 1 <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>sect.</hi> 13.) if it be said in any Booke, that a man is seised in <hi>Fee,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out more saying, it shall be intended in <hi>Fee-simple;</hi> For it shall not be intended by these words <hi>(in Fee)</hi> that a Man is seised in <hi>Fee-tail,</hi> unless there be added to it this addition <hi>Fee-tail</hi> as we may see in <hi>Littleton,</hi> lib. 3. cap. 4. sect. 293. and according to this Rule, our Common Lawyers do all of them constantly use the like expressions at this day.</p>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:64436:67"/>
                     <p>So also in Blazoning Coats of Armes, and particularly to instance in my own; Because the plain Barre is the elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to all other Barres, it shall not be said, that I bear Argent two plain Barres Gules, but only that I beare Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent two Barres Gules, and yet the word <hi>Foedum</hi> is as much the <hi>Genus</hi> to <hi>Fee-simple</hi> and <hi>Fee-tail,</hi> and the word Barre as much the <hi>Genus</hi> to a plain Barre, a Barre engrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, a Barre Nebule, and all other sorts of Barres, as the word <hi>Maritagium</hi> is the <hi>Genus</hi> to <hi>Maritagium Liberum,</hi> and <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagium servitio obnoxium.</hi> And as the words in <hi>Faedo</hi> alone without the word <hi>simplict</hi> joined with them, shall signifie in <hi>Fae-simple;</hi> and as the word Barre alone shall in Blazoning be understood to be a plain Barre and not any other sort of Barre whatsoever, so the words <hi>in Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagio</hi> in a Deed, if no other word be joi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therewith, shall in Law be construed to be in Marriage liable to services.</p>
                     <p>And this doth shew that Sir <hi>Peter Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> was mistaken, when in the 20 and 21 pages of the first of his two Books, he charged me with saying, that <hi>Maritagium
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:64436:68"/>est duplex, vel Maritagium, vel liberum Moritagium;</hi> For I never said or thought any such thing, but when I did divide <hi>Maritagium,</hi> I did divide it into <hi>Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium liberum,</hi> and <hi>Maritagium servitio ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxium,</hi> as you may see in the 39 and 40 pages of my Reply; and I have here made it to appear, that when Lands are given <hi>in Maritagio,</hi> without any other word added thereto, they are then given in Marriage liable to services; but the saying so doth not distinguish <hi>Maritagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> into <hi>Maritagium,</hi> and <hi>Maritagium li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berum,</hi> as Sir <hi>Peter</hi> did thereupon say that I did.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in his Advertisement to the Reader, gives us this Record, in these following words.</p>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:64436:68"/>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                           <body>
                              <div type="book_excerpt">
                                 <head>Ex Rotulo Chartarum de anno sexto Regis Johannis, numero <hi>32.</hi>
                                 </head>
                                 <head type="sub">Charta Lewelini</head>
                                 <head type="sub">
                                    <hi>Principis Walliae.</hi>
                                 </head>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>JOhannes Dei gratia,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Sciatis, nos dedisse, concessisse, &amp; hac Charta no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra confirmasse Lewelino Principi North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walliae, in Maritagium cum Johanna filia nostra Castrum de Ellesmara cum omnibus pertinentiis suis: Tenendum ei &amp; haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus suis qui de eo &amp; praedicta filia nostra exierint, de nobis &amp; haeredibus nostris in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berum Maritagium, salvis Conventionibus inter nos &amp; ipsum de terra &amp; eodem Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagio factis: Et nos &amp; haeredes nostri praedictum castrum cum pertinentiis suis ei, &amp; praedictis haeredibus suis, Warrantiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimus contra omnes qui in eo jus clamare voluerint: Quare volumus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>quod prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus Lewelinus &amp; praedicti haeredes sui habeant &amp; teneant praedictum castrum de Ellesmara cum omnibus pertinentiis suis, bene &amp; in pace, libere &amp; quiete, integre, in bosco &amp; plano, in pratis &amp; pascuis, in viis &amp; semitis, in aquis &amp; molendinis, in Stagnis
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:64436:69"/>&amp; vivariis, in moris &amp; marciscis, &amp; Pis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eariis, &amp; in omnibus aliis locis &amp; rebus, cum omnibus libertatibus &amp; liberis Consue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinibus ad illud Castrum pertinentibus, si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut praedictum est. Testibus Domino Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico Cantuariensi Archiepiscopo, G. filio P. Comite Essexiae Willielmo Comite Sarum, Johanne de Cursy: Datum per manum H. de Wellen. Archidiaconi Wellensis à apud Dovorum,</hi> 16 <hi>die Aprilis, anno,</hi> &amp;c. 6.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <dateline>
                                       <hi>Convenit cum Recordo, Gulielmus Ryley Deputatus Algar. May Militis,</hi>
                                       <date>
                                          <hi>Februario,</hi> 1674.</date>
                                    </dateline>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>By which Record Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> sayes it plainly appears, that this Grant to <hi>Lewellin</hi> with <hi>Joane</hi> Daughter of King <hi>John,</hi> was a Grant <hi>in liberum Maritagium</hi> (in express words) of the Castle of <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesmere</hi> in <hi>Shropshire,</hi> dated the 16 day of <hi>April,</hi> in the sixth year of the Reign of King <hi>John,</hi> which falleth in the year after the Incarnation of Christ, 1204.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. To which I answer, First, That it doth not plainly appear, as hath before been shewed, that the said <hi>Joane,</hi> Wift of <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> was a Bastard; and in this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:64436:69"/>Record, (as she is in all the rest) she is called the Kings Daughter, without the least blemish of Bastardy at all.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Secondly, It is manifest by a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord herein before by me mentioned, that Livery was made of <hi>Ellesmere</hi> unto <hi>Lhewellin</hi> by the Sheriff of <hi>Shropshire,</hi> about the 6<seg rend="sup">th</seg> year of King <hi>John;</hi> and as Livery doth not need to be made upon a legal gift in Frank Marriage, so on the other hand my Lord <hi>Coke on Littleton,</hi> fol. 21. b. tells us, that if Lands be given in Frank Marriage with one that is not of the blood of the Donor; yet an Estate for life will pass, if Livery be made; and we may find both by the <hi>Welsh</hi> History put out by Dr. <hi>Powell,</hi> pag. 306. and <hi>Matt. Paris</hi> put out by Dr. <hi>Watts,</hi> pag. 605, &amp; 626. that the next year after the death of the said <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> the said <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesmere</hi> was in the hands of King <hi>Henry</hi> the III. and it appears by good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, that it was afterwards committed by him to the trust of <hi>Hamon le Strange;</hi> so that such a Grant, and such an enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as this was, might have been, if the said <hi>Joane</hi> had been certainly a Bastard, and therefore cannot have any relation to
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:64436:70"/>this Case of <hi>Amicia</hi> at all. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Sir <hi>Peter</hi> hath heretofore objected, that if this had been but an Estate for life, it would have reverted to the King upon the death of <hi>Joane,</hi> who dyed four years before her Husband <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> in that he is clearly mistaken, because the Grant and Livery were both of them made to <hi>Lhewellin</hi> himself; And whereas he also would have it, that <hi>Ellesmere</hi> did not of right belong to King <hi>Henry</hi> the III. and thereupon in the first of his two Books; taking notice of the Articles betwixe King <hi>Henry</hi> the III. and <hi>David</hi> Prince of <hi>North Wales,</hi> doth ask this question. What needed this Covenant from <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Ellesmere,</hi> if it were the right of King <hi>Henry</hi> before that Agreement made? Sir <hi>Peter</hi> if he had so pleased, might easily have discerned that there was the same Covenant and Grant from the said <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> concerning some Lands of <hi>Roger de Montealto</hi> Steward of <hi>Chester,</hi> and of some other Barons, &amp;c. of the right and title to which lands there could be no doubt.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. But Thirdly, What disputes so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever might have arisen about this Grant,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:64436:70"/>if it had been made by a common person, because the granting part thereof is <hi>in Maritagium,</hi> without any other word, but the <hi>Tenendum</hi> is <hi>in liberum Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium;</hi> yet there being a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Kings case, and the case of a common person, this Grant was certainly a void grant and by consequence is of no force or weight at all as to the matter in hand; for as we may read in the case of <hi>Tenures</hi> put out by Baron <hi>Barry,</hi> and Printd at <hi>Dublin</hi> 1637. pag. 48. in the Grants of a common person, the Rule of Law is, that the Grant shall be taken most strongly against the Grantor; But in the King's Grants the Rule is, that they shall be taken most benificially for the King, and most strongly against the <hi>Patentees.</hi> Also in the same 48. <hi>page,</hi> there is another Rule, that the Grant of of the King shall not be extended to pass any thing contrary to the intent of the King expressed in his Grant; and if the Grant cannot take effect, according to his intent expressed in his Grant, the Grant is void. And accordingly in the 49. and 50 <hi>pages</hi> there are these cases put, where the Grants would have been
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:64436:71"/>good in the Cases of common persons, but not in the Case of the King.</p>
                     <p>In the Lord <hi>Lovell</hi>'s Case, 18 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>B. Pat.</hi> 104. The King <hi>ex certa scientia, &amp; mero motu,</hi> grants Lands to one and his Heits-males; If a common person had made such a Grant, the Law would say, that the word Males were void, and the <hi>Fee simple</hi> should pass; But will the Law make such construction in the Kings Grant? No; There the Grant shall be void, for, he was deceived in his Grant, in that it cannot take effect according to his intent expressed in his Letters Patents. 29 <hi>Eliz.</hi> in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> the Case was, King <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. was seized of two Mannors, <hi>scilicet de Ryton &amp; Condor;</hi> He Grants <hi>ex certa scientia &amp; mero motu totum illud Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerium de Ryton &amp; Condor;</hi> Adjudged that the Grant was void.</p>
                     <p>The like Case was resolved, 30. <hi>Eliz.</hi> where the Queen was seized of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of <hi>Milborne,</hi> and <hi>Saperton</hi> in the County of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> and the Queen grants <hi>ex certa scientia &amp; mero motu totum illud Manerium de Milborne cum Saperton in
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:64436:71"/>com. Line,</hi> and it was held, that neither of the Mannors did pass; and yet if a common person had made such Grants, the Grantee in both the said Cases should have had both the said Mannors.</p>
                     <p>By which said Rules and Cases it also appears, that this Grant of <hi>Elesmer &amp;c.</hi> to <hi>Lbewellin</hi> was a void Grant, and by consequence of no force at all; For that the King was deceived in his Grant, when he made the <hi>tenendum in liberum Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagium,</hi> is very plain, as well because the King grants the said Castle and Lands <hi>in Maritagium</hi> only, (which by Law im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies Marriage liable to services) as also, because it appears by those words in the Grant, <hi>Salvis conventionibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nos &amp; ipsum de</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note>
                        <hi>terra &amp; codem maritagio factis,</hi> that the King intended to have money paid, or service done to him, for the said Castle and Lands, and by consequence they were not to be held <hi>in liberum Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagium.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So that all the objections against my first Argument, though so very numerous, are fully answered, and wholly removed out of the way, and by necessary
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:64436:72"/>consequence it appears, that <hi>Amicia</hi> was <hi>Hugh Ceviliok</hi>'s legitimate Child.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Against my second Argument, Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in the 52 page of his Answer to my defence of <hi>Amicia,</hi> doth object, That although Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> was wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to very many Deeds of the then Earls of <hi>Chester,</hi> and was also much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versant with them, as appears by those many circumstances which I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in taken notice of; yet this was occasioned by his place, he being Judge, and that <hi>Philip de Orreby,</hi> who was Judge of <hi>Chester</hi> next after the said <hi>Ralph,</hi> was also a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to the like Multitudes of Charters or more.</p>
                  <p>To which I answer, that although <hi>Phillip de Orreby</hi> was Justice of <hi>Chester</hi> above twenty years, yet I beleive it cannot be prooved that the said <hi>Phillip</hi> was witness to near so many Charters of the Earls of <hi>Chester,</hi> as the said <hi>Ralph</hi> was; And which shews that the familiarity betwixt the said Earls, and the said <hi>Ralph,</hi> was not upon that account which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> speaks of, we find as before ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that the <hi>said Ralph,</hi> was a witness to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:64436:72"/>
                     <hi>Hugh Civiliok</hi>'s Deeds of confirmation to the Priory of <hi>Cale</hi> in <hi>Darbyshire,</hi> and was with <hi>Randle Blundevil</hi> at <hi>Coventry,</hi> and a witness to his Charter to the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesses there, which could not be occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned, by his being Judge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>And as to my third Argument, Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> gives this only Answer, as we may see in the 53 <hi>page</hi> of his answer to my defence of <hi>Amicia,</hi> that indeed Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents are scant; but some there be: what do you think of <hi>Ranulpho de Astbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nepote Comitis Cestriae;</hi> who is put the last of all the Witnesses in the Deed, as you may see in the <hi>Addenda</hi> of my Book? Certainly he was but an ordinary Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, nor Knight, nor Lord: But you will say, I cannot prove him a Bastard; yet I should be glad to find out his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, if he were not: 'tis a shrewd presumption.</p>
                  <p>So that Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth in effect confess, that he hath no such Precedent at all, and indeed this precedent will fail him for two reasons.</p>
                  <p>First Because Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth as good
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:64436:73"/>as confess, that he cannot prove him to be a Bastard, (and he might perhaps be a younger Brother or son of a younger Brother, and so not necessarily a Knight or a Lord.)</p>
                  <p>And Secondly; Because he doth not call himself the Earl's Nephew, but is called so by others; and that is so far from contradicting, that it doth confirm what I said in my former Book.</p>
                  <p>And whereas Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> says, he should be glad to find out the Extraction of the said <hi>Randle de Astbury,</hi> if he were not a Bastard. Though it be perhaps impossible now to tell him his Extraction certainly, because he lived so long since, and we only find him mentioned as a witness in one Deed, yet I doubt not but to satisfie the Reader, that he and his Father and Mother might all be legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate; For, (not to say that he might be a son of some other Daughter of the said <hi>Hugh Civiliock</hi> by his former wife) he might possibly be the Son of <hi>Roger,</hi> Son of <hi>Hugh Civiliock;</hi> and I know no reason why the said <hi>Roger</hi> should by Sir <hi>Peter</hi> be suspected to be a Bastard, for he only
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:64436:73"/>finds him (as appears by his <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 134.) mentioned as a witness to a Deed of his Brother <hi>Randle</hi>'s, to the Abby of St. <hi>Werburge:</hi> So that he conceives him to be a Bastard, because neither he, nor any Issue Male of his, suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in the Earldom of <hi>Chester,</hi> after the death of <hi>Randle Blundevil;</hi> whereas the said <hi>Roger</hi> might be lawful, and be Father to this <hi>Randle de Astbury,</hi> and yet both he and the said <hi>Randle de Astbury</hi> might dye before the said <hi>Randle de Blundevil;</hi> For he lived very long, and was Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> above 50 years: so that this third Argument of mine is not answered at all.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>And whereas I have in my 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, shewed out of Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi>'s Glossary on the word <hi>Bastardus,</hi> how the said Sir <hi>Henry</hi> quotes <hi>Constum. du Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Artic.</hi> 77. <hi>in Annot.</hi> thus: <hi>Quoties enim agitur de honore vel commodo filio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, appellatione filiorum non comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duntur Bastardi:</hi> And have from thence argued, that <hi>Amice</hi> would not have been stiled <hi>filia,</hi> as she is in the said Deed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less she had been a legitimate Child; Sir <hi>Peter</hi> in the 63<seg rend="sup">d</seg>
                     <hi>page</hi> of his Answer to my
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:64436:74"/>Defence of <hi>Amicia,</hi> doth object against this in these very words.</p>
                  <p>And what you add out of <hi>Spelman,</hi> is little to the purpose; that in Cases of Honour and Profit, distinction was then made; that by the Appellation of Sons, Bastards are not comprehended by the Customs of <hi>Normandy:</hi> What then? this supposeth that in other Cases, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly by the Appellation of Sons, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stards were comprehended: This makes directly against you, and you know what <hi>Spelman</hi> saith in the very words next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing—That the ancient Northern people admitted Bastards to succeed in their Inheritance; and that <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror was not ashamed of that title, who began his Letter to <hi>Alan,</hi> Earl of <hi>Little Britain,</hi> (as he did many others) <hi>Ego Willielmus cognomento Bastardus.</hi> But what is all this to the answering of the Argument, or proving <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> to have had a former Wife? only you would have the words <hi>in libero Maritagio,</hi> to prove <hi>Amice</hi> absolutely legitimate: this is all the Answer you give to the Point; and this will not do it, as is before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, whither I have referred the ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reader.</p>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:64436:74"/>
                  <p>To which I answer, First, that though Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> doth here say, that this (which I here cite) supposeth that in other Cases, and formerly by the Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Sons, Bastards were compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended: And that this makes directly against me; yet he is very much deceived in so saying: For if in other Cases by the Appellation of Sons, Bastards were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, but were not comprehended by that Appellation in Cases of Profit; it will from hence appear that <hi>Amicia</hi> was legitimate, because she was called <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> in a Case, that did concern her Profit, and by consequence her Father must have a former Wife. And whereas he tells us, out of the next words of <hi>Spelman,</hi> viz. that the ancient Northern People admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Bastards to succeed in their Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and that <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror was not ashamed of that Title, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan his Letter to <hi>Alan,</hi> Earl of <hi>Little Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> as he did many others, <hi>Ego Willielmus cognomento Bastardus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I do not know how Sir <hi>Peter</hi> can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply those expressions to the Case in hand, and if he could, they would make against
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:64436:75"/>him; For, when Bastard Children were so much esteemed, as to be admitted to succeed in the inheritance, then certainly illegitimate Daughters were very near of equal repute with those that were legitimate. And by this Rule, why should not <hi>Amicia,</hi> if she was a Bastard, be so called, as well as <hi>Paganus</hi> was? (who as Sir <hi>Peter</hi> says, was the son of <hi>Hugh Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliok</hi>) or why should <hi>Hugh Civiliok</hi> himselfe, be more ashamed to call her so, than <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror was to stile himself a Bastard.</p>
                  <p>But these Cases of Princes differ much from those of Subjects; For Sir <hi>Richard Baker</hi> in his <hi>Chronicle</hi> printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1665. page 22. in the Life and Reign of King <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, tells us, that in those days it was not unfrequent, for Princes to confer their Principalities after their own deceases, upon whom they pleased, counting it as lawful to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point successors after them, as substitutes under them; And he also observes how in our time, and Kingdom, the Duke of <hi>Northumberland</hi> prevailed with King <hi>Edward</hi> the sixth, to exclude his two Sisters, <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the Lady <hi>Jane Grey,</hi> Daughter of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:64436:75"/>the Duke of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> to succeed him: so that Precedents brought from Princes, will in this Case be of no force at all.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>And whereas I have shewed in my 5<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Argument, that although the Constable of <hi>Cheshire</hi> (who had that Office in Fee) was by Charter to go next to the Earl of <hi>Chester;</hi> And the <hi>Dapifer, Seneschal</hi> or <hi>Steward</hi> of <hi>Cheshire,</hi> (who also had that Office in Fee, was to go next to the said <hi>Constable,</hi> that yet the said <hi>Ralph Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring,</hi> notwithstanding the said Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, is not only named as a Witness be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the said <hi>Constable, Seneschal,</hi> and other Barons, in those Deeds which I have there mentioned, but that also the Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> himself in his Charter, (contrary to all other Precedents in the times of other Justices which I have seen) doth name the Justice of <hi>Chester</hi> before both the <hi>Constable</hi> of <hi>Cheshire,</hi> and <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> of <hi>Cheshire.</hi> And that I did suppose, that the reason why the said <hi>Ralph</hi> had that great respect, was, because he had married a lawful Child of the said Earl, it being too great to have been shewed him, if he had only married one who
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:64436:76"/>was a Bastard; and that it will be very difficult to give any other reason there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in the 77<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                     <hi>page</hi> of his Answer to my Defence of <hi>Amicia,</hi> doth only give this Answer in these very words.</p>
                  <p>To this I say, it will not be difficult at all to give a reason, and much more easie, than to give a reason, why <hi>Amice</hi> should be no Bastard, because Sir <hi>Raufe Manwaring</hi> is sometime subscribed before the Barons of <hi>Cheshire.</hi> The reason I give is this, that anciently in those Ages, the Justice was put sometimes before the Barons, and sometimes after; and sometimes after the <hi>Constable,</hi> and <hi>Dapifer,</hi> and before the rest of the Barons, as it hapned: For proof, see the Deed in my Book, making the Baron of <hi>Halton,</hi> the prime Baron, <hi>pag.</hi> 160. where the Justice comes after all the Barons; also in the Deed of Earl <hi>Randle</hi> to his Barons, <hi>pag.</hi> 162. where the Justice comes next after the <hi>Constable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer,</hi> and before the other Barons; see also in my Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 130, 131. two Deeds made by <hi>Hugh Cyveliok:</hi> In the one, the Justice is put after the <hi>Constable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer:</hi> In the other, the Justice is put before them; many other like exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:64436:76"/>may be produced elsewhere: I will appeal herein to Mr. <hi>Dugdale,</hi> or to any Antiquary in <hi>England;</hi> and considering the great uncertainty of subscription of Witnesses in old Deeds, sometimes put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one before another, in one Deed, and again putting the same person after the other in another Deed; sometimes put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Domino</hi> prefixed before the names of some persons in one Deed, and omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the word <hi>Domino</hi> before the names of the same persons in another Deed, whereof I have spoken, <hi>pag.</hi> 5, 6. in the beginning of this Book. I say, had you well confidered or observed these things, it was not worth your labor to have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded those three or four leafs in the close of your Book.</p>
                  <p>To which I reply, That what Sir <hi>Peter</hi> sayes in the 77, 78, and 79 <hi>pages</hi> of his said Answer, is so far from answering that Argument of mine, which is contained between the 69, and 75 <hi>pages</hi> of my first Book, that that which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> pretends to be an Answer, (if rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood) is the very Argument which I there frame against him; For, though what he sayes, <hi>pag.</hi> 78. be true, that
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:64436:77"/>sometimes the <hi>Justice</hi> is put after the <hi>Constable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer,</hi> and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times before the <hi>Constable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer,</hi> yet all the <hi>Justices</hi> of <hi>Chester,</hi> except Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> are named in the Charts of the Earls of <hi>Chester,</hi> after the <hi>Constable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer,</hi> and are also named after the <hi>Constable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer,</hi> when they were witnesses to any Deeds; But it is only in the time of the said Sir <hi>Ralph Manwairing,</hi> when the <hi>Justice</hi> is named before the <hi>Constable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer</hi> in the Charts of the said Earls, and it is only he who is named as a Witness, and that frequently before the <hi>Constable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer</hi> as I have proved by several Deeds, which I then mentioned both out of Sir <hi>Peters</hi> former Book, and elsewhere, and doth also further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, by another Deed in his <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 205. where the said Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> is also named as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness before the then <hi>Dapifer, Ralph de Montealto;</hi> and this respect was shewed to the said Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, as we may see in his said Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 160. <hi>&amp;</hi> 161. that the <hi>Constable</hi> by Charter was to go next the Earl, and had his Office in Fee, and that the Steward
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:64436:77"/>was to go next after the Constable, and had his Office also in Fee.</p>
                  <p>But when <hi>Phillip Orreby,</hi> who did succeed the said Sir <hi>Ralph Manwairing,</hi> was Justice of <hi>Chester,</hi> then, according to the old usual way, as appears in the 162. <hi>page</hi> of Sir <hi>Peters</hi> first Book, the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer</hi> were again named in the Earls Chart before the Justice of <hi>Chester,</hi> and also as we may see at the bottom of the 144 <hi>page</hi> and top of the 145 <hi>page</hi> of his said Book, the said <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable</hi> was named as a Witness before <hi>Phillip de Orreby,</hi> though then Justice of <hi>Chester;</hi> and I beleive Sir <hi>Peter</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not shew any Chart of any of the Earls of <hi>Chester,</hi> in which any other Justice of <hi>Chester</hi> had the like preeminence; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I think he can shew any Deeds, in which any other Justice is named as a witness before the <hi>Constable</hi> or <hi>Dapifer;</hi> and if any such single Precedent can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance be found, I am confident it will prove to be a Deed wherein the said <hi>Philip de Orreby</hi> is named as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and was occasioned by the simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Clark, who did write the said Deed, who finding Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:64436:78"/>Justice of <hi>Chester</hi> (the immediate Predecessor of the said <hi>Philip de Orreby</hi>) to be written as a witness before the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer,</hi> might thereupon think that <hi>Philip de Orreby</hi> should also be so placed, though it was not allowed to the said <hi>Philip.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And although Sir <hi>Peter</hi> truly objects, <hi>p.</hi> 78. how great the uncertainty of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of witnesses was in old Deeds, sometimes putting one before another in one Deed, and after putting the same person after the other in another Deed; yet, that will be nothing in this Case, for Sir <hi>Peter</hi> himself confesses, <hi>pag.</hi> 160. <hi>&amp;</hi> 161. of his <hi>Historical Antiquities;</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the uncertainty of subscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of Witnesses, that after certain Offices were annexed to certain Barons, that the matter was without controversie (as to the <hi>Constable</hi> and <hi>Dapifer</hi>) and that the <hi>Constable</hi> of <hi>Cheshire</hi> in Fee car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it clear by his Office, which was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to his Barony, and that the <hi>Steward</hi> was the next after him.</p>
                  <p>And therefore this Preeminence being thus given to the said Sir <hi>Ralph,</hi> and to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:64436:78"/>him only; and he also, so far as I have found, being ever named before all the other Barons of <hi>Cheshire,</hi> after he had married the said <hi>Amicia,</hi> as well when he had parted with his Office of Justice, as before; I think I may still say, it will be difficult to give a reason thereof, if he did not marry a lawful Daughter of the aforesaid Earl.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p n="6">6. Sixthly, My last Argument to prove <hi>Amicia</hi> lawful, was raised, from the vast disproportion of years, that was betwixt <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> and his Wife <hi>Bertred,</hi> it not being at all probable, that so great a person as Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> was, should continue unmarried, without having a former Wife until the said <hi>Bertred</hi> became mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riageable. And this I formerly proved by three reasons.</p>
                  <p>First, By shewing how Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> did join with his Mother <hi>Matilda,</hi> in giving by Deed <hi>Stivinghale,</hi> and other things, to <hi>Walter Durdent</hi> Bishop of <hi>Chester,</hi> and his Successors, to which Deed <hi>Eustace</hi> the Constable was a Witness, and I having there proved out of Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> that the said <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stace</hi>
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:64436:79"/>was slain in the year 1157 (in which year the said <hi>Bertred</hi> was born) it would from thence follow, that if that Deed was sealed immediately before the said <hi>Eustace</hi> was slain, yet the said <hi>Hugh</hi> must needs be at the least 21 years older than his Wife <hi>Bertred.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, I have shewed out of <hi>Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docus Lhancaruensis</hi> (whom I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be an Author of good credit, and to be living at that time) that the said <hi>Hugh</hi> in the year 1142. fortified his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle of <hi>Cymaron</hi> and <hi>wan Melyenith</hi> to himself; and if the said <hi>Hugh</hi> was but 12 years of age at that time, yet he would be about 41 years old when he married the said <hi>Bertred.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And Thirdly, I have mentioned a Deed which is in Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storical Antiquities,</hi> which the said <hi>Hugh</hi> when he was Earl, made to the Nuns of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lington,</hi> in which is this expression, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> fuit tempore Heurici Regis;</hi> by which it appears, that the said Deed was made in the time of King <hi>Steven:</hi> For the said <hi>Hugh,</hi> as Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> tells us, came to be Earl in the year 1153. 18. of King
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:64436:79"/>
                     <hi>Steven,</hi> and dyed <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1181. 27 <hi>H.</hi> 2. But in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the second, it could not be made; for then Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> would have said, <hi>Sicut fuit tempore Henrici primi,</hi> or else he would have used some other words to distinguish King <hi>Henry</hi> the first, from the then King <hi>Henry</hi> the second. And if it was made in the time of King <hi>Steven,</hi> he dying in the year 1154. which was three years before the said <hi>Bertred</hi> was born, if the said Deed was made immediately before King <hi>Steven</hi> dyed, yet Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> would be at least 24 years older than <hi>Bertred</hi> his Wife.</p>
                  <p>Against every of these three reasons, Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> doth object, and as to the first he tells us, how <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> joined with his Mother <hi>Ermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude</hi> in the Grant of <hi>Wadmundesley,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Domini 1106. when he was scarce 12 years old, and so would have the Case of <hi>Stivinghale,</hi> to be like that of <hi>Wad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundesley,</hi> and therefore will suppose Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> when he made the Deed of <hi>Stivinghale</hi> to be then but about 12 years old also, because his Mother then joined with him. But in my Answer to Sir <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:64436:80"/>two Books, <hi>pag.</hi> 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, &amp; 46. I have shewed out of the Book of <hi>Abington,</hi> that that Deed of <hi>Wad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundesiey</hi> was sealed with the
<note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> Seal of the Earls Mother on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not with the Earls Seal at all, and that it was taken notice of as a strange Case, and other very material differences, I have there observed besides, to which, for brevity sake, I shall refer the Reader at this time.</p>
                  <p>And whereas he hath objected against my second reason, that <hi>Caradocus Lhan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caruan</hi> is not to be believed, because he says King <hi>Steven</hi> took <hi>Geffrey Mandevyle</hi> Prisoner at St. <hi>Albans</hi> in the year 1142. whereas <hi>Matt. Paris</hi> in that Edition put out by Dr. <hi>Wats,</hi> pag. 79. says it was <hi>William Mandevyle;</hi> if you look in <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of <hi>Huntington,</hi> who lived in the time of the said King <hi>Steven,</hi> pag. 393. lin. 15. And in the History of <hi>Simeon Dunelmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis,</hi> (who also lived in the time of the said King <hi>Steven,</hi> and whose History was continued for about 25 years, by <hi>John Prior</hi> of <hi>Hagulsted</hi> or <hi>Hexam</hi>) Col. 273. lin. 15. And in <hi>Roger Hoveden</hi> (who lived in the times of King <hi>Henry</hi> the II.
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:64436:80"/>King <hi>Richard</hi> the I. and King <hi>John</hi>) in his Annals printed at <hi>Francfurt,</hi> 1601. pag. 488. l. 41. And in <hi>Gulielmus Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brigensis,</hi> who lived in the times of King <hi>Richard</hi> the I. and King <hi>John,</hi> lib. 1. cap. 11. And in <hi>Ralph de Diceto,</hi> who was Dean of <hi>Pauls</hi> in King <hi>John</hi>'s time, in his <hi>Abbrev. Chronic.</hi> Col. 508. l. 32. And in <hi>Gervasius,</hi> a Benedictine Monk of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> (who lived in the time of King <hi>John</hi>) Col. 1360. lin. 7. And in <hi>John Bromton</hi>'s <hi>Chronicon,</hi> which ends with the death of King <hi>Richard</hi> the I. Col. 1033. lin. 1. you will there find, that according to what <hi>Caradocus Lhancaruensis</hi> says, his name was <hi>Goffrey,</hi> and not <hi>William Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devyle.</hi> And if Sir <hi>Peter</hi> had but lookt in <hi>Mat. Paris</hi> on the other side of the leaf, <hi>pag.</hi> 80. <hi>l.</hi> 20. he would have found <hi>Mat. Paris</hi> also calling him <hi>Geffrey Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devyle,</hi> so that the calling of him <hi>William</hi> in the former leaf, was either a slip of the Printer, or of <hi>Mat. Paris</hi>'s Pen. Neither is that second Objection which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> makes against this second reason, of any force: For whereas it is misprinted, <hi>Hugh</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> instead of <hi>Hugh</hi> Son to the Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> as appears by the amendment of the <hi>Errata,</hi> at the end of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:64436:81"/>the said Book, Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> of his own Authority, without naming any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to justifie what he says, tells us, that it should have been printed <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> and not <hi>Hugh</hi> Son to the Earl of <hi>Chester;</hi> but I will appeal to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who is most like to know, how it was in <hi>Caradocus Lhancaruensis</hi>'s <hi>Welsh</hi> Manuscript, whether Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> who never saw it, or Dr. <hi>Powel,</hi> who translated the same into <hi>English</hi> out of <hi>Welsh.</hi> And whereas Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in the 39 and 40 <hi>pages</hi> of his second Reply, objects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst my third reason, and says, that in the said Deed to the Nuns of <hi>Bolington,</hi> the not adding the words of <hi>Henrici Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis nunc,</hi> shews clearly it is meant of <hi>Hen.</hi> I. In that he says very true, for the words <hi>sicut fuit tempore Regis Henrici,</hi> do certainly relate to King <hi>Henry</hi> the first's time, because when this Deed was made, there had been no other King <hi>Henry;</hi> but it shews clearly, that this Deed was made in King <hi>Steven</hi>'s time; for if it had been made in King <hi>Henry</hi> the second's time, it would have said, <hi>sicut fuit tempore Regis Henrici primi,</hi> or else it would have used some other expression, to distinguish King <hi>Henry</hi> the I. from King <hi>Henry</hi> the II.
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:64436:81"/>the then King. And if that Deed was made in King <hi>Steven</hi>'s time, then my said Argument is still in force; for King <hi>Steven</hi> dyed three years before <hi>Bertred</hi> was born. And I think I may securely say, it will be hard for any one to shew me the like expression to that of <hi>sicut fuit tempore Henrici Regis,</hi> in any Deed, that he can make appear was made by a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the II. or any other later King <hi>Henry,</hi> or in the time of any other King in the like Case.</p>
                  <p>But besides these Objections against my said three reasons, Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> knowing very well, (according to what he did once acknowledge in the 49 <hi>page</hi> of his Answer to my Defence of <hi>Amicia</hi>) that if there was any great number of years betwixt the age of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> and his Wife <hi>Bertred,</hi> a man might then reasonably suppose, that the said Earl had a former Wife, doth labor very much to prove, there was no great difference of age betwixt them, and to that purpose he gives us this Record.</p>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:64436:82"/>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="record">
                              <head>Scacearium apud Westminster.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>In Rotulo de Dominabus Pueris, &amp; Puellis, de anno</hi> 31. <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. <hi>in Custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Rememoratoris Regis existente, continetur (inter alia) ut sequitur, &amp;c.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Com. Lincoln.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Balteslawe-Wapentak.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>MAtilda Comitissa Cestriae est de do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                                       <desc>••</desc>
                                    </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>i Regis: &amp; fuit filia Roberti Comitis Glocestriae filii Regis Henrici primi, &amp; est Lannorum, &amp; am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius: Hujus villae recepit Comitissa his VIII. annis: Ipsa tenet Wadinton in dote de feodo Comitis Cestriae: &amp; firma est XXII. libr. per annum: dict a villa valet per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num XL. lib. cum hoc instauramento, sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet, II. Carucis, IIII. Vaccis, I. Tauro, IIII. suibus, I. verre, D. ovibus, quae ibi sunt—&amp;c.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <pb n="153" facs="tcp:64436:82"/>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Com. Lincoln.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Jeretre Wapentak.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Bertrea Comitissa, filia Comitis de Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reous, uxor Hugonis Comitis Cestriae, est de donatione Domini Regis; &amp; est</hi> xxix. <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum Terra quam Comitissa habet,</hi> xl. <hi>lib.</hi>
                                 <note n="*" place="margin">My Copy is <hi>Maritagium &amp; Dos ejus sunt ultrà mare.</hi>
                                 </note>
                                 <hi>Maritagium; &amp; defectus sunt ultrà mare, ideo nesciunt Juratores quid valeant. Dominus Rex prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit, quod ipsa haberet</hi> xl. <hi>libratas terrae Domini sui in Beltesford, Hemmingly, &amp; Duninton: licet non habuit nisi</hi> xxxv. <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratas, &amp;</hi> x. <hi>solidatas. Quia (ut dicunt) dicta terra non potest plus valere cum In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stauramento quod Comitissa ibi recepit; scili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet,</hi> v. <hi>Carucis,</hi> cccxli. <hi>ovibus,</hi> x. <hi>suibus,</hi> i, <hi>verre. Sed si in Duninton apponerentur</hi> cc. <hi>oves, &amp;</hi> x. <hi>sues, &amp;</hi> i. <hi>verris, tunc valeret.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>And from this Record, Sir <hi>Peter Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> tells us, that it clearly appears that the said <hi>Matilda</hi> or <hi>Maude</hi> was born, <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> 1135. and was aged fifty years, <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Domini,</hi> 1185. 31 <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. and that
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:64436:83"/>therefore Earl of <hi>Hugh</hi> could not be born till the year 1150. at soonest, and so could be but about six (or seven) years older than his Wife <hi>Bertred;</hi> and hereupon he says that he hath laid this Argument asleep for ever, which was brought from their great difference in age.</p>
                  <p>To which I answer, that this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is so far from proving clearly what Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> doth suppose it to prove, that it is of no force at all; for I shall yet make it manifest to all, that <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> was very many years elder than his Wife <hi>Bertred,</hi> and that <hi>Matilda</hi> her self was also of a far greater age than Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> from this Record doth suppose her to be; and therefore besides those three Reasons which I have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given, I shall also give these several Reasons to make good what I do here say:</p>
                  <p>And first, I desire the Reader to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, that though this Record tell us, that the age of <hi>Bertred</hi> was twenty nine years, in the 31 year of King <hi>Henry the Second,</hi> yet it doth not say that <hi>Matilda</hi>
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:64436:83"/>was aged fifty years at that time, but that she was then aged fifty years and more, which it might say, and say true, if the said <hi>Matilda</hi> had been ninety years of age <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that time.</p>
                  <p>And Secondly, I shall appeal to those who are versed in these matters, whether it be any strange thing to find a person said to be aged thirty years and more, or forty years and more, when they are really aged many years more, than that number of years which is particularly mentioned, and especially when the weaker Sex is concerned, and the age of the Party not material to the Case in hand.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, I desire the Reader to observe, how this new Argument of Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s doth clash with what he hath said be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; for in the 89 page of his first Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, he supposeth Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> either to be born in the year 1145. or in the year 1143. The first of which reckonings if <hi>Matilda</hi> was born in the year 1135. makes him to be born when his Mother was but ten years old, and the second reckoning makes him to be born, when his Mother was but 8 years old, so little did Sir <hi>Peter</hi> consider what he hath formerly said.</p>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:64436:84"/>
                  <p>Fourthly, What likelihood can there be, that <hi>Matilda</hi> was born in the year, 1135. since we find that she and her Son Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> sealed the Deed of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hale</hi> in the life-time of <hi>Eustace</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable, who, as appears before, was slain in the year, 1157. whereas by that reckoning <hi>Matilda</hi> her self could not have been one and twenty years of age, when she and her Son seared that Deed of <hi>Stivinghale,</hi> unless that Deed was sealed but about a year before the death of the said <hi>Eustace;</hi> for from the year, 1135. in which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> supposeth <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda</hi> to be born to the year 1157. in which <hi>Eustace</hi> was flain, is but two and twenty years.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, It is not likely that <hi>Matilda</hi> was so young as Sir <hi>Peter</hi> did conceive her to be, because as you may see in Mr. <hi>Selden</hi>'s <hi>Titles of Honor,</hi> printed at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> 1631. pag. 647. out of an old Rithmical Story attributed to one <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> of <hi>Gloucester,</hi> the Father and Mother of the said <hi>Matilda</hi> were married in the year, 1109. The Verses concerning the said Marriage are many, but the words
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:64436:84"/>as to the time of the Marriage are these:
<q>
                        <l>This was End leue hundred yeer and in the nith yeer right</l>
                        <l>After that vre Louerd was in his moder a hight.</l>
                     </q> Now if the said <hi>Matilda</hi> was born in the year, 1135. she then was not born till six and twenty years after the Marriage of her Father and Mother, which though possible, is yet very improbable so to be; indeed <hi>Stow</hi> in his <hi>Annals</hi> print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>London,</hi> 163.1. <hi>pag.</hi> 137.50. <hi>b.</hi> makes this Marriage in the year 1110. but he there mistakes the <hi>Christian</hi> Name of the Wife of the said <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Glouce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> and calls her <hi>Maude</hi> instead of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel;</hi> and for that reason, as also because the Author of the said Rithmical Story was first in time, he ought to be credited in this Point before Mr. <hi>Stow;</hi> however it could make but one year difference in time.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, If the said <hi>Maude,</hi> according to Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s fancy, was not born till the year, 1135. then, as Sir <hi>Peter</hi> himself
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:64436:85"/>confesseth in his <hi>Peroratio,</hi> pag. 78. Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> could not be imagined to be born till the year, 1150. at soonest; and if he was not born till the said year, 1150. he then would have been but one and thirty years of age, when he died; for as you may see in Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 134. he died in the year 1181. Now what likelihood is there that this Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> should be but one and thirty years of age when he died, seeing he had his Daughter <hi>Amicia</hi> marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his life-time to <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> and none knows how many years before the death of the said Earl.</p>
                  <p>Seventhly <hi>Speed</hi> in his History of <hi>Great-Brittain,</hi> printed 1632. <hi>pag.</hi> 473. <hi>a. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> in his Collection of the History of <hi>England,</hi> pag. 62. <hi>Polydore Virgil</hi> in his <hi>Histor. Anglic.</hi> put out by <hi>Thysius,</hi> and printed at <hi>Leyden,</hi> 1651. pag. 264. <hi>Matt. Paris,</hi> put out by Dr. <hi>Wats,</hi> and printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1640. p. 78. <hi>Henry Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> who lived in King <hi>Stephen</hi>'s time printed at <hi>Frankfurt,</hi> 1601. pag. 390. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Hoveden</hi> (who was, as <hi>Vossius</hi> says, <hi>Inter Domesticos Regis Henrici secundi</hi>) in the same Edition at <hi>Frankfurt,</hi> p. 485.
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:64436:85"/>
                     <hi>John Prior</hi> of <hi>Hagulstad,</hi> or <hi>Hexham,</hi> who lived in <hi>Henry the Second</hi>'s time, <hi>col.</hi> 269. <hi>John Brompton,</hi> col. 1030, (which two last were printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1652,) and <hi>Gulielmus Neubrigensis,</hi> who lived in King <hi>Richard the First,</hi> and King <hi>John</hi>'s time, in that Edition printed at <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> 1587. p. 363. and <hi>Ordericus Vitalis,</hi> who lived in King <hi>Stephen</hi>'s time. <hi>lib.</hi> 13. <hi>Eccles. Hist. pag.</hi> 921. and the Author of the Treatise called <hi>Chronica Normanniae,</hi> p. 978. do some of them in the year, 1141. and some of them sooner, (but occasionally onely) take notice of that relation of Father in Law, and Son in Law that was betwixt <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Gloucester,</hi> and <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter</hi> himself, as we may see in his <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> p. 121. and in his Answer to the <hi>Defence of Amicia,</hi> p. 48 and 49. doth acknowledge that some Authors do speak of that Relation, in the year 1139. Now the said <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> as Sir <hi>Peter</hi> says in his <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> was a Gallant Man at Arms, and took King <hi>Stephen</hi> prisoner in the year 1141. and he also was in the Field, and in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great danger in the year 1136. as we may see in the History written by <hi>Simeon
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:64436:86"/>Dunelmensis,</hi> and continued by <hi>John Prior</hi> of <hi>Hagulstad,</hi> col. 259. What likelihood therefore is there that he should be Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to the said <hi>Maude</hi> in the year 1139. which Sir <hi>Peter</hi> confesseth he was, if she was not born till the year 1135. especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally considering that none of the said Authors (that I can find) do tell us the time of their Marriage, or take any notice that she was a Child: Nay Mr. <hi>Daniel</hi> is so far from that, that he says the Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> left his Brother and Wife within the said Castle, to defend it, but the Earl of <hi>Chester</hi>'s name is there misprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, instead of <hi>Randle,</hi> he being called <hi>Ralph.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Eighthly, Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in his <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> p. 131 and 132. gives us this Deed following in these very words;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ROberto Dei gratia Lincolniensi Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copo, &amp; Capitulo sanctae Ecclesiae Lincolniae, toti{que} Clero illius Praesulatus, Hugo comes Cestriae Salutem. Necnon &amp; &amp; Constabulario, &amp; Dapifero, &amp; Baroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; Ministris, &amp; Famulis, &amp; Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inbus suis omnibus, tam Cleris, quam Laicis,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:64436:86"/>salutem similiter, vos scire volo, me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessisse &amp; confirmasse sancti-monialibus de Grenefelt illam terram quam Willielmus filius Otuheri eis in Elemosynam perpetuam dedit; quam vero pater meus Comes Ranul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus eis concessit Carta sua confirmatam: Ea propter volo &amp; praecipio, quod praefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae sanctimoniales terram illam perenniter bene &amp; quiete, &amp; libere habeant &amp; possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deant; Testibus Matilda Comitissa Matre mea, Simone silio Willielmi, Rogero Capel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lano, Ricard Capellano &amp; aliis multis; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Beltesford valete.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now this Deed being made by Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> without his Mother <hi>Matilda</hi> joining with him (she being only Witness to the said Deed) and it being sealed only with the Earls Seal (which said Seal Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth there describe) it will not I suppose be deny'd but that the said Earl was then at age when he sealed the said Deed; now there being at the time of the making of the said Deed a <hi>Robert</hi> Bishop of <hi>Lincolne</hi> living, and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no <hi>Robert</hi> who was Bishop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne</hi> during any of the time that the said <hi>Hugh</hi> was Earl, except <hi>Robert de Chis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ey,</hi> surnamed by some <hi>de Querceto,</hi> by others
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:64436:87"/>
                     <hi>Chesueto</hi> (which as Bishop <hi>Godwin</hi> says was all one, the one being drawn from the French, the other Latin, both signifying a Grove of Oaks) it will thereupon follow that this Deed was made whilst the said <hi>Robert de Chisuey</hi> was alive; now <hi>Gulielmus Nubrigensis</hi> printed at <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> 1587. pag. 398. and <hi>Matt. Westminster</hi> printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1570. <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 48. and several others tells us, that this <hi>Robert de Chisuey</hi> died in the year 1167. and Bishop <hi>Godwin,</hi> in that Edition print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>London,</hi> 1615. <hi>pag.</hi> 293. tells us the very day, and says it was <hi>January</hi> 8. 1167. And <hi>John Brompton,</hi> col. 1059. says it was in the 14 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. which agrees right with Bishop <hi>Godwin,</hi> if he reckon according to the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Account; Now if the said <hi>Matil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> had been born in the year 1135. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Sir <hi>Peter</hi>'s fancy, she would have been but about 32 years of age in the year 1167. If therefore that Deed had been made at the very time of the death of the said Bishop (which there is no reason to believe it was) yet the said <hi>Hugh</hi> being then at age, if his Mother had been born in the year, 1135. she must have had her Son <hi>Hugh</hi> when
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:64436:87"/>she her self was but about eleven years old, which is unreasonable to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, and therefore we may safely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude she was born many years before.</p>
                  <p>Ninthly, If you look into the first Part of Sir <hi>William Dugdale</hi>'s <hi>Baronage of</hi> England, <hi>pag.</hi> 40. we shall find him speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Record (of which I have now a Copy) which shews, that in 10 <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> was one of those Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Lords who came to an accord with the King for their ancient Liberties. Now the tenth year of King <hi>Henry the Second</hi> falling out part of it in the year 1163. and part of it in the year 1164. (in which latter year the said Record is dated) the said <hi>Matilda,</hi> if she had been born in the year 1135. would have been then but about Nine and twenty years old; and who can imagine that any man should have been employed or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in so great a Concern, whose Mother was then no more than Nine and twenty years of age.</p>
                  <p>Tenthly, If we look in that Treatise which is called <hi>Gesta Stephani Regis, pag.</hi> 952. which Treatise was written by a Contemporary, though an unknown
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:64436:88"/>Author, and is bound up with <hi>Orderi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Vitalis</hi> in that Edition printed at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> 1619. Although the said Treatise be imperfect, and have two leaves wanting in that very place, yet we may there find enough to shew that the said <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda</hi> (who was the only Wife of the said Earl <hi>Randle</hi>) must need be born long before the year 1135. for as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears there, a little before the besieging of <hi>Lincolne</hi> Castle (which Siege as appears by other Authors, as also by Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> in his <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 121 &amp; 122. was in the year 1141.) the said Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> was in <hi>Lincolne</hi> Castle with his Wife and Sons; and how could the said Earl at that time have Sons, if <hi>Matilda,</hi> who was his only Wife was then but six years of age; The words of the said Treatise are these;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plurimo itaque evoluto tempore, cum nec comes solito devotiùs Regi pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reret, cumque in Lincolnensi</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note>
                     <hi>cum uxore &amp; filiis commorans castello, civibus &amp; affinibus dira injungere, cives Regi privatim &amp; occultè nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is destinatis, ut ad Comitem cum su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:64436:88"/>suffragiis obsidendum quam festinus adesset, cum multa supplicatione saepiùs mandarunt. Rex autem repente &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provisè adveniens, à civibus susceptus, castellum evacuatum penèinvenit; exceptis uxore &amp; fratre Comitis, paucis{que} eorum suffraganeis, quos idem Rege civitatem su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beunte ibi relinquens, vix à castello solus effugit. Rege ita{que} constanter &amp; animose castellum obsidente, quique includebantur balistis, &amp; aliis diversi studii machinis gravissimè infestante, Comes Cestriae, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datis Roberto Comite Glaorniae, sed &amp; Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, &amp; omnibus, qui se in Regem arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; sed &amp; Walensium gravi secum &amp; intolerabili conducta multitudine, unà om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes conspiratione, imò &amp; concordi animo ad Regem expugnandum pariter convene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Erat autem festivus Purificationis dies, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that you here see that the same <hi>Comes</hi> or Earl, who is said to be then in <hi>Lincoln</hi> Castle, <hi>cum uxore &amp; filiis,</hi> is the same Earl, that fled out of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, and left there his Wife and Brother, and came again with several men out of <hi>Cheshire</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> and that the said Earl who did so was the Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> we
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:64436:89"/>find in most Historians, and also in Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi>'s <hi>Historical Antiquities,</hi> pag. 122. so that hence also it is very clear that <hi>Matilda</hi> was not born in the year 1135. for she could not be Mother of several Children when she was but about six years of age.</p>
                  <p>Eleventhly, <hi>William Malmesbury</hi> in that Edition printed at <hi>Frankfurt,</hi> 1601. in the second Book of that which he calls his <hi>Historia Novella,</hi> pag. 186. in the year, 1142. thus writes, <hi>Rex Stephanus ante Natale à Lindocolina provincia pacifice ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesserat, Comitem{que} Cestrensem, &amp; ejus fratrem honoribus auxerat. Is Comes filiam Comitis Glocestrensis,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note>
                     <hi>jamdudum a tempore Regis Henrici duxerat.</hi> Now this Author as to his Testimony is beyond all exception, for he lived in the time of the said Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> and <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>de,</hi> and cannot be supposed to be ignorant when their Marriage was; for he was well known to <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Glocester,</hi> Father of the said <hi>Maud,</hi> and dedicated his said Book called <hi>Historia Novella,</hi> as also his Book <hi>de Gestis Regum Anglorum,</hi> to the said Earl; and as his words can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not possibly be otherwise construed than
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:64436:89"/>so, as to make the said Marriage to be at the least in the year, 1135. (King <hi>Henry the First</hi> dying the second of <hi>December</hi> in that year) so no one can imagine but that the said <hi>Maud</hi> was born long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that year, there being no probability that <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> who was so brave a Man, should marry a new born Child; but there is no doubt but that the meaning of those words are, that the said <hi>Randle</hi> married the said <hi>Maude</hi> some years before the death of King <hi>Henry the First,</hi> and consequently before the time that Sir <hi>Peter</hi> doth suppose the said <hi>Maude</hi> to be born; for as Mr. <hi>Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> tells us in his Dictionary, the Letter <hi>A, prima significatione connotat terminum loci unde aliquid movetur, ut redeo a villa, &amp;c. hinc ad alia transfertur, ut notet causam agentem, unde sit motus, &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, unde proceditur, &amp; declaratur per cùm; ut, a parvo te novi, h. e. cum par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus esses.</hi> And accordingly we say in the <hi>English</hi> Tongue, <hi>I knew such a one from a Child,</hi> (that is) <hi>I knew him when he was a Child,</hi> so that the aforesaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmesbury,</hi> doth not exclude, but include some of the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the I.</p>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:64436:90"/>
                  <p>Twelfthly, <hi>Gulielmus Gemiticensis,</hi> who lived in the times of <hi>William</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, <hi>William Rufus,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the I. and some part of King <hi>Steven,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently was living when the said <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda</hi> was married, will give us very good satisfaction in the point in hand; this <hi>Willielmus Gemiticensis,</hi> as you may see in <hi>Vossius</hi>'s Book, <hi>de Historicis Latinis,</hi> and in <hi>Willielmus Gemiticensis</hi>'s own Books, did write six Books <hi>de Gestis Normanno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> and dedicate them to <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, and did afterwards add a 7<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Book, in which he did write some little of <hi>William Rufus,</hi> but more largely of King <hi>Henry</hi> the I. whose death (which hapned <hi>Decemb.</hi> 2. 1135.) he declares, but writes of nothing later than the year 1137. and in that year he only speaks of the death of some great persons, and some few inconsiderable things. Now it cannot (as I think) be probably supposed, that this <hi>Gulielmus Gemiticensis</hi> could be less than 30 years of age, when he had finished his first six Books <hi>de gestis Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannorum,</hi> and dedicated them to <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the Conqueror: And if that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the last year of the said King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi>
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:64436:90"/>the said <hi>Wilhelmus Gemeticensis</hi> would be 30 years of age in the year 1087. (for in that year <hi>William</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror dyed) and by this computation the said <hi>Gulielm. Gemit.</hi> would be 80 years of age, when he finished his last Book in the year 1137. which is the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most time that we find him to write. Now the said <hi>Wilhelmus Gemiticensis,</hi> in that Edition put out by M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Cambden,</hi> and printed at <hi>Frankfurt,</hi> 1603 in his last Book, and 38 <hi>Chapter,</hi> in that very <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> where he tells us of the death of King <hi>Henry</hi> the I. and how King <hi>Stephen</hi> suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him, (which things hapned in the year 1135.) doth thus write:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mortuo autem Ranulpho</hi> (this was the first Earl <hi>Randle</hi> of <hi>Chester</hi>) <hi>successit ei item Ranulphus filius ejus, vir in rebus bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis strenuus. Hujus autem Ranulphi so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorem duxit Richardus filius Gisleberti, ex qua suscepit tres filios, Ipse denique Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardus peremptus est à Walensibus ut prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixum est, Praedictus autem Ranulphus Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes accepit uxorem Mathildem filiam Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berti Comitis Glocestriae, ex qua genuit duos filios</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note>
                     <hi>Hugonem &amp; Richardum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:64436:91"/>
                  <p>Now how can it be imagined, that this old <hi>Wilhelmus Gemiticensis,</hi> who did write but to 1137, should in the same <hi>Chapter</hi> that he tells us of the death of King <hi>Henry</hi> the I. (which hapned in the year 1135.) tell us of <hi>Hugh</hi> and <hi>Richard,</hi> the two Sons of the said <hi>Matilda,</hi> if the said <hi>Matilda</hi> was not born till the year 1135.</p>
                  <p>And these words of <hi>Wilhelmus Gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticensis,</hi> besides what they prove them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, do also strongly confirm what <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radocus Lancaruensis</hi> (the before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned contemporary Author) had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly said; For if the said <hi>Hugh,</hi> the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of those Sons, was five years old in that year, that the said <hi>Gulielmus Gemiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>censis</hi> doth mention the said <hi>Hugh</hi> and his younger Brother <hi>Richard,</hi> the said <hi>Hugh</hi> would then be as old as I suppose him to be, in that year in which the said <hi>Carado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> says that the said <hi>Hugh</hi> fortified his Castle of <hi>Cymaron,</hi> and wan <hi>Melyenith</hi> to himself.</p>
                  <p>So that there is no doubt at all, but that <hi>Hugh Cyvelioc</hi> himself was several
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:64436:91"/>years older, than Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> doth suppose <hi>Matilda</hi> the Mother of the said <hi>Hugh Cyvelioc</hi> to be, and by consequence there must be a vast difference betwixt the age of the said <hi>Hugh,</hi> and the said <hi>Bertred,</hi> who was second Wife of the said <hi>Hugh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Baddeley,</hi>
                        <date>May 22. 1677.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>